<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hypocrisie discovered in its nature and workings. Delivered in several sermons, by that faithfull minister of the Gospell, Mr Cuthbert Sidenham, late teacher to a Church of Christ in Newcastle upon Tyne.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 117 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1504_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867595</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119912</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119912)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1504[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hypocrisie discovered in its nature and workings. Delivered in several sermons, by that faithfull minister of the Gospell, Mr Cuthbert Sidenham, late teacher to a Church of Christ in Newcastle upon Tyne.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 212, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.H. for Rich. Tomlins, at the Sun and Bible in Pye-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: [the] 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hypocrisy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HYPOCRISIE DISCOVERED In its NATURE and WORKINGS.</p>
            <p>Delivered in ſeveral Sermons, By That faithfull Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, Mr <hi>Cuthbert Sidenham,</hi> Late Teacher to a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. H.</hi> for <hi>Rich. Tomlins,</hi> at the Sun and Bible in <hi>Pye-Corner,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:2"/>
            <head>For the Honourable, Sir <hi>Arthur Heſilrig,</hi> Knight and Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu that have ſo long profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and have been honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſuffer for him in no ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trials, and been drawn out to great employments, cannot but have met with various workings of your own heart in theſe times, eſpecially having gone both through good and evill report, all which will diſcover much of that
<pb facs="tcp:119912:3"/> which is within a man to himſelf; this being upon our ſpirits (with the more than ordinary reſpects you ſhewed to this precious ſervant of Chriſt, the Author of theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons) hath drawn us out to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix your name to this worke, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to beare witneſſe to the world (though he be in his grave) how much he reſented your favour and love towards him. Sir, the matter of this Book you will find very ſearching, but Gold loſeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the criticall examination of the fire but its droſſe, which no reall Saint but will rejoyce to part with. We queſtion not but in the reading of it you will find ſpeciall advantages for your ſpirituall inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for the teachings of the ſpirit of that God who hath hitherto helped
<pb facs="tcp:119912:3"/> you, who was with you in the field and covered your head in the day of battell, who made you a reall terrour to the enemies of his Son Ieſus in this Nation, and did by the good hand of his providence bring you among us when his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were very high and turbulent by your courage and faithfulneſs to calme and bring them under, who alſo drew out your heart to ſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall a proofe of your reall deſire to ſerve Ieſus Chriſt every way, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Inſtrument to procure the three yeares Commiſsion for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the Goſpell in theſe foure Northerne Counties. Theſe things we mention as that which hath laid engagements upon our hearts towards you; Oh, that you may yet go on and proſper, and do more
<pb facs="tcp:119912:4"/> worthily for God and his people, that your enemies may be found lyars, that after your many trials God may cleare up your integrity, that you may be as the light of the morning, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.4. Sir, we have this only to beg of you, look whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God in all, and walke humbly and cloſe with him, and learne that of the Apoſtle, he is only approved whom God approveth, thus will you engage the Saints more and more, and us to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the ſervice of the Goſpell.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Tho. Weld,</item>
                     <item>Sam. Hamond,</item>
                     <item>Tho. Trurin,</item>
                     <item>Wil. Durant.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:4"/>
            <head>To all that profeſſe the name of the Lord Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle, ſpeaking of the laſt daies, cals them perilous times, or as the word is, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult times, not ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the formality and hypocriſie of many that ſhall then profeſſe the Goſpell, and as in other propheſies the fullest opening of the book is the event of providences made out to Saints by the Spirit of God, ſo in this the ſad influences that the hypocriſie and formality of Profeſſours hath had upon the Saints in theſe laſt daies, make us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand where the perill and difficulty lies; and the reaſon why the Apoſtle ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:119912:5"/> make it matter of prophecy and of imminent danger and difficulty to the Saints who ſhall converſe among them, how ſoon was <hi>Peter,</hi> that great Apoſtle, leavened with hypocriſie, and <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo carried away with that diſſimulation, <hi>(Gal. 2.12, 13.)</hi> though men otherwiſe full of the Holy Ghoſt? And have not we ground to thinke that the ſleeping of the fooliſh virgins will be no ſmall temptation to the wiſe to ſlumber alſo, as Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in that Parable, <hi>Mat 25.</hi> How hard is it to touch pitch and not be defiled? Oh that the danger of this, ſo clearely held out by Christ and his Apoſtles, might leave a more powerfull impreſſion upon the hearts of the Saints to be very circumſpect where they are neceſſitated, to have their converſation among the deceitfull ſpirits of theſe times, we meane, men having the forme of godlineſſe, but not the power of it; whoever of you are obſervers of your own hearts, ſurely you have ſometimes found with what inſinuating po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the miſcarriages of ſome eminent profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors have crept into your hearts, and led you away into divers fooliſh luſts; Can you look back upon your walkings, for theſe ten yeares
<pb facs="tcp:119912:5"/> paſt, without regret of ſoule to review the many ſecret apoſtaſies of your hearts from Chriſt? Doth not ſo many of your unholy walkings, as you may find in the ſearchings of your ſoules, put you upon more thorow and ſtrict examination, whether this root of bitterneſſe do not ſpring up and trouble you? It would ſtagger a man to conſider what an aptneſſe there is in many profeſſors moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to comply with, if not fully to act the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate miſcarriages of this preſent evill world; ſhould holy <hi>Baynes,</hi> or <hi>Rogers,</hi> or <hi>Greenham</hi> ariſe from the dead, and take a view of ſome of the now-profeſſors of <hi>England,</hi> who pretend to far clearer diſcoveries of the Goſpell than they lived under; would not they bleſſe the Lord, that their portion was not caſt to live in thoſe wicked daies? ſhould they ſee the loathſome faſhions of many of you with powdered haire, painted faces, naked breaſts, and ſuch phantaſtick garbes, that yet would go for choice Saints and Chriſtians, would not they mourne in ſecret over theſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and cry out, oh the hypocriſie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe of your ſpirits, and tell you, your light is darkneſſe, and that you are thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:119912:6"/> which do hold the truth of God in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe? Hath not Satan hence taken his ground to oppoſe the truths of Chriſt, and to ſpeake evill of the good waies of God? Doth not the Quakers naturall conſcience (for that is his light and Chriſt within him) put him upon laying aſide the ordinances, and divers other principles of the Goſpell, becauſe he ſees ſo many of you living ſo much in pride, and luſts of the fleſh, and walking according to the vanity of your minds, yet pleading for them under a pretence of Gospell-liberty? Doth not the Arminian make that one of his great Arguments for the Apoſtacy of the Saints, becauſe ſo many of you pretending to be ſuch, grow ſo looſe and vaine at laſt, and after you have pretended by the knowledge of Chriſt to have eſcaped the pollutions of the world, are again intangled therein and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, <hi>2 Pet. 2.20.</hi> may he not be hardened by this generation, in his opinion, if that no ſpecificall difference betwixt temporary and ſaving grace; becauſe many under the bare authority of reſtraining grace come up to as high conformity to the Goſpell as you do, who yet would be taken as the great profeſſors of
<pb facs="tcp:119912:6"/> it? Do not you obſerve how many, alledging to be ſcandalized by your walkings, are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to embrace the groſs Abomination of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery? And however the goodneſs of our God hath been abundantly held forth in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that glorious light of the Goſpell which hath, and doth yet ſhine among us, yet it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that the Lord hath given up very many to walke after their fooliſh hearts lusts, and to embrace deluſions through their not walking cloſe with God under theſe diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; Oh at what a high rate do you ſin, that are profeſsors, who live thus, and walke car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally under ſo holy a Goſpell as that of our glorious Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Brethren, though we thus ſpeake, yet we may not but faithfully witneſſe, to the praiſe of our bleſſed Lord, that our lines are fallen into better places, where our ſoules are not vexed with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding ſuch folly and abominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thoſe that do profeſſe the Goſpell; neither our Congregations peſtered with ſuch ſpots of vanity: yet our deare Brother, the Author of theſe Sermons, doubtleſſe not without a ſecret impulſe of the bleſſed Spirit, was moved to be ſo large in opening the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:119912:7"/> and workings of Hypocriſie; for Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie hath its ſeverall formes, and dreſſes, and may lye for a while undiſcovered in the hearts and duties of the moſt reall Saints, but where it workes moſt ſecretly and ſubtilly there it requires a more quick eye, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand to the anatomizing of it, which we can without flatery ſay, God had eminently beſtowed upon him, of whom, to you that know him not, we ſhall give this briefe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; He was trained up under Religious education from his Childhood, which made him often profeſs his jealouſie of Profeſsors, eſpecially ſuch who had the advantage of a godly education, through the many experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the deceits of his own heart, his ſpeciall inſight into the myſteries of Christ, as you may obſerve by his Sermons upon <hi>1 Tim. 3. ult.</hi> publiſhed by himſelfe a little before his death; his judicious and drawing diſcoveries of the riches of grace, which if the Lord pleaſe we ſhall hereafter ſhew to you, where you may ſee his tender bowels toward the poorest ſoules under any of the workings of God, his unwearied paines, even to the viſible waſting of his owne bodily
<pb facs="tcp:119912:7"/> ſtrength in the work of the Miniſtery, and his great care over the Flock over which the Holy Ghoſt had made him overſeer, all of theſe did beſpeake him a veſsell fitted for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters uſe, and it is not unknown to thoſe in chiefeſt places his otherwiſe uſefulneſs to the people of God in this Nation, thus did he ſerve his generation with theſe many talents his God had furniſhed him with, and for theſe few Sermons we can only ſay, you have them as they were taken from his mouth in his ordinary Miniſtery, without any alteration, which is enough to exciſe the often inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted expreſſions you meet with in them, they were the laſt of his publike exerciſes among us, and now for the uſefulneſs of them we ſhall ſay:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That here you ſhall find out the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings of the ſubtilleſt hypocrite in all his formes and duties, even to his greateſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of communion with God, for the devil hath not had a ſtronger hold in theſe daies for the carrying on the moſt terrible actings of profaneneſs, as lying, cheating, pride, and luſt, and the like, than by a pretence to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in light and love: we do not
<pb facs="tcp:119912:8"/> without ſhame and griefe of heart mention thoſe things, but God will have them ſearched out.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Here thou wilt find, if a true Saint, how much of the Leven of Hypocriſie is yet work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in thy own heart; and is not this a mercy indeed to have theſe ſpreading iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties diſcovered, as <hi>Pſal. 139.23. Try me, O God, and know my heart: prove me, and examine my thoughts,</hi> and ſee if there be any way of wickedneſſe in me.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Here is a ground of eſtabliſhment to the moſt diſcouraged reall Saint againſt the feares of hypocriſie, and how neceſſary is this for poore weake ſoules who are (how ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſoever, yet) often tempted to conclude themſelves but very hypocrites; we have but one word more, and that is to thoſe profeſſors that walke in the fellowſhip of the Goſpell, to put them in mind that the veſſels of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle were of pure gold, <hi>Exod. 25.29, 31,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the diſhes, ſpoons, bowles, candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, tonges, ſnuffers, were all by Gods command of pure gold;</hi> and then to read the proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſie of Church-members in the laſt daies, <hi>Zech. 14.20, 21. The pots in the
<pb facs="tcp:119912:8"/> Lords houſe ſhall be like the bowles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, yea, every pot in Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and in Judah ſhall be holineſſe to the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> ſo will the Lord be ſerved in the beauties of holineſſe, and his Churches will be the praiſe of the whole earth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119912:9"/>Hypocriſie diſcovered in its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Workings.</head>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <head>SERMON I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke <hi>12. latter end of the firſt verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beware ye of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypocriſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU ſhall find, in the former Chapter, Chriſt charging of the Phariſees for their unſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table actings unto the rule, notwithſtanding all their profeſſion, and pronouncing woes againſt them of all ſorts of people: And here he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119912:10"/> takes occaſion upon the addreſſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to open thoſe things further, and to apply what he had ſaid unto them; <hi>When he ſaw a multitude of people,</hi> many people gathered together, <hi>inſomuch that they trode one upon another, he began to preach and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto them;</hi> and this is the firſt Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he gave them, an admonition that they ſhould <hi>take heed of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypocriſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by <hi>leaven</hi> here of the Phariſees, ſome take the <hi>doctrine</hi> of them to be meant: but you know Chriſt tels them in another place (<hi>Math.</hi> 23.2, 3.) <hi>they ſit in</hi> Moſes <hi>chaire, all therefore whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and doe:</hi> Yet certainly it may be taken for their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine here likewiſe, for they did manage their doctrine with hypocriſie, and did not plainly and clearly open the nature of thoſe things the Law ſpake of. But chiefly and eſpecially is meant here by <hi>the leaven of them,</hi> i.e. <hi>thoſe private and particular doctrines</hi> that they gave out from their <hi>owne</hi> Sect, from their <hi>own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular judgment:</hi> For when they expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119912:10"/> the Law, ſo far as it referred to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Lord Jeſus gave them a warrant to heare them; but they have <hi>private inſtructions,</hi> and <hi>practices</hi> that will be as <hi>leaven</hi> to corrupt you, if you be not very exact. I need not to comment upon it, for my deſigne is only to open the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> and diſcover it to you both <hi>in the Churches</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>and up and down the world.</hi> And I have choſen this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Jeſus Chriſt: now it's mighty <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall</hi> to conſider, who are the <hi>perſons</hi> he picks out, as who are the <hi>ſubjects</hi> of this admonition; The <hi>Phariſees,</hi> the <hi>ſtricteſt</hi> Sect among the Jewes, thoſe that had the <hi>greateſt name of Religion,</hi> that did moſt <hi>exactly (outwardly)</hi> follow all the rules that the Law ſeemes to command; they were expounders of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law (to give you but a ſhort hint of their life and actings) they gave themſelves up wholly to it: ſo you ſhall find up and downe all the New Teſtament, they were <hi>ſequestred perſons</hi> from all ſorts of men, muſt not be ſo much <hi>as touched by any:</hi> For ſo it ſeems there when the poore woman came to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119912:11"/> Chriſt, <hi>and touched the hemme of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> they wondred that Chriſt would ſuffer himſelfe to be touched by her being a ſinner; they were ſo exact, that they would have no legall pollution upon them, they would not eat a bit of meat untill they waſhed, eſpecially at a Faſt, then ſome of them would even goe to waſh their whole bodies, for feare any pollution ſhould fall upon them; they were ſo exact, that they counted all men but themſelves to be ſinners: theſe things you ſhall find up and downe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I need not name the places; they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes were faſting twice a weeke, would not touch any meat, ſo exact that they wore <hi>ſchedules</hi> about their armes and necks, whereon the Law was written, the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>poſitive</hi> Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo exact were they, as to outward appearance humbling themſelves on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſo that they ſeemed to be moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act (<hi>Paul</hi> was of the <hi>ſame</hi> Sect which he gloried of) and yet the moſt hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and unworthy generation of men that ever were, and the greateſt enemies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119912:11"/> of Chriſt that ever he had, and there's none he gave that bitter language to as to them.</p>
            <p>They did ever endeavour theſe two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, To <hi>intrap</hi> and intangle him with with their queſtions, to make him ſpeake ſomething contrary to the Law.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, To <hi>blurr him</hi> if they could, to put a <hi>publique blot</hi> upon him before the people, and ſuch a kind of calumny that they might all hate him; therefore the greateſt woes that <hi>Chriſt</hi> pronounces are againſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to goe no further, obſerve only this;</p>
            <p>Obſ. <hi>The more outwardly Religious men are, without ſpirituall Principles, the more dangerous they are to converſe withall:</hi> there's a <hi>leaven</hi> in them, there are no ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo dangerous to converſe with the Saints as theſe, a man is gone <hi>inſenſibly,</hi> and taken <hi>inſenſibly</hi> with theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he knowes where he is; the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the perſon takes hold on his heart: Can ſuch a perſon be ſo and ſo? he is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119912:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119912:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119912:13"/> rather fit for heaven then earth, and ſo a man ſucks in all the venome of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and opinions; and ſo it was with thoſe that went about to be falſe Apoſtles, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 <hi>chap.</hi> they went about <hi>cunningly</hi> to deale with men, and they gained <hi>excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly;</hi> and I am confident that in theſe latter dayes more have been deceived by the ſeeming profeſſion of men ſpeaking <hi>great things,</hi> and lifted up high in eſteeme then by any otherway, as they ſpeak lyes ſecretly and with hypocriſie; all their actings, and all they did was but hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
            <p>But the thing I ſhall come to, is to open hypocriſie: Now that which I ſhall ſhew in the generall, is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, what <hi>hypocriſie</hi> is? what the <hi>nature</hi> of it is? 2. and the ſeverall <hi>ſorts</hi> of it. 3. how it <hi>acts?</hi> 4. what the <hi>characters</hi> of hypocrites are, how they paſſe through all ſorts of duties?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyprocriſie</hi> may be conſidered theſe two wayes:</p>
            <p>Firſt, as oppoſed unto the <hi>reality</hi> of the worke of the Goſpell in a mans heart, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119912:13"/> oppoſed unto what's reall in a man, that's hypocriſie, when I have an appearance of what I have not; that's the firſt thing. I doe, it may be, conceive I have this and that which I have not, and ſo hypocriſie lyes in a <hi>defect</hi> of thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> that ſhould be in a man, it's oppoſed unto that reall worke in a mans ſoule, when I act thoſe things outwardly that I have no reall foundation for in my owne heart, pray, and preach, and heare, and doe all duties that are ſuitable to the will of God, and no reality of theſe things in my owne heart, nothing within but the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of my naturall affections, and the like; when as a man hath not that clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of judgement to diſcerne his owne ſtate, and hath not that within him that is reall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hypocriſie is oppoſed to that <hi>inward ſimplicity of heart and intention</hi> in a mans ſpirit, when I doe profeſſe that which I doe not intend, that's hypocriſie; when I doe that in the Goſpell which my intentions are not reall in, and yet my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions may be reall in the things I doe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119912:14"/> but I have not a reality in the principle: but this is the groſſeſt ſort of hypocriſie, when it is oppoſed to that <hi>ſingleneſſe</hi> of ſincerity and intention; they are as Stage-players, act the part of them they know they are not. A man doth out of ſhew and vanity faigne himſelfe to be that which he is not; this is the ſecond ſort of hypocriſie, when I would be counted ſo for ſtrictneſſe and holineſſe that I am not, and there's now in the very inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſoule hypocriſie. But hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie may be without the intention, where there is not that ſpoken of in the 1 <hi>Philip.</hi> 10. that you may be <hi>ſincere,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is a very large word, and ſignifies that cleare judgement a man ſhould have, as if he were <hi>tryed by the beames of the Sun.</hi> Now though there be ſincerity as to <hi>intention,</hi> yet there may be hypocriſie as to the <hi>defect</hi> of the reality that ſhould be in a mans ſoule.</p>
            <p>So that from theſe two conſiderations in generall, you may ſee that hypocrites may be of thoſe ſorts.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119912:14"/>
            <p>Firſt, a man may be an hypocrite and may <hi>not know it;</hi> he may go on in all ſorts of duties of Religion, and do all things <hi>exactly</hi> according <hi>to the letter</hi> of the Law, and do it with <hi>integrity</hi> in his <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as he <hi>thinks,</hi> not knowing that he doth it out of any falſe intention, hath not that cunningneſſe to deceive (as I ſhall ſhew you by and by,) not ſo cunning a hypocrite as one who deales from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward wickedneſſe of his heart, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to deceive: but yet he goes on, and never had the worke of God upon his ſoule; he follows on the outward Letter of the Law, goes on in a <hi>drudging</hi> way, he finds ſome naturall propenſity in his ſpirit to it from ingenuity, and common principles which are left in him by the Goſpell: ſo a man may be long in duties, (<hi>Paul</hi> was ſo) he profeſſeth, that what he did was out of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. he did not know he was an hypocrite, he had no deſigne to deceive the world, and to deceive himſelfe, he thought he was an exact man, and carried it as clearely as could be, he had no deſigne but to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119912:15"/>propagate his own principles, and he was above all the Phariſees, therefore he puts down himſelfe as the moſt zealous of them, and ſurely he had a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention as to his own thoughts, as <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne</hi> he was, as it were, an <hi>innocent</hi> hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite. And ſurely ſo it was with the <hi>fooliſh Virgins, Mat.</hi> 25. they went on <hi>ſmoothly</hi> a long time, and <hi>ſlumbred,</hi> and ſlept, and thought themſelves as pure Virgins as the wiſe untill <hi>midnight</hi> came. And the <hi>young man</hi> in the Goſpell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. he came to Chriſt with a confidence in his own intentions, that he had kept the Law, or elſe he would never have come to Chriſt as he did, but yet he <hi>lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſomething,</hi> he wanted the maine principle, he wanted <hi>ſelfe-deniall,</hi> never knew what it was to caſt himſelfe upon the Lord Jeſus purely: All his hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie lay in that. If there be but a <hi>naturall ingenuity</hi> and <hi>ſimplicity,</hi> and it come under the Goſpell, it will be mightily impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a mans following the <hi>outward Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of it, he will be as <hi>ſimple-hearted</hi> in all duties, as much as formerly he was by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119912:15"/> following the common principles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty: therefore when the <hi>young man</hi> came to Chriſt, there was a kind of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Jeſus Chriſt to him, and a love to him, and yet this was his hypocriſie; he did all thoſe things, and had no inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all to deceive the world or him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by it, but he wanted the <hi>principle</hi> that ſhould have carried him on in all things: So that a man appeares to be what he is not, appeares to be a Saint, and does duties well, but is not, this comes from a want of principles, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in that; <hi>It is not my intention that makes me a hypocrite before God,</hi> but if I go on in profeſſion, and have not what ſhould make out that profeſſion to be from God, it is hypocriſie. Only theſe are the moſt to be pittied and bewailed that go innocently to hell; they thinke they have grace, and no man in the world can perſwade them to the contrary, and as ſtrong a faith as any in the world, and alas they have not; they thinke they love Chriſt, and would do any thing for him, but they never had that love flaming in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119912:16"/> them from the power of divine love, and ſpirituall Goſpell-principles.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſons why men go on thus are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe they never had the <hi>ſight</hi> of their own <hi>natures;</hi> they never were under the <hi>through</hi>-convictions of their <hi>ſinfull ſtate by nature,</hi> only bred up <hi>faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>ingenuouſly</hi> in the Goſpell; God never ſhewed them their own faces in the glaſſe of the Law, only they have looked on the Law with their own eye, in their own proſpect; it is impoſſible, if God ſhewed a man his nature, he ſhould go without principles in his heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It comes from a <hi>generall view</hi> of the Goſpell, meerly from <hi>generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and <hi>outward rule,</hi> without any <hi>particular inward ſenſe of the ſpirit</hi> and <hi>frame</hi> that ſhould be in him: men looke upon the Goſpell as a Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and never come to ſee what ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all frames ſhould be in their hearts to every duty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Men do find ſome kind of <hi>comfort</hi> in thoſe waies, and they have not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119912:16"/> thoſe <hi>checks of conſcience</hi> that others have, becauſe they are not ſo <hi>groſſe</hi> in their actings, but go on <hi>ſmoothly,</hi> without <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning</hi> their own ſtate, and their ſpirits are pretty well compoſed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The maine and the great reaſon is <hi>want of through-examination,</hi> want of <hi>diving</hi> into the <hi>depths</hi> of the heart, not putting a mans ſelfe to it every day, men take up meerly the <hi>imitation,</hi> as it were, of others, and the <hi>ſhadow,</hi> and the outward <hi>expreſſion,</hi> and conſider them no otherwaies, whereas they are but ſhews; men never go no further in their own ſpirits than the outſides, never ſearch their hearts to lay them open before the Majeſty and Authority of a great God, and ſo they live and dye ſecurely. And is not this a ſad thing, that a man ſhould thinke he hath grace, and have no inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all to deceive? That is, he hath not that cunning and deſperate frame, but only goes on and truſts his own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and truſts his own generall appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and hopes well of himſelfe, and thinkes ſurely he would do no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119912:17"/> wrong, do no evill, and this man ſlips down, and away to the bottome of hell; <hi>here is a hypocrite, though not a profeſſed one,</hi> he is <hi>deceived,</hi> though he intend not to <hi>deceive,</hi> for here is that I would have you look to.</p>
            <p>☞ It is not your <hi>thinking</hi> and <hi>ſaying</hi> you have grace, you may be hypocrites for all that, if you are not what you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be: you are a hypocrite what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you ſeeme to be, and whether you think ſo or no. <hi>God thinkes</hi> ſo, and <hi>know's</hi> ſo, and you will find it ſo one day, when you come to have the vaile taken off from your eyes; <hi>Paul</hi> wondred what he was a doing when God opened his eyes, what he had been doing all this while. Therefore you had need be <hi>trying</hi> your hearts every day, dayly fearing your hearts, and jealous over your ſpirits, and ſuſpecting every motion, untill you have tried your hearts by Law and Goſpell, yea, and waited upon the Spirit for a new triall.</p>
            <p>Now there is a <hi>ſecond ſort,</hi> and they are ſuch as are conſcious to themſelves of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119912:17"/> their hypocriſie, that they are not yet <hi>ſound</hi> in the <hi>maine,</hi> and yet go on in their profeſſion from their education, or for ſome <hi>deſigne,</hi> and cannot leave it, have many ſtirrings of God in their hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Ordinances from light convictions of the Lord upon their Spirits. And this is <hi>exceeding common,</hi> many go on a long time in profeſſion and cannot leave it, but have many motions of God in their ſoules, and many ſharpe reproofes from God, and yet cannot ſee a through work upon their hearts, yet go on and profeſſe, and hope it may be, but take themſelves for Saints continually, and muſt have their names enrolled for Saints in Churches, and yet have a jealouſie of their own hypocriſie, and go on ſo for many yeares under many <hi>regrets</hi> and <hi>wounds</hi> of ſpirit; they have many <hi>twangs</hi> that pierce them ſometimes, and yet the Conviction is not ſo <hi>ſtrong</hi> as to ſhew them their <hi>miſerable and vile eſtate,</hi> or to preſſe them on to the through worke of the Goſpell upon their hearts. And you ſhall find thoſe perſons very <hi>high in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119912:18"/> and <hi>very able to ſpeake well</hi> in their converſe with Saints: But they never met with God in duties, never had Gods aſſiſtance, never found that ſpirituall ſtrength; when they heare men <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing</hi> of ſoules, they are only for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the <hi>glorious outſide,</hi> and the glory of outward formes; they have been ſome ten or twenty years, and knew that Chriſt never appeared to them, and yet they cannot leave off duties, conſcience and the outward rule lies upon them ſtill: <hi>this is very common:</hi> And ſo it was with <hi>Saul,</hi> he knew in his own heart that God had forſaken him, and yet he would be doing ſomething, he would have <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray for him, but God had left him: he knew in his own conſcience he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, and had not done the will of God. And ſo a man may go up and down a great while, having a conſcience and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as to outward actings, and yet never be ſound: God improving a <hi>naturall light</hi> ſo far as to outward actings, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but do thoſe outward duties, and yet he knows in his conſcience that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119912:18"/> he never met with God, and if he do, it is only to tell him thou art not ſound, and ſometimes he breakes out in extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; theſe can find nothing in their hearts, but conſcience will be preſſing them on ſtill to keep up the forme. <hi>This is a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſoule.</hi> Certainely ſome men are <hi>ſelf-condemned,</hi> and it is impoſſible if ſo be a man have any ſtirrings of Conſcience, and live under the Miniſtry of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, but he will ſome time or other (if he be a hypocrite) have ſome diſcoveries of his owne heart, when he comes to prayer, there is not that working of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Adoption; God may leave a man ſo in a generall kind of way, that he may not at all ſet out thoſe convictions, but thoſe that have their conſciences convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of particular acts of ſin, when they turne Profeſſors they have often times conviction, as to thoſe acts, but let a man have never ſuch a daily hint that he is an hypocrite, yet it is no more to him to ſtrike him off his bottome and make him to be ſound, no more than if a man had a dayly ſenſe of ſin that he cannot get
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119912:19"/> mortified, and he finds convictions not ſo ſharpe but that he can go under them and live, (though ſometimes they are <hi>ſore</hi> to him) and ſtop the mouth of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. The Lords power comes not in with the Conviction; and certainely thoſe ſoules are mightily <hi>ſtartled</hi> ſoules, have mighty ſharpe convictions upon their ſpirits, but it is off againe, and they carry a generall kind of feare in their own hearts, but ſtill ſomething or other there is, and they muſt keep up: <hi>O take heed then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke to your own hearts, what ſecret hints you have of hypocriſie, you that have lived long under the Goſpell, been given much to duties, look to your own hearts, how many <hi>twangs</hi> have you had in the night-ſeaſon in your ſpirits? You never met with God in the duty, though you prayed well, and read well in the ſight of men, though you have carried it faire up and down the world: what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward regret have you had in your own ſpirits? This is a <hi>lamentable condition,</hi> for a man to be ſo a hypocrite, that a man
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119912:19"/> goes on under the conviction and cannot get from it, and yet goes on in duties ſtill. Now you have a third and laſt ſort, which is the groſſeſt ſort.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, <hi>a deſigning</hi> hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, one that takes up Religion for ſome <hi>particular deſigne,</hi> which he knows the deſigne of in his own heart, as to get <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> or <hi>profit,</hi> or the <hi>countenancing of ſome particular laſt,</hi> or whatever it be; meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that a man may cover ſome ſecret luſt, meerly to follow the opportunities and ſeaſons of the world: this is the <hi>groſſeſt</hi> of all: <hi>State</hi>-hypocrites, as I may ſo call them, thoſe that are only making uſe of the name of Religion on purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and <hi>begin all their evill in the name of God;</hi> theſe are the <hi>groſſeſt</hi> ſort that can be poſſibly. And there are ſeverall ſorts of theſe. Some that are more <hi>refined,</hi> as to be honoured among men, as <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> he would give any thing that he might have had the <hi>gift</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe he thought it was a brave thing to do <hi>miracles</hi> that he might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of among men, therefore he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119912:20"/> was in the <hi>Gall of bitterneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are a <hi>more refined ſort,</hi> which care not ſo much for outward kind of <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>honour,</hi> but they do follow on duties and the waies of God, meerly to <hi>quiet their conſciences</hi> upon ſome ſpeciall guilt as to former actings, to <hi>cover</hi> ſome kind of corruptions that they may be <hi>huſht,</hi> and be counted Saints beſides: That is a more ſpirituall way, for there be ſome ſo <hi>curious in a ſpirituall hypocriſie</hi> that no man can find them out, they have ſome old <hi>blot</hi> upon their conſciences that they would take off by a new way of acting, take it off from the ſight of others, and be accounted as new: I only give you theſe in generall, they have ſome ſecret corruption that is their <hi>darling</hi> luſt that they would <hi>nouriſh.</hi> This is now to be a <hi>Stage-player</hi> indeed: when I know I am a <hi>beggar,</hi> and yet ſhall put on the <hi>Robes of a Prince,</hi> when I know I have that <hi>unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in my heart, and yet would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a <hi>ſincere</hi> Saint, and would do ſomething that ſhall cover my corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and I would do duties becauſe I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119912:20"/> would get ſuch an honour: That is a moſt <hi>ſhamefull</hi> way: Theſe are the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedeſt ſorts of men in the world; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely there is none have more ſhame in their own ſoules than theſe, if they look into their own hearts.</p>
            <p>I would therefore now apply this, and leave the reſt for ſome other time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> I beſeech ye therefore every one take in the exhortation of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>take heed of</hi> this <hi>Leaven,</hi> this <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> this <hi>wicked venemous poyſon</hi> that lies in <hi>all ſorts;</hi> moſt in <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Congregations</hi> where the Goſpell is Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, we are leavened before we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, take all diligence and care, yet it comes in: This is that which Chriſt did adviſe his Diſciples of: <hi>take heed</hi> of that above all things; but before I go on, I would leave theſe Conſiderations with you, that you may not miſtake.</p>
            <p>Firſt know, that there <hi>may be hypocriſie in the ſoule, and yet a man cannot be called a Hypocrite;</hi> There is Hypocriſie in every ſtate; you muſt not thinke that if you find ſome Hypocriſie you are a Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119912:21"/> I ſpeake this for the <hi>comfort of poore Saints;</hi> if they find any deceit or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in their ſpirits in their duties, then they ſay they are hypocrites; they are damned; no, I would have you to know, that <hi>Hypocriſie lies very cloſe in the ſoule of the beſt Saints;</hi> but only when the ſtraine of a mans ſpirit goes on ſo, then you had need looke to your ſelves when you find that Hypocriſie <hi>predominant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>There may be great charges of hypocriſie as to particular actings, (nay, whole actings may be in hypocriſie) yet not a Hypocrite. Gal.</hi> 2.13. as <hi>Paul</hi> charged <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> with Hypocriſie, the whole act was done hypocritically, and he brings in <hi>Barnabas</hi> as guilty with him, he did <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble,</hi> ſo it may be with a Saint; he may <hi>diſſemble</hi> in an action, in a duty, and yet not be ſo in his <hi>whole ſtate.</hi> Therefore judge not of your ſelves by particular acts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, know that <hi>Hypocriſie is not only as to an outward duty, but in every moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your ſpirits you muſt looke;</hi> it lies not only in groſſe deſignes to advantage ſelfe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119912:21"/> but it grows ſecretly, you know not how it touches upon every part upon a ſudden before you are aware of it; <hi>In your love to Chriſt,</hi> ſtrange Hypocriſie! In <hi>your very motion to Saints, and expreſſions,</hi> what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull vailes of hypocriſie. You muſt therefore looke exceeding <hi>narrowly,</hi> you muſt put on <hi>Goſpell-eyes</hi> to try hypocriſie in your own hearts. But I ſay however, whatever you do in the world, and whatever you be, be not Hypocrites, <hi>Shew your ſelves to be what you are,</hi> let the ſenſe of things ſo lye upon you, that you may not deceive. I ſay not, that profane hearts ſhould vent their profane thoughts, but lye humbly before God in a deep ſence of your deceitfull hearts. And make not the world beleeve you have ſuch and ſuch <hi>enjoyments,</hi> and ſights of Chriſt, yet have none.</p>
            <p>☞ Take the beſt of men in the world, <hi>we that preach to you,</hi> we are in ſome kind Hypocrites: we thinke we are ſo and ſo, and ſpeake nothing but from our own experiences in our hearts; <hi>we may ſhew a perfect rule, and yet be Hypocrites in many
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119912:22"/> things.</hi> Only there is the ſpirituall inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reality to honour God, which is the only comfort; but we are not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what we appeare to be, yet are endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring and preſſing on to be ſo, and that ſhews we are not hypocrites, <hi>though, in ſome ſenſe, every man may be called a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> when he is not what he ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Oh! <hi>take heed, take heed.</hi> But I ſay, be what the Goſpell ſaies, hold forth what you are indeed unto the world. I had thought to have named ſeverall ſorts of perſons, that had more need to looke into their own hearts about hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>thoſe that are of popular ſpirits,</hi> that are to converſe with many, theſe had need looke cloſely to their own ſpirits, for the moſt of our <hi>garbs</hi> and expreſſions are but very <hi>ſeldome true,</hi> and reall, but of the deep ſence of our duties to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Take heed therefore, leſt we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up a name of hypocriſie: it is very hard to have much converſe with the World, and not be much in hypocriſie; without a man be much given up to <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119912:22"/> of ſpirit:</hi> you will find your tempers, in that regard, how they are: you had need have more warineſſe in your owne ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>thoſe that are of a naturall cunningneſſe, a naturall craftineſs of ſpirit,</hi> they had need to take heed, eſpecially when they come under the Goſpell, in opening their ſoules, and converſing with Saints; then that naturall cunningneſſe will be mightily improved under the Goſpell; if not mighty wary it will come up to <hi>a ſpirituall hypocriſie,</hi> if a man have not an exceeding care, and it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous dealing with a perſon that is apt to cunningneſſe. There are exceeding many that are thus in theſe daies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thoſe had need to looke to their own ſpirits, <hi>whoſe Religion begins with ſome particular occaſion in the world;</hi> where Religion begins with the times, it is a thouſand to one but ſuch will prove hypocrites, and dangerous ones too.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Thoſe that are given to an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtrictneſs and ſeverity to externall things,</hi> obſervance of outward actings,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119912:23"/> and circumſtances of outward formes, without they be very careful in them, for here lies hypocriſie, in doing all duties, in being moſt exact in the outward form.</p>
            <p>We ſhall come to open ſomething hereafter, that if it pleaſe God all ſhall ſee if they be hypocrites or no.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119912:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SERMON II.</hi> Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, which is Hypocriſie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is one of the <hi>ſerious</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to his owne Diſciples; and to thoſe that had grace; yet he bids them, and all that ever he met with, to beware of the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Phariſees, which he ſaies was hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Now he calls the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees a <hi>Leaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe of the <hi>ſpreading nature of it,</hi> there is nothing ſo ſpreading as Leaven: put a little of it in, and it will go through the whole Lumpe. <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is the moſt ſpreading thing in the ſoule,</hi> and goes over all the faculties, no faculty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119912:24"/> is free of it; a little Leaven, once it is engendred, ſaies the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> will leaven the whole Lumpe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. A little Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie in a mans ſpirit it will ſoone ſpread (if it be countenanced) over his affections and faculties; and then</p>
            <p>Secondly, he compares hypocriſie to Leaven, becauſe of <hi>its inſenſible way of ſpreading,</hi> no man knows it; a man puts but a little Leaven and it gives a Tincture of it preſently, ſo it is in the heart; Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie workes ſo <hi>inſenſibly,</hi> ſo <hi>cloſely</hi> in a mans <hi>ſpirit,</hi> that if you be not excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wary and carefull, it will undo your whole ſoule; It will give you ſuch a <hi>Tincture</hi> that you will hardly be able to take off the ſavour of it without you have a mighty power from heaven; therefore you had need beware of the Leaven of Hypocriſie. That is only for the Word.</p>
            <p>But you may remember I began laſt time to open the nature of Hypocriſie, and ſhewed you that it was oppoſed to two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Unto the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reality</hi> of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119912:24"/> things, as they lay in their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Unto that <hi>ſimulation,</hi> that <hi>fainedneſs,</hi> unto that ſincerity of intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, faining what a man doth.</p>
            <p>As it ſignifies a faining in that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, It was oppoſed unto the <hi>truth of things; that is Hypocriſie that is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of things as they are;</hi> ſo he is a hypocrite that is not reallie ſound, though he may pretend he is ſo, and thinke he is ſo; for I ſhewed you that is the <hi>groſſer</hi> ſort of hypocriſie to be fained ſo; to <hi>faine</hi> my ſelfe to be a holy perſon, to <hi>faine</hi> my ſelfe to be Saint when I am not, that is the groſſer ſort of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; but there is Hypocriſie lies cloſer, when I thinke I am a Saint and am not ſo, I am a hypocrite.</p>
            <p>So it is oppoſed to a word in the Greeke, often-times uſed and put for ſinceritie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and is a word that will expreſſe it exceeding clearly.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only ſpeake to the firſt ſence at this time.</p>
            <p>To open it more clearely to you.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119912:25"/>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>Hypocriſie is oppoſed to the truth, the reality, and cleareneſſe, the ſincerity and ſoundneſſe of things in their being and nature.</hi> As you know that is a falſe <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> and <hi>Diamond</hi> that hath not the <hi>proper nature</hi> and <hi>colour</hi> that belongs to it, it is counterfeit, it is not right, though I may thinke I am enriched by it; that makes not the thing the truer for that, they are but all counterfeit. I am not richer if I had many of thoſe glittering Diamonds, that is my miſtake; ſo it is as to hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie on this firſt conſideration if there be not a <hi>cleanneſſe,</hi> a <hi>perfection</hi> in the kind. If I be not a Saint reallie in my own Spirit, let my <hi>perſwaſions</hi> be what they will of my ſelfe, and others perſwaſions be what they will be of me, yet I am a hypocrite in the eyes of God. Let my graces be never ſo glittering and glorious in the ſight of my ſelfe and others, yet if they be not ſuch as can be tried according to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſinceritie, ſuch that may abide the judgement of the Sun: If they cannot 'bide the pure ſight of God, and his Glorie, I ſhall be found to be ſtill
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119912:25"/> a perſon that I am not, I ſhall be found in another condition.</p>
            <p>This is that I would ſpeake unto:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not my intention only that will make me a hypocrite,</hi> it makes me a groſſer, to feigne and diſſemble; But it is as well the one as the other: the want of the reall principle, the want of a ſound worke upon my heart.</p>
            <p>Take in the firſt place this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>I appeare to my ſelfe and others to be what God will not own me to be at the laſt day;</hi> ſo there is Hypocriſie in <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals;</hi> I ſay I have grace, and God ſaies I have none. I ſay I beleeve, and God will never owne my faith when it comes to triall. I am as far to ſeeke, and I am as much a Hypocrite, (for <hi>I</hi> have a falſe faith, a falſe motion after God and Chriſt) as much as if I did intend to palliate, to counterfeit my faith on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: A man may have the <hi>complexion</hi> but not the <hi>conſtitution</hi> of a Saint. If I appeare not really what I am before God, I am a hypocrite. Therefore this I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119912:26"/> ſay is the great thing that few in the world do know, <hi>that moſt of Profeſſors are Hypocrites;</hi> they are not throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted though they have (as they thinke) the glorious workings of God upon them, yet if they be not true and reall, and will go through the fire of a divine eye, and the ſearch of that Omniſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Lord, they will never hold. <hi>I am an Hypocrite, though not ſo in intention:</hi> I am not ſo as to the <hi>formality</hi> of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, but I am ſo <hi>really</hi> as to God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider of it, conſider it; for the moſt people think, if they have but a good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intention in what they do; they think they are perfectlie free of all danger of hypocriſie; they are ſafe and ſound in Religion if they pray and do not diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their prayers: that is, that their hearts and their tongues do not jar but do agree, they are then free from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: but that is a miſerable miſtake. For alas, it is all one <hi>whether or no you feigne your ſelves to be what you are not, or are not what you thinke yourſelves to be;</hi> it is all one as to the thing it ſelfe, you will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119912:26"/> find it ſo one day in your own ſpirits: when you ſhall find all that ever you have done to be but glorious appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; What will it do you good when you can ſay only, I had a good intention, I thought I prayed well, and had the ſtraines of the Goſpell in my own ſpirit, what will this do you good if you be not found ſo? But this is that I ſay, that if I have not the truth in me of what I do profeſſe, though I do ſincerelie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly profeſſe what I thinke, it is all one (as to the nature of the thing) as if I do feigne what I am not: For I ſhall be as well undone by the one as by the other, and I am not the perſon I thinke my ſelfe to be, nor others thinkes to be, if God thinkes not me to be what I and others thinkes me to be; and to what end ſhould we ſoulke up and down and not be what we are in our own hearts, but delude our ſelves, and not deale faithfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with our own ſpirits.</p>
            <p>☞ As now take <hi>a Preacher of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,</hi> ſuppoſe I preach the Goſpell; if I preach any thing that is untruth, or a lye,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119912:27"/> though I do it with never ſo honeſt a heart, I ſhall be damned for it: If I preach againſt Jeſus Chriſt any thing that will <hi>deſtroy the fundamentals</hi> of the Goſpell, I ſhall be deſtroyed for all that, though I be never ſo honeſt in my intention; For our intentions are but naturall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: If I think I have grace, and a work of God upon my ſoule, and yet have it not, it is all one as with thoſe that know they have no worke of God and yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is hypocriſie ſeene in it likewiſe, becauſe <hi>I take up things in a generall manner, and never try them, nor my own heart by them,</hi> that ſhews my hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, though I thinke I am reall in my intentions, I ſhould try them over and over againe. But to make out this a little more cleare to you.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider in the <hi>generall the power that imagination hath upon the ſpirits of men:</hi> Take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>one that is thought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the devill,</hi> and trade with him upon promiſe of Gold, and Silver, and the like. The power of <hi>imagination</hi> will
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119912:27"/> worke upon ſuch a man that he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve on the <hi>Devill,</hi> that he hath all the riches in the world, the gold of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> this the very power of <hi>imagination</hi> will do, he thinkes he can want nothing, and yet ſo ſtrong is this power of imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon him all his daies.</p>
            <p>Do but take <hi>a man in a melancholly ſtraine,</hi> he will thinke really he is what he thinkes any other man to be: If any man be taken in a feaver, he will beleeve he is ſo, he will ſweat at it. If any one be thought to go mad, he will be the ſame; It is the ſame in Religion; the <hi>fancy</hi> and <hi>imagination</hi> of a man will work as ſtrongly in Religion and the Goſpell-perſwaſion as a melancholy conſtitution: I will perſwade my ſelfe to be in heaven, and ſee Angels and glorious Saints, and be in the boſome of Chriſt, though I never heard his voice to my own ſoule, and all this upon the power of imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is ſo ſtrong upon our ſpirits; if there were no more but that, it were enough.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in generall know this, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119912:28"/> 
               <hi>you may ſee it by the contrary of ſincerity;</hi> you know that is ſaid to be ſincere in the proper ſence of it that is <hi>not mixt,</hi> that is without any <hi>mixture</hi> at all; as that is pure wine that is not ſophiſticated by any brewing, that is ſincere that is not mixt, that is pure from the grape, ſhines in its own luſtre; we call that hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call that is mixt, or hath any thing to ſet it off but its own nature, theſe things that come purely from it ſelfe; ſo it is in the ſoule of a man that is hypocriticall in his owne ſpirit: that is not ſincere that hath a ſhew of grace, and yet hath it not, that is hypocriſie; he hath common and carnall principles, or, if you will, <hi>common grace and carnall principles mixt together,</hi> it is ordinary in the Goſpell; man hath his <hi>naturall principles;</hi> and <hi>ſome additions of aſſiſtance and power from God,</hi> and they are jumbled together, they are not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere at all, but hypocriticall, nothing ſhines in its own nature; ſo it is with moſt men in the world: there are other <hi>ingredients</hi> that are mixt with all their actings, there is ſomething mixt with it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119912:28"/> in the Principles, in the very firſt moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And certainly this is that which is ſutable to this <hi>Text,</hi> where he ſaies, <hi>Take heed of the leaven of the Phariſees</hi> which is Hypocriſie. <hi>You muſt not thinke the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees did preach Hypocriſie,</hi> but only their doctrine tended to nothing elſe but ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up an outward Religion, without any power, to lead men to holineſſe in ſincerity: and ſo they mixed their own intereſts with any thing of the Goſpell; you muſt not thinke they preached hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, no, they were <hi>wiſe</hi> men and <hi>obſervant,</hi> but their doctrine did <hi>lead</hi> men alwaies to nothing but <hi>outſides of Religion:</hi> to be common Profeſſors, and look after nothing at all but the meere ſhew of the Goſpell and of the Law; the Doctrine it ſelfe was good, but they mixed it with ſome <hi>other ends;</hi> they had <hi>a daſh of their owne</hi> (as I may ſay) with what they ſaid, they were never pure and ſincere in their actings. Therefore the ſame word that is put for ſinceritie is put for unleavened bread, that is, pure bread that is made up without any leaven. Now if a ſoule be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119912:29"/> not cleare and ſound in the principles of the Goſpell, in the workings of it, he is a hypocrite be he what he will.</p>
            <p>There may be <hi>mixtures in ſecond actings,</hi> but if there be <hi>mixtures in principles,</hi> that is hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>And upon this account all Profeſſors that live under the Goſpell, be they of what height they will, they are Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, they never had a ſound worke of God: if there be a mixture in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and the end: They are hypocrites <hi>that never had a through worke of God, and pure divine principles acting in their ſoules:</hi> But have a mixture of other ends in their hearts, that do leaven and ſpread through their whole principles, they are Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</p>
            <p>But for a ſincere ſoule, in principles and actings, they have really unmixt actings from heavenly and holy princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to a holy, and ſpirituall, and divine end.</p>
            <p>How many Hypocrites ſhall we then find before we have done, if men will but ſearch their hearts?</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119912:29"/>
            <p>But that <hi>men may be thus hypocrites, and thinke they have grace, and yet not know ſo,</hi> do not beleeve they are ſuch:</p>
            <p>I will give you firſt ſome <hi>demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Shew you that <hi>they may have ſome ſincerity,</hi> and yet be hypocrites.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That men may be hypocrites, and yet not know it in their own ſpirits, take theſe demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>From the generall rule that all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines give; That whatſoever grace is in a Saint, the likeneſſe and imitation of it may be in a Hypocrite,</hi> and he may thinke he hath it ſo; there is a <hi>faith</hi> in the Goſpell like the faith of a true beleever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is a <hi>joy</hi> in the Goſpell like thoſe that have ſeene the face of God; there is a <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> in the Goſpell like that which comes to the perfect ſubmiſſion to Gods will: and ſo I might go over all the reſt. And ſo there is a <hi>likeneſſe</hi> of <hi>ſincerity</hi> to that which is flowing out from a pure hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſpirit: For look <hi>whatſoever God hath imprinted, that the Devill can paint;</hi> what God leaves as a Character of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119912:30"/> heart of a Saint, that the Devill may ſtrive to imitate, and from a compliance in a mans owne temper forme up the ſame, as Children do make up Babies in imitation of children which are reall: and thoſe that know not this know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, as another conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and demonſtration to make this out, know, that <hi>all thoſe things we call morall virtues, that were in heathens, that is the very reliques</hi> and remainders of pure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that God hath left in ſome meaſure: <hi>thoſe morall virtues are as much improved in the Goſpell without grace, as any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, principle, or rule.</hi> I ſay, morall virtues, as the <hi>Juſtice, Integrity, Patience, keeping of corruptions,</hi> and the <hi>evenneſſe of actings</hi> unto a Rule, the ſame are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable under the Goſpell with more advantage than by any other Rule.</p>
            <p>Take <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> two of the great paterns of morality that ever lived in the <hi>Heathen</hi> world; had they been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law with <hi>Paul,</hi> and brought up under the legall diſpenſations as <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119912:30"/> and the <hi>young man</hi> in the Goſpell were, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. they would have as eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with that Rule, that is, been as faire, as improved men as ever <hi>Paul,</hi> or as the young man, that came to Chriſt, and ſaid, he did never omit any of thoſe things from his youth.</p>
            <p>They did all that the light of nature did ſhew them, and their conſciences, and <hi>Paul's</hi> conſcience did not check him doubtleſſe, as to his exact walking accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rule of the Law: Now as the Law was a higher Rule than the Light of Nature, becauſe it was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and given more poſitively by God, and ſome ſpirituall addition given to it being writtten by that finger of God; the other had as it were the <hi>whole Copy.</hi> So <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> had they been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and brought up as well as <hi>Paul</hi> was, Phariſees, they would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in as eaſily thoſe things, and have brought up under it with as much zeale, and largeneſſe, and refinedneſſe of their natures as he.</p>
            <p>And my reaſon is this; becauſe <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119912:31"/> Rules are as improvable by one as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> according as a man is but under the knowledge of them; A man can as well take in the ſenſe of the one as of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, while he is inured to them he ſees ſome conveniencie, ſome goodneſſe in them; ſo that conſider all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe things are <hi>improvable</hi> in the Goſpell, and then you will ſee how nature may be <hi>refined</hi> by the Goſpell; and if the very meere light of nature imprinted, and glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in a mans conſcience could learne a man ſo far, how would a man come to be when he was under the Letter of the Law: and beleeve it was writ by the finger of God; and then if a man ſhould paſſe through the Law, and come to the Goſpell Letter, and beleeve in a common manner, that this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a more pure and refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Rule, ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit goes on, and is more heig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> to a more bright frame, that <hi>a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thinks all theſe morall virtues even perfectly to be graces:</hi> For a man acts but the ſame principles, the ſame faculties ſtill in the Goſpell, only they are changed, transformed: But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119912:31"/> there is enough in the Goſpell to ſuit all theſe principles, to <hi>refine</hi> them, and make them more <hi>curious</hi> than ever they were by any other principle or Rule.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Adde this, <hi>the voluntary agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and power of the ſpirit,</hi> and workings of the Holy Ghoſt, who workes as he pleaſes, and how he will, and is not bound to worke the uttermoſt of his ſtrength upon a ſoule, but he may work upon nature, and glance upon nature, and leave it ſtill in its own condition, and yet mightily improved as to thoſe <hi>taſtings</hi> and <hi>enlightnings, Heb.</hi> 6. there is even in nature a kind of <hi>taſte</hi> of Heaven and Grace, which will make a man thinke he hath the <hi>power of the world to come,</hi> as you have it in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, as I told you before, there are:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that grace is ſealed upon,</hi> as <hi>nature,</hi> the ſame <hi>underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> the ſame <hi>will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>ſame kind of motions,</hi> as I muſt <hi>know Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>will Christ,</hi> and <hi>go out to Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>breathe after Chriſt,</hi> only
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119912:32"/> they are; they have the ſame <hi>motion</hi> as to will and deſire, but not the <hi>ſame prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> And therefore it is no wonder a man may be deceived in his own ſpirit, and thinkes he knows <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and beleeves on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and hath many motions of him, and all it may be are of outward conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of him: never hath a pure light ſhining from heaven upon his ſoule, ſo that, I ſay, it is a very eaſie thing to ſee how a man can be a hypocrite and not know it: to conſider what voluntary motions there are of the Holy Ghoſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a mans ſpirit, yet not a ſaving worke; for as the Spirit blows upon whom he will, is not bound to convert you: ſo he may preſent the <hi>outward ſpecies</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to you, and never change your will, nor underſtanding, and yet a man may thinke he knows perfectly what's the nature of the whole Goſpell in his ſoule.</p>
            <p>For a man hath to be improved in the Goſpell <hi>a rationall underſtanding,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell can improve as well as any other Rule.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>There are thoſe paſſionate love-expreſſions
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119912:32"/> that will worke mightily upon the affections,</hi> as they are taken in with ſo much fulneſſe and variety as to thinke of <hi>Chriſts</hi> dying, that was innocent, and out of love, if it were but read in a Hiſtory would worke upon the affections, and yet leave nature as nature; a man thinks he loves <hi>Christ,</hi> and may weep at the thoughts of <hi>Christs</hi> death, and yet be unſound for all this.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if you conſider <hi>the variety of Gods workings upon ſoules in converſion;</hi> how many waies he workes, he may thinke he is perfectly converted, and yet an unſound man for all this: Alas the ways of God are ſo <hi>myſterious</hi> it is comap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a <hi>new birth, Joh.</hi> 3. who knows how a child is borne in the womb? A man muſt have a divine light in his ſoule to ſee through and through his ſoule; Take a Saint himſelfe in his cleare light, he can hardly tell how to diſcerne into the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Gods workings: what hath been the pure working of God: where lies the Child; the new-borne babe, as it were. It hath come and paſt through the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119912:33"/> many varieties of Nature and Grace; and then if I ſhould adde, <hi>how apt men are to be perſwaded of the goodneſſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> and not know the badneſſe of them, and how eaſily <hi>ſelfe-love</hi> will be trying to ſet off what hath but a ſhadow of Religion, with many other deceits: then you will eaſily ſay, A man may be unſound and never know it in his own ſpirit for a long while.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A man may be ſincere, and have honeſt intentions in all his duties and actions, and yet be an hypocrite. And that it may be ſo, I ſhall demonſtrate it thus to you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is in ſome men ſuch <hi>a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> ſuch a <hi>naturall ſincerity</hi> (as I may ſo ſay) in their actings, that they are not diſpoſed unto the <hi>contradicting of their principles, and their actings,</hi> they are <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered</hi> within themſelves; they are not diſpoſed to contradict their actings, ſo it is ſaid of the ſincerity of <hi>Alimelech,</hi> as concerning <hi>Abraham's</hi> wife, he appealed to God in <hi>Geneſis</hi> 20. in the beginning, Saies he, in the integrity of my heart,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119912:33"/> and innocency of my hands have I done this: ſaies God, I know thy integrity. Now there is ſuch a ſinceritie even in men that have not grace, that they would not do ſuch a thing if they knew it to be unjuſt, according to their Principles, they would not do it for a world: or if they had taken up an opinion, they would not go againſt their opinion, there is ſuch a kind of ſincerity. Now the ſame may be in the Goſpell; that is, I go on ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly as I think, able to preach, and pray, and I have no kind of ill intention to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, only <hi>I have not a ſpirituall principle to act me, there is my miſery;</hi> I come not ſo much to be ſeen of men as from the intention of my heart; but I come not to have <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or to meet with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> ſo I am a hypocrite, becauſe I come not from the maine principle. Therefore firſt know this as a Rule, that you may ſee this cleare: That <hi>ſimplicity of intention cannot juſtifie any acts of men that are bad,</hi> all will grant that: for as it was with <hi>Pilate,</hi> he waſhed his hands, yet that did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119912:34"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>My intentions in any action doe not make a thing to be true or good in it ſelfe at all;</hi> as if I have a <hi>Jewell</hi> to ſell, my intention in the ſelling it for a good one may deceive the buyer, it being coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit; no act can be good without a good intention, but my good intention makes not the thing really good in it ſelf: if the thing in it ſelfe be not perfect and good, it is hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, know, that <hi>a meere good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention may proceed from the naturall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of a perſon, not from the goodneſſe of his heart.</hi> It may be I am not given ſo much to cunning and deceit as other men, but have a plaine naturall conſtitution; but if it come to a particular, it may be I have as much in my intention (if I were put to it) as others.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, know this about intentions, and the ſincerity of them: That ſincerity that will demonſtrate a man to be a Saint, <hi>muſt flow from the pure and even wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of principles towards their ends:</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity muſt flow from the even acting of faculties within towards their ends: I do
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119912:34"/> not act ſincerely to God though I pray never ſo much in duties, if I have not a divine <hi>ſpirituall ſpring of love</hi> to God, A heart <hi>impulſed,</hi> moved to God from the power of his own ſpirit: If I have not <hi>graces acting together in a harmony</hi> (faith, and love, and all other graces) purely and really working to God: For ſincerity (as I may ſay) is but the ſpirituall <hi>tune</hi> of the motions of all graces in a mans ſoule, it is no more. But I will cloſe up all, there are many things I ſhould have ſhown you.</p>
            <p>But now for diſtinction ſake, having laid down this: That a man may be a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite and not know it, thinke he hath grace and hath it not: I ſhall therefore come and ſhew you the ſeverall ſorts of hypocrites; I will but name them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there is <hi>a meer formall hypocrite</hi> that inſenſibly <hi>drudges</hi> on in his duties, praies, and heares, and comes to Church, and no more, and hath no inward power nor vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in his own ſoule, nor is convinced of any thing to the contrary; as <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay over their <hi>beads</hi> whilſt they are ſleeping;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119912:35"/> I confeſſe every Formaliſt is a hypocrite, but there is a low ſort of Formaliſt that meerely drudges, and that is all, there is ſomething wanting within.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is <hi>a zealous hypocrite,</hi> and he ſeemes to <hi>actuate his Forme,</hi> a <hi>fiery</hi> hypocrite, (as I may ſo ſay) one that you would thinke had life and ſoule indeed, and follows on Religion to purpoſe, and yet <hi>it is but his paſſion and humour,</hi> no grace at all: Some men have taken up an opinion, and are devoted to a way, and their heat is ſo much as they follow it on with might and maine, and ſpits in the faces of others beſides: Such a hypocrite was <hi>Paul,</hi> as to zeale-perſecuting the Church, I followed them on, I dragg'd them to priſon, ſaith he: ſo it is certaine, there are ſome men have taken up <hi>an opinion</hi> ſome way or other, and have no more Religion than the ſtones in the ſtreet; and that they will follow with fire and ſword, and thinke all Religion is loſt if that be loſt, that is their end and Centre; That is a zealous hypocrite, I call him ſo, <hi>for he hath nothing at all but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119912:35"/> that opinion;</hi> come to aske him of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Worke</hi> of God upon his ſoule, and he can tell you no more than a Heathen: and commonly where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>you find ſo much zeale and fire there is hypocriſie;</hi> for the fire of the Sanctuary will enflame a ſoule, there is that: but it will not ſcorch the fleſh, nor burne the heart; We have enough of thoſe zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots in our daies, that without they have their own opinions maintained, they do not mind Chriſt or the Goſpell; nor obſerve how it will go with their own immortall ſoules no more than if they were heathens.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>There are confident and lofty hypocrites upon thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> opinion:</hi> They are full of perſwaſions of the love of God, and grace in their hearts, they have lived under the bright ſun-ſhine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and never came to the truth of the Goſpel, never ſaw their own ſoules and hearts, never came to the furnace of the Law and Goſpell; they have met with ſome good notions of grace and mercy, and apprehenſions of Gods love and joys
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119912:36"/> in their ſpirits, have had ſome little twangs of conſcience now and then, which have put them to ſeeke after the beſt kind of remedy, and <hi>of a ſudden, are got to a great height in the apprehenſions of Gods love,</hi> thoſe I call <hi>lofty, confident hypocrites:</hi> yet it is ſaid in <hi>Job</hi> 8. the hope of the hypocrite ſhall periſh; many ſoules have great <hi>flouriſhings,</hi> mighty bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, they thinke Summer is come and Winter is paſt, and no more but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſpring in the ſoules; like the <hi>ſtony ground,</hi> they beleeved for a time, and immediately received the word with joy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> How can they receive the Word with joy? That is ſtrange that a man ſhould receive the Word with joy and wither preſently.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Truly they had ſome workings on their ſoules, and pangs in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, they ſaw ſome ſins, and had ſome feares, and lived where (it may be) they had ſome ſweet notions of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell was, and they had a promiſe, and tooke it in preſently before ever they knew the nature of it, and rejoyced, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119912:36"/> were confident of their own eſtate, and of the love of God, ſo they go away merry from Sermons, and duties, and nothing at all of true grace; this is the higheſt judgement of God upon ſoules; in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. the Apoſtle ſpeakes of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men up to ſtrong deluſions: Though it is taken for deluſion of doctrines, yet it may as well be taken for mens being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to their own ſtrong perſwaſions of that they have. This is a ſtrong delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſaying, I have ſeene heaven, and the face of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and yet deluded in my own ſpirit. I will adde but one more.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, <hi>A demure and ſtately hypocrite,</hi> this is the higheſt ſort of them: as upon this principle, one that will walke ſo exactly and <hi>curiouſly,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving converſed with all the notions and rules of the Goſpell, that hath <hi>ſprung up</hi> ſo curiouſly, and yet is choaked with ſomething at the bottome of his own heart; he goes on with that ſtrictneſſe, that gravity in the Goſpell, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes all others as unfit, as below him, as one above all others, he hath all kind
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119912:37"/> of <hi>Artificiall motions,</hi> one that hath a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty even temper in his naturall conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and what through <hi>reſtraining grace,</hi> and what with <hi>morall conſiderations,</hi> and <hi>enlightnings</hi> of the Goſpell, he hath got ſome <hi>exact formes</hi> of the Goſpell; this man walkes ſo ſtrictly, ſo curiouſly, that none can diſcover him: Such a hypocrite there is in the world. Look to it, this man walkes ſtep by ſtep, he walkes ſo exactly that all the Saints may admire him: ſo curiouſly that none can diſcover him: But for thoſe glorious converſes with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and through powerfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings he never knew them; he is the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to looke upon of all ſorts of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites: Now there be many things I ſhould have ſhown to you, how to diſcover thoſe ſorts of hypocriſie; As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſhew to you that of all ſorts and ſtraine, <hi>ſelfe is the bottome</hi> of all they do, that is the ſecret of all their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and indeed <hi>ſelfe-love is the ground of all hypocriſie;</hi> for it makes a man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe he is that which he is not, and feigne himſelfe to be what he knows
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119912:37"/> he is not, ſelfe-love is at the bottome: and that workes at the heart ſecretly and cloſely; there be two things I would have ſhewed you about this acting of ſelfe. That</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>a man acts purely, and moves moſt ſtrongly from ſelfe-love, and ſelfe-conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Selfe-ſatisfaction is the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the deſires of the beſt ſort of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly know this likewiſe, (that you may diſcover ſuch an hypocriſie in your own hearts) that <hi>all ſuch ſorts of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, as are known to themſelves, cannot abide to be tried,</hi> to be unript, doth not love launching and piercing, he loves not to have his bowels turned up, he cannot endure to thinke to be put to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his own ſpirit, that is a perfect ſigne of ſuch a hypocrite; Theſe things that go between the marrow and the bone, the ſoule and the ſpirit, he cannot endure that: he would avoid the dints of the ſharpeſt Arrows in the Goſpell, if poſſible. Looke how much flinching you
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119912:38"/> find in your own ſpirits ſo much hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie. A hypocrite cannot abide to be touched fully to the quick, and laid open: to be ripped at the heart, to have the naile driven into the vitals, which a gracious heart longs for.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>There is ever ſome ſecret un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified luſts under all thoſe ſeeming gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a hypocrite;</hi> ever ſome ſecret un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified luſt, either pride, paſſion, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, or concupiſcence, ſomething or other, which will, and doth breake forth ſome time or other; and looke to your ſelves, you that have been ten or twenty yeares under the power of a luſt, and it breakes forth continually upon you: if you be not hypocrites, you are as nigh them as ever was egge to egge, as to the likeneſſe of them; you that have been known to be what you are ſo many yeares together, I durſt denounce ſuch a man a hypocrite that hath lived ſo many yeares under a ſecret luſt unmortified; what, is there no power in Chriſt? haſt thou not kept thy luſt cloſe all this while? It may be thou goeſt to prayer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119912:38"/> and thinkeſt that will make it up, but thy prayer ſhall ſhew thy hypocriſie more, ſeeing thy luſts live.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, thoſe are the higheſt hypocrites of this kind: <hi>They ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly envy the brightneſſe and glories of the gifts and graces of other Saints that goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them;</hi> and that is the perfect Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a hypocrite where ever it is found, if that be not a hypocrite there is none in the world; when a ſoule can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide to be outſhined, it is a ſigne that a man never loved grace for grace, for then he would love it where it is moſt pure, and ſhines moſt gloriouſly, and this the Phariſees were vext at, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſt perfectly, becauſe he went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them, and was a conviction to them: theſe and ſeverall other Characters I had thought to given you; but to ſatisfie ſome ſoules that will be apt to ſay: every one will be a hypocrite if this be ſo, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>My deſigne is to bid you beware of hypocriſie as Chriſt doth:</hi> Try your hearts, take not things up in ordinary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119912:39"/> waies, be not unbeleeving and doubting, that is not the thing I would be at, <hi>it is not to ſcare you off the Goſpell;</hi> be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and criticall, <hi>be ſerious in the viewing of your own hearts,</hi> and ſearch to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and <hi>truſt not your ſelves</hi> with feigned enjoyments, ☞ <hi>I would not diſcourage the pooreſt looker after Chriſt for all the world,</hi> only I would have all men to be pure in their ſpirits, and let every man put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to it; let a man have gold that hath paſſed through the furnace; let a man that will be rich be rich with thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things that are of an eternall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to anſwer that, <hi>you will find grace will lye but in a little roome,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I put you to it, true grace is like a <hi>Diamond,</hi> very <hi>little</hi> in bulke, but of a <hi>high</hi> price, and mighty value; therefore I beſeech you be through in your own hearts, thou poore looker after Chriſt, Grace lies in a little roome, more may be in one motion than in all the acts of the world: you may have more grace than the greateſt and gloriouſeſt Preacher of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119912:39"/> the Goſpell, therefore try thy ſoule, and be not diſcouraged though thou art not ſuch a flouriſhing and glorious profeſſor as another, yet thou maieſt be a greater Saint.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>I would have none taken up with any outſide or glorious formes in the world, but be looking within what inward frames you have</hi> in all your duties; no, I would have no ſoule taken up with <hi>any opinion, with any religion</hi> that is <hi>externall</hi> at all, but that carries out purely to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as the very heart is meeting with the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> and as he hath a ſpirit acted in every word he ſpeakes in the Goſpell, not to <hi>dant you from Religion,</hi> that is not my deſigne, <hi>but to keep you only from the leaven of the Phariſees;</hi> externall depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, that your ſoules may not be loſt with the greateſt miſery to all eternity.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119912:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SERMON III.</hi> Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, which is Hypocriſie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have endeavoured to ſhew you in <hi>general</hi> what Hypocriſie is, and the laſt time gave you a hint of ſeverall ſorts of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; for <hi>hypocriſie lies not in one ſtraine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we will lay this down as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, (which was named before) that looke <hi>as many ſorts of tempers as there are, and humours, and conſtitutions of men, and deſignes that men have in Religion, and as many waies as there are, ſo many common workings as God may have upon men; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of hypocrites may you have entring upon Religion on thoſe grounds;</hi> for looke
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119912:40"/> as it is with grace, where it worketh ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, it changes not the faculties, nor conſtitutions: A melancholly man is ſo ſtill though he have grace, and ſo you ſhall find; his actings will ſhew ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his temper and nature, ſo as to hypocriſie and demonſtrations of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſo many ſorts of tempers as there are in the world, when men enter on the ways of Godlines upon unſound grounds, not being wrought upon throughly by God, ſo many ſorts of hypocrites you will have. I told you of foure Sects the laſt time; now I ſhall go on and ſhew you more.</p>
            <p>Looke as <hi>a man is by nature of a duller and heavier constitution,</hi> and hath got the <hi>outward forme</hi> of Religion, he <hi>will be a meere formaliſt, drudging</hi> on in duties, and no more: nothing of the ſpirituall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, taking abundance of paines without ſenſe, go on in his waies, and his duties without any power at all, and that was the <hi>meere formall hypocrite</hi> I told you of, he hath had ſome little touches upon his ſpirit that moves him, and together
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119912:41"/> with education hath gone on as in a Tract.</p>
            <p>If a man be of a <hi>hot temper</hi> and <hi>conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, fiery</hi> in his nature, and enter on Religion upon ſuch common grounds and ordinary frames (as the moſt do) <hi>he will be a zealous man, exceeding zealous:</hi> Some opinion or other, ſome particular forme his heart is moſt in, and <hi>he is the zealous hypocrite</hi> I ſpake of; he will ſtick to his opinion and hazard all, and never care for the other part of Religion if they can but maintaine that; ſo it is with many in theſe times, never care how the work of God goes on in the world, or their own ſoules, ſo they have their opinion. So if a man be of a <hi>facile and eaſie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> to be perſwaded, and enter upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, he will eaſily conclude that all the promiſes are his, Take every thing for granted in the Goſpell, and apply it to his own ſoule, as if he had a peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to all the promiſes, and ſo grows in a confident ſecure frame, and that is the hypocrite I told you was confident, that out of the eaſineſſe of his nature
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119912:41"/> takes all things in the Goſpell as his owne, though he never ſaw the need and want of them, and never knew the worth of them; for I told you, that <hi>ſelfe-love is the ground of all hypocriſie in a mans ſpirit:</hi> If a man can get any thing for himſelfe, as ſelfe-love acts, ſo a man gets into ſuch and ſuch a frame, as it was with a mad man that ſate at a Port, that when all the ſhips came by, ſaid, this is mine, this is mine: ſo doth all men ſay, without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion, or the knowledge of the nature of the promiſes of the Goſpell, challenging them without a need of them, or a knowledge of the glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of God in them.</p>
            <p>Then againe, if a man <hi>be of a more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and daring ſpirit,</hi> and if he get into a profeſſion of Religion, he will prove a <hi>preſumptuous hypocrite,</hi> to preſume excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly upon the Goſpell, and the things of it; he will vent the opinions he hath taken into his conſideration, and that he ſees moſt ſutable to the world.</p>
            <p>If a man be of a <hi>more grave and ſober temper,</hi> and hath got ſuch a cuſtome of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119912:42"/> Religion and duties, and taken up the profeſſion of it with a ſecret inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of applauſe to be ſomewhat in the world, he will be moſt curiouſly exact in all his frames, ſuch a man will cut to a hair, and he will obſerve the leaſt thing in others that may be as a blot in them, and him I called <hi>a ſtately and curious hypocrite,</hi> he will not be blamed in the world, that is all his deſigne; he will keep all plots and ſpots off him, if out of miſtake he be wrung, he will mend it next time; his name lies at the ſtake for it, and all his comforts lies only in a faire handſome neat carriage in his duties to the Sons of men, that he may be able to be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in his reputation in the world, and ſome men have been ſo curious in their actings and obſervances, that they have ſhamed many precious people; that was <hi>Pauls temper</hi> and care alwaies, that he might be <hi>without blame</hi> to the world; as <hi>to the Law he was blameleſſe, Phil.</hi> 3. and it is as great a thing as a man can ſpeake, and doubtleſſe the Phariſees had a handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and neatneſſe in all their obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119912:42"/> that they were very much admired by the People: A ſtrictneſſe, that they looked at a <hi>Point,</hi> at a <hi>Latchet,</hi> though the great and eternall things lay with no weight on their ſpirits: ſuch kind of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites will go on <hi>ſmoothly</hi> in the world, that a man ſhall <hi>admire</hi> them, and <hi>check</hi> his own heart, &amp; ſay, I am a <hi>hypocrite,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely I never came up to thoſe frames; This man <hi>dazels</hi> the eyes of men, and all his deſigne is to carry on a handſome garbe, and go for ſomebody in the world. Oh! this is that, that many in theſe times had need looke to their own hearts in; <hi>Tithe mint and cummin,</hi> and <hi>neglect the moſt weighty things of the Goſpell;</hi> they have handſome apparell without, but never look within to the eternall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of their poore ſoules, and that ſtate that muſt be before God for ever.</p>
            <p>And againe, If a man be of a <hi>crafty cunning temper,</hi> of a <hi>naturall ſubtilty,</hi> and he begin to profeſſe the Goſpell, he will play the part of a hypocrite to purpoſe, he will <hi>ſhift</hi> at every turne, and <hi>change</hi> every time; he will not be found at any
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119912:43"/> time unſutable, he will tell you he muſt change with <hi>providence;</hi> he will be ſure to mannage all that naturall ſubtilty in Religion to his owne deſigne perfectly: and truly <hi>there are no perſons ſo perfectly hypocrites as theſe,</hi> that out of craftineſſe begin to be hypocrites; upon <hi>ſubtle prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> are privy to their own deceits, they are out of <hi>intention</hi> hypocrites, and they know they can ſhift and comply with any occaſion; there are thouſands of theſe hypocrites in theſe times in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that conclude with the times, that make uſe of the time and occaſion, and have no more grace in them than <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> So take it as to any other temper, whatever you will, if a man be not throughly converted and enter upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; looke <hi>as his temper is naturally, ſo will his hypocriſie be;</hi> and that I may go on a little clearer, take it now as to the temper of <hi>feare</hi> on a man, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of God upon him: If a man be apt to feare, and God lay any thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a mans conſcience, (for God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times keeps ſuch all their life-time in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119912:43"/> feare) you ſhall find that there will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of hypocriſie appeare in thoſe actings, and ſuch a man ſhall be a <hi>terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied hypocrite;</hi> he ſhall live under terrours, and make abundance of worke through his feares, <hi>[for feare may put a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly on to duties]</hi> and be but a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite all this while: Now of theſe there be two ſorts that live under terrours, and I will eſpecially ſpeake to theſe; for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinke if they be under trouble of conſcience and terrour, they are paſt the worſt, and in the beſt frame that can be: Therefore,</p>
            <p>Firſt, there are ſome that <hi>are but more generally touched with the ſenſe of ſome ſin</hi> that God meets them with, and laies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and at every turne checks them for, and lets in glimpſes of his wrath now and then upon his conſcience, and they get into a ſtrange kind of temper, of <hi>complaining,</hi> and <hi>whining,</hi> and <hi>whimpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> in their owne ſpirits, and go on in their duties, (for they dare not but go to duties) but yet it doth not worke ſo much upon them as to cry out with hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119912:44"/> noyſes of damnation, yet are kept under feare, and <hi>bondage</hi> of ſpirit, and cannot get out of it, and all their deſign is to whine at it, and complaine of it to others abroad: that as we ſay in griefe, (to open a mans mind is a mighty eaſe) ſo you ſhall find them open their hearts, and ſay, they are under theſe and theſe ſins, talking of their corruptions, telling how they are under ſuch trials, under ſuch feares of their paſſions, and tell you of hypocriſie, and thus they go from doore to doore, and from Profeſſor to Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and all to no purpoſe, for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew, nor never found the weight and power of the Goſpell lying upon their ſpirits, never ſee the depth of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull heart for all this; But only ſay, alas! <hi>I have ſuch and ſuch corruptions, I am afraid of my eſtate and condition;</hi> and ſo take a <hi>pleaſure</hi> in their complaining. Now there are three waies wherein they ſhew their hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>By this way of complaining they thinke to get off from ſuſpition of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie:</hi> Such Soules, ſuch creatures are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119912:44"/> complaining of their conditions; and ſo they thinke to be free of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie by this kind of <hi>whining,</hi> though they never knew what the hatred of ſin was, never knew what it was to be pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through with the darts of the Goſpel for ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they thinke by this <hi>to get the pity and compaſſion of other Saints,</hi> to pitty and bemoane them, and we ought (ſay they) to ſpeak a good word to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them: Though Saints nor Angels cannot ſpeake a good word to ſoules, yet they looke for it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they ſhew their hypocriſie by this, <hi>They looke upon themſelves by it as poore in ſpirit,</hi> alwaies in ſenſe of ſin, and under a ſenſe of their loſt condition, and would have others thinke ſo too: there is a poore ſpirit, nothing but poverty of ſpirit, never come to him but he hath low eſteeme of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, But the <hi>great ſtraine</hi> of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie lies in this, <hi>they perfectly rest in this ſtraine of complaining, and never look after Chriſt,</hi> they get eaſe by opening their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119912:45"/> minds, and if they can but get a good anſwer to quiet them for the preſent, they go away content; I have abominated this frame of any frame in Profeſſors; A ſtrange ugly whining frame of ſpirit conſtantly upon a ſoule, which ſhould not be upon a Profeſſour but in the <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteſt</hi> caſes of neceſſity, and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion, for he ſhews he hath not been at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and opened his condition to him, but he muſt have this and that outward help firſt, and if he cannot help himſelfe, then go to him. It is common, you ſhall find people complaining and ſpeaking ſtrangely of their condition, and by a poore common word ſpeaking to them they go away content, though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had the thoughts of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in their hearts, many make <hi>a trade</hi> of it; you ſhall find an <hi>old</hi> Profeſſour ſay, I am of a ſtrange <hi>paſſionate</hi> ſpirit, and have been ſo many yeares, of a ſullen, ugly, peeviſh ſpirit, that none can deale with me, I have ſuch and ſuch a corruption, and I am afraid that I am a hypocrite. [Aye, ſo thou maieſt know thou art one.] They
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119912:45"/> will complaine, Oh! what a wicked wretch am I; give him but one word of comfort in an ordinary manner, they are content, though the corruption be lying ſtill, be living in the heart ſtill; I told you the laſt time, <hi>I would pawne my life that he was a hypocrite that lived ſo long time under the Goſpell under the power of one corruption, having no power againſt it,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no grace to ballance his corruption, and though the corruption might act, yet a ſoule might ſee there are other glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous graces beſides; and do you thinke, that complaining of your corruptions, can that ſerve your turnes? you will come to a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> or a ſerious Saint, and ſay, thou art troubled <hi>for</hi> thy ſin or corruption: Art thou troubled <hi>with</hi> thy corruption? Then thy trouble would be known, the very bowels of thee would be ſeene working out, one way or other; thou wouldſt never let <hi>Chriſt</hi> reſt, but get pardon, and power to kill thy corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if it ſhould breake out, it would be the conſtant ſhame of thy ſoule night and day before all the Saints; <hi>Never tell
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119912:46"/> me of Religion if it lies not in the vitals of men, and kills the vitall corruptions, and actuates the ſoule into the eternall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</hi> And a man may be found to be a hypocrite for all theſe things: Art thou troubled with a corruption and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of it, canſt thou be quiet with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining? Can any word comfort thee but the <hi>death</hi> of it, and the <hi>ſence</hi> of the death of it every day? Can any <hi>promiſes</hi> comfort thee, but as they tend directly <hi>to deſtroy</hi> thy corruption? Is it poſſible if a ſoule have any reality of grace in his own heart: I had rather [ſaies a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart, ſaies a poore ſincere ſoule] go to the <hi>funerall</hi> of that corruption, and ſee it buried, than be the greateſt <hi>Emperour</hi> of the world, or in the glorious frame in the world, be it <hi>Pride, Paſſion, Luſt,</hi> or whatever it be in a mans ſoule. But this is the miſery of men taken up with meer complainings: of all Profeſſors this ſort goes on moſt cunningly, for we common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judge of men by their <hi>ſence</hi> and <hi>ſight</hi> of ſin, and thinke they are in the moſt <hi>fundamentall</hi> way of the Goſpell; and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119912:46"/> they have the <hi>root of the matter,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> hath touched them indeed; and yet <hi>God</hi> hath done nothing for all this.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is another ſort that lie under terrours <hi>ſharply, flaming ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> and are <hi>ſcorched,</hi> in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for ſome <hi>ſpeciall</hi> ſin; and mighty <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> in duty: they will run here and there, and ſay, <hi>I am damned, I am damned,</hi> what ſhall I do, I am <hi>loſt</hi> for ever, they will come with ſuch hideous noiſes and cries to men, and run any where, the flame is ſo hot; yet all this while ſin not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, nor the ſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> taken in upon the ſoules of men.</p>
            <p>Now know theſe two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the <hi>greateſt unbeliefe</hi> is hid under the <hi>greateſt terrours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the <hi>greateſt hypocriſie is under the ſights of ſin,</hi> and <hi>greateſt terrours,</hi> [for a man will do any thing to avoid that] that if he be mightily terrified he will <hi>be</hi> any thing, <hi>do</hi> any thing to take off that ſin: herein lies</p>
            <p>Firſt, the hypocriſie, that <hi>he does no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to eaſe himſelfe,</hi> quiet his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119912:47"/> and he lets ſin alone: that he may but live quietly, he deſires no more.</p>
            <p>So I have known ſome Profeſſors that have been in <hi>mighty terrours for one halfe yeare, and the other halfe yeare been as joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as could be:</hi> Going to others, ſaying, <hi>pitty</hi> me, <hi>ſave</hi> me, do any thing with me and ſave me, and when <hi>God</hi> hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn the violence againe from them, when any conſiderations have come in, they have falne to their old corruptions againe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Their hypocriſie lies in this, <hi>they will ſnatch at any thing to comfort them,</hi> take any hand as ſoone as <hi>Chriſts.</hi> But a truly touch'd ſoule will not be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>a poore ſoule indeed cannot be quieted or comforted by any but Chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festations of his love;</hi> but as for this terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied hypocrite, he will ſnatch at any thing as ſoon as Chriſt; give him but a <hi>Promiſe</hi> [though it no more concerne his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than if it were never named, yet he will have it as if it had been made for him,] he will be ſure to catch at it, if you can <hi>divert</hi> his thoughts, it ſhall be as much
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119912:47"/> to him as <hi>Chriſts bloud:</hi> take off the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of his terrours he is <hi>pleaſed.</hi> And the truth is, moſt kind of hypocrites are under ſome kind of terrours or other; they would never have ſuch twangs of conſcience as they have, but that they are under ſome terrours of conſcience from <hi>God</hi> upon their ſoules: But as for this kind of hypocrite, he may be ſo carried on, that he may do all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with the moſt zeale and violence: he may pray with great paſſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moane his condition, that it would make a mans heartake [if you could but heare him praying] ſometimes, if you could but be privy to his cryings, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he makes loud ones, and every man may heare him; but ſtill his <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> grows more <hi>inſenſible</hi> and his heart <hi>hardened,</hi> and grows <hi>common</hi> to him at laſt. And ſuch a hypocrite will live in the <hi>fire,</hi> if he can but get off the <hi>violence</hi> of terrours, his heart ſhall be as black as hell, with the very burnings of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and certainly that which the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> ſaies of a conſcience <hi>ſeared with a hot
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119912:48"/> Iron</hi> may referre exceeding much to this, that God may with terrours ſeare up a mans heart, for the devill is the greateſt hypocrite, and he lives under the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt terrours, the flame of wrath hath hardened his heart infinitely againſt God, that there can be no place of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſo theſe hypocrites goe on by degrees, and only in a generall manner find the terrours of God upon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and never ſee the nature of ſin and vileneſſe of it to the ſoule. So that this I ſay, do not thinke, that becauſe you are troubled in your conſciences, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der terrours, that you are free from hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; nay, there is moſt hypocriſie there; plainneſſe of heart is under cleare light, when a man is free from advantage of feare, or terrour, and too much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, then is the beſt time to try a mans heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Take one in the ſecond place as to Gods workings, <hi>one of a naturall capacity,</hi> that is, he is capable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of things; he begins to profeſſe the Goſpell, and comes under a kind of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119912:48"/> enlightning of God, God giving a man [as he may] a common gift of grace by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon notions of the Goſpell, here is one will come to be a moſt glorious hypocrite; I call a hypocrite, becauſe the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall worke is not done, becauſe he is not what he ſhould be, nor what he ſeemes to be. <hi>Now as the former ſort his conſcience was enlightned with flames, this man he is enlightened with more calme and ſun-like beames;</hi> this man can now ſee into the Rules of the Goſpell, he can be able by degrees and time to forme and worke in all the notions of the Goſpell into his head, that he now comes to be a profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hypocrite unto others, comes to be able to ſpeake very great things of the Goſpell, and can tell you as perfect truths as any experienced Saint in the world can do; and eſpecially if he have edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and time, and acquaintance to communicate them to: he will come to be able to delude any Saint in the world, for now he is not a meere out-ſide man in ſight, but one that <hi>brings out of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury things new and old,</hi> that hath got a vein
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119912:49"/> of diſcuſſing and ſpeaking as reall things as any man can ſpeake in the Goſpell; how far may this man go? and yet here lies his hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>All theſe things goe no further than the head;</hi> they were never ſtamped upon the heart, never upon the breaſt, they are <hi>Artificially</hi> formed in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, never come down to be imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſoul, upon the will &amp; affections, never had thoſe heavenly influences dropping in the favour, the ſweetneſſe, the power, and the virtue of that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, proportionably working in their ſpirits: and there lies their hypocriſie, that all thoſe things are but artificially formed in the underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>All that ſuch a man doth act in the expreſſion of any knowledge he hath, it is with ſecret glory;</hi> he joyes, he takes himſelfe to be ſomewhat now, and makes all theſe things to be his own, as though he received them from Chriſt, he glories in them, there is all, <hi>ſhame him,</hi> there you make him <hi>miſerable,</hi> if you hit him there you cut upon his heart veine. And that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119912:49"/> is the way of God commonly with thoſe ſorts, their <hi>parts</hi> die, and God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws by degrees, and lets knowledge dye, letting corruption come in ſo much upon them as they loſe all at laſt. But it is wonderfull to conceive how far theſe convictions will carry a man, when he hath a <hi>Candle lighted</hi> by God how far he may walke in the Goſpell; when God ſhall ſhine in (as it were) upon nature, how it will appeare before the Sons of men: It lies in the head, and <hi>ſelfe</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly advanced, not <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that Chriſt may have all the praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as it is ſaid in <hi>Job</hi> of the hypocrite, <hi>the heart of him is little worth;</hi> he may have ſome fine parts and be <hi>ingenuous</hi> in his underſtanding, but his heart is the worſt, there is nothing but ſin and ſelfe together, and inward ſecret contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and working againſt God, and the power of Religion; ſo it was with the <hi>fooliſh Virgins,</hi> they went on gloriouſly, but at laſt they ſaid, <hi>our Lampes are gone out,</hi> we have loſt our light, we have ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered and ſlept away our time, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119912:50"/> upon our gifts and endowments, and our faire actings in the world, and our Lamps are gone out, and now we have nothing to ſhew for all our profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I will a little ſet home this with a word or two of Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> Firſt therefore, if this be ſo, that there may be ſo many ſorts of hypocrites and ſtraines, I beſeech you <hi>examine</hi> your own hearts, and put your ſoules upon it, <hi>find out this Leaven;</hi> I told you why hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie was called Leaven, becauſe of the ſpreading nature of it, none knows how it ſpreads; Hypocriſie hath many <hi>vizards,</hi> many <hi>waies,</hi> you may go on ſo fairely, and ſo painted, that no man, nor your own hearts can diſcerne you: But looke ſeriouſly, looke every day what is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, aske your owne ſoules <hi>what is within;</hi> bring your ſelves before a <hi>divine eye,</hi> looke to every <hi>part,</hi> to every <hi>motion,</hi> let nothing paſs you without a <hi>divine and exact ſcrutiny,</hi> never be quiet till you have get a through definition of your owne eſtate, ſtand <hi>Sentinell</hi> to your own hearts; ſay not, I am a Saint till you have found
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119912:50"/> clearely, both by Law and Goſpell, till it be written with the beames of the Sun upon your own hearts; Oh! <hi>I am afraid the moſt Profeſſors will be found hypocrites at the laſt day;</hi> that thoſe that have the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt faces to us will have the fouleſt rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings up before the Lord; many that go ſo neately now will have a black Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter at laſt; Oh! for <hi>Chriſt</hi> to ſay, <hi>go you curſed,</hi> at the laſt day, to a glorious Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, what a word will that be? Appeare to what you are indeed, and ſtrive to be what you ſhould be; take not up ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and common things in your owne ſpirits; lay not the weight of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe things that are not reall, that are but meere gilt upon Copper, that will not endure; men are apt to take themſelves up with profeſſion if they have but a faire face, if they have but a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome carriage in the world: Oh! that <hi>Christ</hi> would have charity to you at the laſt day, as we muſt have now: Chriſt loves thoſe that are holy, and he loves to make them holy: He muſt judge you as you are, no charity after the Goſpell is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119912:51"/> paſt, therefore look to your own ſoules; there is a day when <hi>every thing that is hid ſhall be revealed,</hi> there is no halting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Almighty, he hath an eye on you: Chriſt will find you out in the croud of Men, Devils, and Angels, and pick you out with his eye, and ſay, <hi>Friend, how came you hither?</hi> You never had the power of the worke of God upon your heart: do not thinke to deceive your own ſoules by theſe pretences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But you will ſay, What ſhall I do then? You make all men hypocrites, how ſhall I know whether I be a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite yea or no?</p>
            <p>I gave you three things the laſt time in the generall to conſider of:</p>
            <p>Firſt, I told you my deſigne was <hi>to preſſe you on to try your ſelves,</hi> and to ſecure your own eſtates.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Grace will lye in a little roome,</hi> in a very little compaſſe, it lies not in the flaunting garbes and modes of the times, it is like a Diamond, little, but of great prize.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>I would have no man taken up
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119912:51"/> with ſhews:</hi> It is not my deſigne to make you Hypocrites, but to diſcover Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie to you: Therefore looke to your own hearts that you be not Hypocrites. I would not diſcourage any poore ſoule that is panting after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Therefore</p>
            <p>Firſt, know in generall, <hi>though thou maiest be no hypocrite, yet thou maieſt ſuſpect thy ſelfe for hypocriſie</hi> every day, in every duty, though thou beeſt none ſo called, nor ſo accounted by God, yet thou muſt ſuſpect thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, know this in the generall, <hi>Thou ſhouldſt not charge thy ſelfe to be a Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite for every ſight of Hypocriſie:</hi> And the more ſpirituall you grow under the Goſpell, the more you will ſee of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe of your heart every day.</p>
            <p>But I will give you theſe ſix <hi>Characters,</hi> that no hypocrite can ever have in their hearts, nor attaine to: and I hope ſome poore ſoules will be comforted, and they are the pooreſt things you would thinke to fleſh and bloud in the world: thoſe things that a man would never imagine, eſpecially thoſe high-grown men in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:119912:52"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Can you hate ſin as ſin,</hi> that is, in its whole nature, in every appearance of it, in its firſt motion, in the firſt hints of it, in the ſins that are moſt deare, that I tooke moſt pleaſure in? Hypocriſie in its actings towards ſin picks and chooſes here and there, it may be <hi>angry</hi> with ſome ſin that diſturbes it, but it never <hi>hates</hi> it, no hypocrite <hi>can have a hatred of ſin as ſin;</hi> hate the firſt of the firſt as it were, though it comes never ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, never ſo ſet as it were, hates it as ſin upon no other conſideration; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it troubles my conſcience, and brings me to hell and wrath, and renders me unſutable to my relations and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes in the world: He is a Saint, looke to it, the very Embryo of ſin, the ſincere ſoule hates, it hates it as ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>No hypocrite can delight to be aſhamed by God in his duties,</hi> in his actings, lye under the ſhamings of God, and made purely nothing in its own eyes and others, that the Hypocrite cannot do; and yet a poore ſimple ſincere ſoule can do it, a poore ſoule, that may be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119912:52"/> can hardly ſpeak two words with ſence, and ſutableneſſe of expreſſion, yet he can do it; he can delight as well to ſee God ſhaming his ſoule, bringing him to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, humbling of him to the duſt, as if he were to be in the Armes of the Lord, <hi>taking pleaſure in his humbling acts;</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe God deny him any aſſiſtance in a duty, or in the opening of his heart, that if he be in company, he is aſhamed to looke upon his own heart, here the ſoule takes pleaſure to be aſhamed, no hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite can endure that, to be aſhamed in his actings and relations; for ſelfe-love is the principle of hypocriſie in the heart of a hypocrite: <hi>He cannot endure to be out-ſhined, that is the wicked frame of him;</hi> if a Saint go beyond him in grace, and communion with God, he cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it, and therefore cannot endure to be aſhamed; Oh! how do the Saints love to be laid low before God, that they may have the pure glory of him ſhining upon their ſoules. Then</p>
            <p>Thirdly, know this as a ſpeciall one, <hi>No hypocrite can bleſſe God, and love him
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119912:53"/> from his heart, when God ſmites him in his deareſt enjoyments, or neareſt luſts,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath delighted; take away his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, take away thoſe things he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed formerly, and he cannot love Chriſt, nor bleſſe him in his heart; ſtrike him in any thing that the eye and heart of him hath been upon, he ſecretly hates Chriſt: Now a Saint can cling to Chriſt, love him ſecretly in his own ſoule, though he ſeeme to be as an enemie to him, he cannot but love him for all this; no hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite can do this; take away what pleaſes his nature, and he cannot love him. Try your hearts by theſe things.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, know this, <hi>No hypocrite can love the perſon of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nor a Saint as a Saint,</hi> I put theſe both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he cannot love the perſon of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> for he never had the <hi>glimpſes</hi> of his glory on his heart, he only loves to be pardoned, and have ſome comfort from him, but he never finds his heart to worke in love to the Lord Jeſus; and have an union with him, as the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ground of all his comforts, for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119912:53"/> love you know it longs for union: Nor he cannot love a Saint as a Saint purely: but a Saint ſo tempered, ſo conditioned, he cannot love a poore ſaint, nor a weak Saint, he cannot purely cloſe with him, and have his bowels working towards him purely as a Saint.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>No hypocrite can go on in any ſpirituall worke or ſervice for Chriſt with any contentment, with any pleaſure, without ſenſible comforts, or outward reſpects;</hi> pray obſerve; for if he want inward ſenſible comforts, yet the wind of men will fill his ſailes; but a poore Saint can take pleaſure in the meere mention of Chriſt, in the pooreſt worke of Chriſt, wherein he is leaſt ſeene, wherein he hath hardly a name, only with ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection: this will try a man, if I had time to open it throughly.</p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, <hi>No hypocrite in the world can long to be like Christ, as to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by Chriſt,</hi> either as to inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, or trade in the world. Or thus, No hypocrite <hi>can love the holineſſe of Chriſt as the good things he gets of Chriſt;</hi> he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119912:54"/> abide to be out of his owne forme, and in the forme of the nature of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but a Saint, if he have never ſo much <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> and his ſoule alwaies drawing honey, with marrow and fatneſſe, yet if he have not the <hi>likeneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> and be like Chriſt, he is not pleaſed; no hypocrite can love the holineſſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt with a pure love that may deſtroy his corruption, that may unbottome him, bring him perfectly out of ſelfe, and transforme him into that glorious Image.</p>
            <p>Try your ſelves by all theſe things; I had thought to have ſhewn you wherein the ſtraines of hypocriſie lie to all ſorts of duties, and the ſpirituall workings of it in the hearts of men, but I muſt leave that to ſome other time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:119912:54"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SERMON IV.</hi> Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, which is Hypocriſie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have ſhewed you in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall exerciſes what the nature of hypocriſie is, and have diſtinguiſhed to you the ſeverall ſorts of hypocrites under the Goſpell: ſhewed you how <hi>cunningly</hi> and <hi>cloſely</hi> men may act, and yet ſtill have this leaven in them, paſſing through all their parts; there is ſome little thing or other that is inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſome men, known to others, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are miſtaken and undone under all their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not be able to repeat any thing: but in the latter end of the laſt Sermon I told you of <hi>Six</hi> things that no hypocrite
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119912:55"/> could do, or attaine unto: and I will adde but this one to all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>No hypocrite in the world can deſire Chriſt, that God might be glorified in the utter ſhaming of himſelfe, as to all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and to all enjoyments, and abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of comforts to himſelfe,</hi> pray obſerve it: this is that which ſtrikes at ſelfe-love perfectly, which is, as I told you, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of all hypocriſie in a mans ſpirit: and I ſpeake this as a tryall, that is very cloſe and narrow to the ſpirits of men, and likewiſe to diſtinguiſh in this point between a Saint and a hypocrite.</p>
            <p>For I will not go ſo high as ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have often ſaid, and given it as a Character of a gracious and bleſſed frame (but I will not go ſo high) that they could be content to be damned: <hi>that I take is a paſſionate expreſſion</hi> of Chriſtians not underſtanding. But as to all <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> all things that concerne not purely the glory of God, and all priviledges, and comforts of this life, either inward or outward, that ſoule that is a Saint can ſay, he can be really willing to part with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119912:55"/> that Chriſt may be all (if he be but himſelfe, and have a freedome from temptations, no hypocrite can ſay it, cut him in his priviledges and enjoyments, there he will fret: <hi>But for any Saint to be willing to be damned for Chriſt,</hi> it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that will never hold weight in the Goſpell, if it be conſidered.</p>
            <p>For firſt, know this, <hi>I cannot deſire that which is not Gods will to grant,</hi> nor ought to deſire it; it is a ſin to deſire any thing againſt Gods will: it is not Gods will that a Saint ſhould be damned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Damnation is not an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate act of Gods Soveraignty, but of his vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive juſtice,</hi> for indeed, I am damned, becauſe I have ſinned, not becauſe God hath willed that I ſhould be in that ſtate, for it follows only ſin; damnation, it doth not follow immediately the ſoveraignty God, who chuſeth whom he will, he cals one, rejects another, gives grace to one, leaves another in a ſtate of damnation: that is not immediately an act of Gods ſoveraignty, though it be conſequently.</p>
            <p>Then againe thirdly, <hi>it is againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:119912:56"/> God will never deſire any thing of any that is againſt the conſtitution of that nature which God hath put in him: that is, to be willing to be ſeparated from God, God cannot command you, nor give it as a rule to you to will it, that any of his Creatures ſhould deſire to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from him. Therefore take it as a <hi>flaſhy</hi> expreſſion of a Profeſſor to ſay, he can be willing to be damned; and <hi>I ſhould ſuſpect that ſoules truth of grace that ſhould ſay ſo, if I did not know the temper of that perſon;</hi> As for thoſe expreſſions of <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the like, pray conſider of it, and you will eaſily find the anſwer; it is not the meaning that they deſired to be <hi>ſeparated from God,</hi> for <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe, and <hi>Moſes</hi> caſe was about the <hi>People of God;</hi> the <hi>Children of Iſrael</hi> they had ſinned againſt <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> was angry with them, and would take the outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances from them, and caſt them out of the priviledge of being a Church, (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> blot out me rather, let me ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſe the priviledges than they;) <hi>but to be deſirous to be damned, none could do it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119912:56"/> without ſin:</hi> for it is to deſire to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the greateſt good, that I may be perpetually incapacious of ſerving the living God, or knowing any thing of his love. Neither doth God will it, nor law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully may a Saint, a Saint cannot will it, becauſe it is againſt God, and for God to do it he cannot, for it is againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but that only by the by.</p>
            <p>But this is that I ſay, a Saint can be content and willing if God ſee it fit to be <hi>abſtracted from all priviledges,</hi> from all <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments,</hi> from all thoſe things that are deare to him, if he knows it to be Gods will, and mind, and the glory of God is concerned in it, from all ſelfe-willing, though he ſhould never enjoy any more comforts in the world; for <hi>here is ſelfe-deniall: to be willing to be abſtracted from thoſe things that hinder communion with God,</hi> to be willing that God for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of his name ſhould leave me in the darke ſo long as I have but uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with himſelfe, is but only as to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, and the acting of that glorious love to my ſelfe, elſe it is unworthy for a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119912:57"/> Saint to will ſuch a thing. But I ſay, here is that a hypocrite cannot do, he cannot be willing that God ſhould <hi>ſhame</hi> him to <hi>glorifie</hi> himſelfe, he cannot deſire to be <hi>blaſted</hi> in thoſe things, thoſe comforts which he moſt gloried in, he will fret againſt God, he can never endure it. A Saint, like <hi>Jonah,</hi> may be <hi>pettiſh</hi> for the preſent when the <hi>Gourd</hi> is gone, but he continues not ſo: But a hypocrite let him be poore in the eyes of thoſe Saints he converſes withall, and his heart will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſubmit to God. But I go on now, and come to ſhew you the ſtraines of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie in thoſe three things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, As <hi>to duties</hi> in generall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>In prayer</hi> in ſpeciall.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In <hi>converſes with Saints, and in the world;</hi> we will go as far as we can at this preſent.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>A Hypocrites acting as to duties in generall;</hi> take all the Commandements of God, and that in theſe ten particulars at leaſt, <hi>I deſire you to obſerve them, and try your own ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Every one that is an hypocrite
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119912:57"/> 
               <hi>hath a byas in every duty,</hi> ſomething that <hi>turnes</hi> him alwaies; though he may ſeeme to looke at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet certainly he looks another way; though he may ſeeme to go to the promiſes, yet he hath another end than to be ſanctified and made pure by them: there is never a hypocrite in the world but he hath ſuch a byas, that caſt him which way you will, that ſhall lead him, either applauſe of men, or ſome ſecret corruption that acts within him at the ſame time if he be faithfull to his own heart: and it is the end rules the action; what a man's aimes are, that a man is in his duties; if nothing but pure grace, and Chriſt, and glory will be of only concernment, then it is a ſigne I am carried out by other principles than hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites act from, but I ſhall know com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly this at the end, or beginning, or at the firſt moving to a duty, or the turne of it what hath been that which carries me on, ſtill there is a byas: after I have done, what is that which poyſes my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the duty, or what moves me to it, or what is that I aime at in it: If a mans
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119912:58"/> aimes in every duty be not <hi>primarily the glory of God, ſecondarily to deſire the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in a mans own heart, it is an hypocriticall act:</hi> O it is ſtrange to ſee, when a man runs on a long time fairely, evenly, as it were, when the byas comes to have his weight, then you ſhall ſee him at length turne with the byas. As the ſtrength of a mans hand in throwing a bowle is ſo much, that there will be no ſight at preſent of a byas, but when it is ſet, and the ſtrength of the hand off, then you ſhall ſee which way it will turne: So you may try your own ſpirits; there is a thouſand ſecret kinds of ſhifts that paſs up and down a mans ſpirit ſo inſenſibly in duties, that none knows them but a mans own heart, if he be faithfull; if a man be not high in his aimes, and high in his ends, all his duties are loſt, they are to no purpoſe at all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, know this, that you may know a hypocrite in his duties, that <hi>he is moſt forward and zealous in externall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, more than in internall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of that, know there are two ſorts of duties.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:119912:58"/>
            <p>Firſt, Theſe that are purely the acts of the ſoule within a man, as ſelfe-examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and meditation, and inward hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings, and mournings of the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: they are perfectly the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of the ſoule within from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the things laid before them, as the object is, as the grounds and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of mourning and rejoycing are, ſo thoſe inward actings are: theſe you ſhall find that a hypocrite ſeldome takes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in, or is conſiderate about.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a ſecond ſort of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which I call externall, and they are of two ſorts, and hypocriſie is ſeen in both: they are externall both, but the one is more <hi>publike,</hi> the other <hi>more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi> as to preach or pray among others, that is more publike: Now you ſhall find a hypocrite is more forward, more ſtrict in thoſe duties than in ſecret duties, more in the externall than in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. You ſhall find that hypocriſie it lies in this; firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There will be a perfect careleſſeneſſe as to theſe duties that are inward,</hi> ſeldome exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119912:59"/> and ripping up the heart: ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome going to God in the humbling frame of a mans heart, ſtudying the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of humiliation, that mourning and humbling of a mans ſoule in dutie, and for duties, and as to meditation, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate what is Chriſt, and what I have done againſt Chriſt what is the frame of my own heart, very ſeldome any of thoſe things at all: And if it comes to a pinch the man is quiet, or at leaſt he finds a conveniency to turne it off: If upon examination of his heart he finds not things ſo well as he would, he will turne off them by ſome trick: whereas a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart is never well, never better than when he is ripping up all his bowels, than when he is in ſoule-worke, when he can looke within, there is his great and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty worke he looks after: you ſhall very ſeldome find that the Cloſet-hypocrites if they do theſe things, and make ſome triall of them, yet when they come to the pinch they will have ſomething to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them from the ſtrength of their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:119912:59"/>
            <p>Secondlie, And ſo now as to externall duties, do but compare ſecret to publike, they are mightily taken with thoſe duties that are moſt publike, will be mighty cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in them; but if you come to ſecret duties they ſlubber them over, any thing will ſerve that; if they can but ſay they have been upon their knees, or done a dutie in their Cloſet, or in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, although no care of the nature of thoſe things. That is the ſecond thing: and my Brethren, you ſhould feare and try your own hearts by it, if you have but any conſideration, looke ſeriouſly into your own ſpirits what is that that takes you up moſt, whether thoſe things that are the immediate things of the ſoule, thoſe duties that do ſo purelie belong to the nature of your condition, thoſe things that are ſo within, that they can only be tried by your own ſpirits, and the ſpirit of God in them, or whether you are more choice in externals.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, know this as to duties in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, <hi>Hypocrites have their exceptions, and limitations,</hi> they have their choice, they
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119912:60"/> will pick and chuſe, have what is moſt ſutable to fleſh and bloud, and what is moſt ſutable to their condition, what is moſt plauſible, thoſe duties they will cloſe in withall. But it is, my Brethren, contrary to a Saint; indeed he knows there are the great things of God that his heart is taken up with. But as <hi>David</hi> ſaies, <hi>then ſhall I not be aſhamed when I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to all thy Commandements;</hi> a hypocrite will neglect his duty if he finds it too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, or if it be a hinderance to him in the world, he loves not duty in it ſelfe, but he hath his choice, and thoſe that are ſutable and convenient, thoſe he follows on; and this you will find to be a cloſe tryall for the beſt ſorts of them, you have ſome ſo zealous in ſome duties, that you would thinke their ſoules were in them, but come to other duties, they have no ſence of them: for if I did love duty in it ſelfe, I would not baulke any thing, be glad of every opportunity, there is Chriſt and heaven in this as well as in the other; but few hypocrites ever looke after this, they will pick out duties ſutable to the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119912:60"/> times, and ſutable to their own humours, and fit to the places they live in, but if they come to a dutie that will put a man to it, and wherein a man muſt be laid in the duſt there will be a ſhrinking of the ſoule of a hypocrite; pray conſider of it, and apply thoſe things home to your own hearts; <hi>he that doth not love every dutie, that he knows to be a duty, and would gladly do it with all his ſoule, and doth not ſtudy to know his duty, he is an hypocrite.</hi> Oh, to ſee ſome men, and ſome great Profeſſors, how faire they will be in ſome actings and duties, but come to others, they cannot abide them, they cannot away with them, there are ſuch winſings, ſuch turnings and deviations in their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, know <hi>that hypocrites in their duties make a great deale adoe about little things, and neglect the greater and maine things,</hi> and this is one of the great things Chriſt chargeth the Scribes and Phariſees withall, they make a great deale of adoe about little things that are in themſelves fit to be done, but neglect
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119912:61"/> the greater and the more weighty and conſiderable things, ſo ſaies Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.16. <hi>Woe unto you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites, that ſay, if a man ſweare by the Temple it is nothing, but if he ſweare by the Gold of the Temple he is a debtor,</hi> and <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.14. <hi>You tythe mint and cummin,</hi> &amp;c. Now if you find you are curious in your owne ſpirits about outward little things, (ſuppoſe garments) and are not ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous about ſpirituall things, which ſhould be acted in a mans ſoule and ſpirit, it is a moſt dangerous ſigne of hypocriſie, thoſe things, ſaith he, ought to be done; you ought to be exceeding carefull, even of tything mint and cummin, you ought to be carefull how you carry your ſelves in every thing in the world, but you ought not to have left the other undone; to put weight upon this, and the ſtrictneſſe of the Goſpell upon this, and yet do far worſe, never looking at the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your own hearts within, and the envyings of your own ſoule, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, but you can for a pin or a point be carefull, this is hypocriſie, neglecting
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119912:61"/> the great things of the Goſpell, theſe ought to be done, but the other ought not to be undone. An hypocrite deales in ſmall ware, as I may ſay, he takes care only for a little outward concernments, and garbe of Religion, that is all.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, This is a diſcoverie of a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite as to duties in generall, wherein his hypocriſie is ſeene, <hi>that he never minds to get the ſpirit of a duty, or to a dutie, that is the holy bleſſed frame of it, but only cares how to act handſomly and takingly in his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties abroad in the world,</hi> (for in truth there is moſt of his actings abroad in the world) he cares not to get the frame and the ſpirit of his dutie, he only cares for a handſome deportment in it.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>frame of a duty in the generall is thus, to get our hearts in a poſture fit for the nature of the duty we are about;</hi> for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The frame of a dutie, and the ſpirit of it, <hi>is to get your heart in a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to meet with God,</hi> that is one thing which a hypocrite never lookes after; how ſhall I meet with God? What frame ſhould I be in when I come to meet with
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119912:62"/> God? What ſhould I meet with God about?</p>
            <p>Secondly, The frame of a duty is <hi>to get the heart ſpiritually behaved before God in a duty:</hi> truly few looke after it. I wiſh that the beſt Saints did looke after it more, but a hypocrite never looks after it at all almoſt, a ſpiritual behaviour that lies in that inward proportion of a mans ſoule before God, according as he is to act to God, or expect from God; if I go to God in a mourning frame, to beg ſomething from him, then can my ſoule behave it ſelfe in that poore and low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as one that expects purelie that which I want from heaven; I ought then to be mightie humble, and in a frame to get that of God; if I come to rejoyce and joy in God, then muſt I be in that frame that all the faculties of my ſoule may rejoyce in him, and be in a heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpirituall tune, this ſhould be the frame of my ſoule, that ſpirituall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour which I cannot tell how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſo well, as in that inward decorum, in that inward proportion of a mans
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119912:62"/> ſoule unto God, according to the nature of his dutie. And then</p>
            <p>Thirdly, which a hypocrite never looks after, <hi>it is to have workings in them ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to expectation, and to what I would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to God,</hi> and expect from God, which a hypocrite never hath, thoſe glorious deſires and breathings in the vigour of my ſoule carried out according to the weight and nature of things; ſo that I ſay all thoſe things ſhew you what is the frame of a hypocrite in a duty: If he can but carrie it on handſomely, with quietneſs, and conveniencie, and come off fairelie to his own conſcience, and to Saints, he little minds what his ſoule hath been do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what his heart hath been acting all the while. And then</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Pray you obſerve this: <hi>That a hypocrite in the midſt of all his zeale, and glory of his duties, he is ſecretly weary of them:</hi> you ſhall find it cleare in your own ſpirits, if ever you have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the workings of this ſin in your ſoules, eſpecially if they be duties that do not bring him in preſent profit, ſome
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119912:63"/> internall, or externall things he wants. This is that which God complaines of in <hi>Malachy, They were weary of the Sabbath,</hi> when will the Sabbath be over that we may go to our buying and ſelling? For the truth is, a hypocrite is but a perfect ſlave and drudge to duties, he is hurried on either by neceſſity within, or ſome luſt or feare which moves him outwardlie, but he is wearie, it is a burthen to him, he hath no freedome at all, for no man can have a freedome that hath not a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; it is againſt his nature, he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it, he hath weights hang upon him that moves him to it; but it is not ſo with a gracious man: <hi>thy Commandements are not grievous,</hi> he can be content to do all duties ever, for ſaies <hi>David, How do I delight in thy Law, it is my meditation day and night:</hi> but a hypocrite can be willing to be free, if it were not on ſome other ground, he thinkes them to be <hi>ſhackles of gold</hi> at the beſt, no more: he cannot be without them, becauſe of thoſe things he laies before him as his ground, and aime, and end: but he would be glad to be
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119912:63"/> handſomelie freed of them. Now with a Saint it is not ſo: his knees may faile, and his hands hang down, but his heart never: he would do all Gods will, and he is ſorry he can do no more than he doth, he is ſorry the body ſhould faile when the ſpirit lives; a Saint ſeldome failes in his heart and will, for the moſt part the will is preſent. I would do more, but I have a cloggy body, and I have a nature which is contrarie to it, but I have a reall will. Now it is not ſo with a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, he is ſecretly weary of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the midſt of all his enjoyments.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, pray take this along with you: <hi>That you have all his Religion in a few duties, take him out of duties and he is a common man:</hi> this will be a triall to your hearts if you put them to it ſeriouſlie; take him out of prayer and preaching (if he be one called to that worke) there is all his Religion, come to any dealing of corruption, there is his beſt part paſt, he is no more religious than he is in theſe duties; whereas Religion is a life out of duties as well as in duties, a man is every
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119912:64"/> where going out after God, Religion will move him and breath in him: but a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite take him out of any dutie he is about, and you have no more Religion, he will be as vaine and fooliſh afterwards as you can imagine; but if ever you would know a Saint, take him out of his duties as well as in his duties; ſee how the feare of the Lord is upon him in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, in every walking, how the dread of the Almightie aws him; but a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite it is a wonder to ſee how flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing he will be in duties; but come and take him out of theſe, he knows in his conſcience there is nothing left, no power, only he was carried out to the dutie by ſomething that lay upon him externallie: therefore lay this to heart.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, all duties that hypocrites do <hi>are but the colourings of ſome corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that they keep privately in their owne hearts,</hi> that they may keep them more undiſcernable from the world, looke to it; all their duties do but cover luſts, do but nouriſh corruptions, they do pray, and heare, but it is to keep in ambition,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119912:64"/> or pride, or luſt, or whatſoever it be, that is all they do, or to keep up a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant kind of correſpondency with their relations: and this advantage a hypocrite makes of his duties, that after he hath done with duties, he takes an advantage to act his corruptions; How many men they go to prayer, if it be a faſt-day, they go to faſt, and after they have done their duties, they thinke they are ſecure, then they may to their luſts and the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine more eagerly, they may then give themſelves a little more way, they have been ſo long in duties, and their hearts are now warme to their corruptions after they have done their duties: Oh theſe are the ſecrets of ſome mens thoughts and hearts; I heard of a known Profeſſor in <hi>London,</hi> who would be all the morning two houres in prayer, and then he would ſay, now let the Devill do his worſt, and then play all his rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; Oh, the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deceits that are in mens hearts, as to deceits in that regard: and ſo a hypocrite if he can but ſhuffle off his duty, thinkes then he may act and ſpeake more freely
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119912:65"/> than if he had not done his duty: this is a wicked ſtraine of hypocriſie that is found in many mens ſpirits. Then again,</p>
            <p>Ninthly, herein lies the hypocriſie of men in duties, <hi>that they can be content with the performance of the duty though they have not dealt with Christ in it, and gotten ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing purely from him in it:</hi> And this, my Brethren, is a certaine veine of hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and the common frame of hypocrites, they will be upon their knees a long time together, and never looke for one recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from Chriſt, and go off their knees, though they have not had any diſcovery of God unto their poore ſoules at all. A Saint, though he ſhould pray like an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, I meane, ſpeake the moſt high and and glorious words in the world, and if he ſhould have all the whole world of Saints to applaud him in his duties, he would hate himſelfe, and abhorre his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and all, if he cannot meet with Chriſt in them it is impoſſible he ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for his ſoule is ſet upon it, and it is that which is the object, that which the ſoule hath in his eye, he cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119912:65"/> Chriſt; The power of a Command will force a hypocrite to his dutie, but the reallitie of the enjoyment is that which a Saint lookes after; If I have not gotten ſome love-token from the Lord Jeſus, if my heart be not in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall frame through the operation of the ſpirit, and communion with Chriſt, the ſoule is not ſatisfied; looke to your ſoules what manner of frames you have.</p>
            <p>Tenthly and laſtly, to adde no more at this time; <hi>A Hypocrite never grows in or by his duties at all,</hi> he is the ſame man he was to his corruptions and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he may grow more fluent in his expreſſions, mannage them externally more neatlie, have an eaſineſſe of utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and a frequencie, but he grows not at all, as to inward ſpirituall enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his corruptions never dye, and this is a ſad ſymptome to many ſouls that have run a long time in duties, and no body can perceive the leaſt ſenſible growth in the world, nor they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though they have lived ſo long
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119912:66"/> under the Goſpell of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, praying zealouſlie with much heartineſſe, one would thinke, and no fruit, no corruptions mortified, there is no more inward apprehenſions of things, no more growth than if they had never begun the Goſpell, now, I ſay, that is hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            <p>Now ſome may ſay, what is it to grow in duties?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then a man grows in and by duties, <hi>when a man is more endeared to the ſpirituall nature of thoſe things,</hi> his heart more affected with the heavenly nature of what he is about.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, Then a man grows in and by duties, <hi>when the ſoule finds more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power to performe his duties,</hi> he goes on more eaſilie, more ſpirituallie, and more freelie.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, Then a man grows <hi>when a man is fitted by one duty to performe another:</hi> when in one dutie, I pray now, I can pray anon in my own heart, as to the inward frame, I do not ſpeake of the outward expreſſion, for that will grow
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119912:66"/> by cuſtome, but now I heare, and I can heare better the next time, be more open to take in the things of God: he grows in it; ſo it is as to meditation and ſelfe examination, when I can come and try my own heart now, and I can every day get more ſpirituall inſight into my own ſoule.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, I grow in and by my duties, <hi>when as I get a dayly life in them,</hi> an addition, a vigour, and ſpirit, and life, that whereas I began with a fainting ſpirit, and feeble knees, my heart now grows warmer every day, my ſpirit grows ſtronger: and as a Child finds dayly ſtrength and vigour of ſpirit, ſo I find a vigour in my ſpirit. A hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite runs his round, he grows not at all, there is no ſpirituall motion in him, but juſt the ſame as to the inward frame of his heart; though you and I may thinke he grows, yet he doth not grow, for all growth is by an addition to the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; if you ſhould ſee a heape of ſtones heaped up, you do not ſay it grows, it is not a growth, but an adding ſtones to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119912:67"/> ſtones, it muſt be in the degrees, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and life of the ſame nature, there lies growth.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now have come to the ſecond thing, which is <hi>hypocriſie of men in prayer,</hi> which is a thing eſpeciallie to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, for there is nothing a hypocrite is more excellent in, than in prayer, and nothing he eſteemes more than that; and there is nothing by which a hypocrite gets more eſteeme and a better opinion in the world than by prayer, for it is a dutie ſo much commended in the Goſpel, that all the worſhip of God is placed in it. <hi>My houſe ſhall be called the houſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> it is made the Character of a Saint: behold he praies; it is that which every Saint hath need of every moment, and it is is that the Saints are moſt in of any other duty in the world, and there is the greateſt excellency of a hypocrite of any thing, and to diſcover him there, you would find him out to purpoſe; for a man in prayer, if he hath got that curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, as ſome have done, he ſpeakes as if he were wraſtling with the Almightie,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119912:67"/> and as if he were prompted by ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical ſpirit, and aſſiſted by a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſpirit from above, that a man thinks he is a perfect Saint if he have a mightie fluencie as to expreſſion. I ſhould in many particulars have ſhewed you the deceit of this.</p>
            <p>But I will conclude all with a word or two of Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> Firſt, to every ſoule to looke to his own heart in his duties, there is moſt hypocriſie in duties, more than in any other way of acting, there is the cloſeſt hypocriſie in a mans duties that can be: there is his pride, and ſelfe-ends acted to purpoſe, all other actings are but groſſe, a man may ſee them eaſilie, but as to duties they are carried ſo cloſely no man can know them; Alas, if a man ſhould be found in his Studie alwaies praying, who would not thinke him an excellent Saint? yet he may be the perfecteſt hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite in the world, nothing of God and Chriſt in his prayer, it is not the length or the meaſure you muſt looke after, nor how you have acted them, but how you
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119912:68"/> are moved and acted in them: Oh, my Brethren, moſt glorious Profeſſors in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will be found another day in ſtrange frames before God. We have preached in thy name, O Lord, ſay they, ſo Lord we have prayed night and day, kept all meetings in the Towne or place where we lived, and been at ſo many faſts, and kept all publike daies, and kept them cloſely: Yea ſoule, ſo thou maieſt: but if you have no more than that, depart from me, I know you not; you are no better, you never minded me, you never had the frame of the Goſpell in your own ſpirits, you never knew what it was to be out of your duties, and have the workings of my power in your hearts, you never knew what it was to denie your ſelves in your duties, to be made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for my name and glory.</p>
            <p>Secondly and laſtly, I beſeech you (my Brethren) be not content with any thing but what is purely of God, what is a reality in the Goſpell, pure realities. Truly, my Brethren, the faireſt faces will one day looke like death when God
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119912:68"/> comes to view them; be more afraid in duties than in any other way, the moſt ſpritefull men in duties, that we little thinke of, will be wrinckled like old men one day upon a ſudden when God comes to deale with them about the things of the Goſpell; be more afraid of your ſelves in duties than in any other way, for though you are in the waies of God as to outward actings, yet you are under the moſt ſpirituall temptations that can be, you will wonder to ſee one day how many thouſands will be placed at the left hand, that have paſſed through all the formes of duties to the uttermoſt; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not content with any thing, but what you find perfectly reall, bring it to the touchſtone againe, and againe, let it be written with the Sun-beames in your hearts; looke to your principles and ends, mind the vigour and ſtraines of your ſpirits in duties, obſerve at what rate you act, ſtill be looking that way; Oh, to be a ſound Chriſtian is a moſt glorious thing. Give me that ſoule that can ſay, I have many things that I am
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119912:69"/> aſhamed of before God night and day, but I am ſound, I am reall, though I were to be ſearched by God. I have that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that inward ſinceritie, that is, not only a ſimplicity of ſpirit, but ſuch a ſhining judgement upon my own condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I know how I ſtand before God, and I know whom I have belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and how I have beleeved, and how I have prayed, and heard in the Goſpell; I know it, the divine ſpirit was in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in ſuch a place, in ſuch a corner, the Holy Ghoſt was in my ſpirit; I know that I was carried out in ſuch a duty meerly by the life and ſtrength of God, when I had no power, when I was as weake as water: Oh! this would be a comfort indeed to a poore ſoule. Many are glad to be lulled aſleepe, if they can but be ſaid to be religious and ſaints, and follow the things of the Goſpell, they thinke they are happy. No, ſoule: thou muſt have a principle in thy ſoule, and an eternall worke upon thee; thou muſt know what God is, and what Chriſt is, and what God in Chriſt is, what it is to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119912:69"/> have thy corruptions ſtruck at the heart, and be laid as low as hell in thy owne ſoule, before ever thou enjoy any thing of God in thy owne ſoule. And when thou haſt done ſo, thou muſt try all over againe by a ſpirit of fire and burning, and have not only thy own reaſon to witneſſe, but the Holy Ghoſt and Scriptures to witneſſe to what is in thy heart, to what thy conſcience ſpeakes, and all theſe things will be brought to you one day, though you looke ſlightly over them now.</p>
            <p>Oh that men would be carefull to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void hypocriſie, this wicked leaven that is in ſo many ſoules, to diſcerne the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that workes in every part ſo inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: Beg of God a ſpirit of ſinceritie, to keep you from your own hearts, beg of the Lord that he never would leave you under any ſlight ordinarie common wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of ſpirit, but put you to it every day, ſhew you your own frames, never be quiet untill you find thoſe reall things, and then having a little grace, yet if in ſinceritie, you will find your ſoules in a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119912:70"/> happy eſtate: Oh you ſoules that have this mercie from God, bleſſe him, and magnifie him for ever, you have the earneſt of immortalitie in your owne ſoules.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119912:70"/>
            <head>SERMON V.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LUKE 12.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, which is Hypocriſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have in many exerciſes endeavoured to open to you the nature of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, what kinds and ſorts of hypocrites there are in the world; and the laſt time you may remember we ſhewed you the actings of hypocriſie, as to duties in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, for hypocriſie is moſt acted in duties; a man may find out his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits in many things more eaſilie than in duties, for in duties there are ſuch faire colours, no man knows how to diſcover himſelfe or others, if he be not carefull in his own heart.</p>
            <p>But there were three things propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119912:71"/> at the latter end, which we could not come to: not only as to duties in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall;</p>
            <p>But firſt the hypocriſie of men in prayer, and how a hypocrite is diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, as to communion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Saints and godly perſons.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, as to his carriage in the world, thoſe three we would ſpeake to at this time.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Hypocriſie as to prayer, which is a dutie that hypocrites moſt glory in of any; that is the dutie wherein Saints get ſo much of God, and have ſo much experience of God in, it is a dutie that is uſed as the common way to get whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a ſoule would have; <hi>let your requeſts be made known to God,</hi> therefore there is no dutie a hypocrite is more exact in than that, for he imitates a Saint, that is the nature of a hypocrite that he imitates a Saint in thoſe duties he is moſt in, that he gets moſt by: none knows the incomes that Saints have in the dutie of prayer, how much of God is let into them, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119912:71"/> how much their ſoules are let out unto God, when none know it; it is a dutie that is of that requeſt among thoſe that are godlie, that if a hypocrite be not good at that, he is good at nothing, if he be not very curious there he will be of little account; for it is common for one to deſire to pray one for another, and with one another, abundance of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes come by it in a ſpirituall way; and therefore that is the care of a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite to do that well whatever he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, and you ſhall find that as to their parts they never excell ſo much as in that dutie, wherein they excell and go beyond many Saints, as to the outward perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it. I ſhall ſhew their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie therefore as to this.</p>
            <p>And firſt in generall, <hi>know that all that a hypocrite doth, as to prayer, is from an art of it, not from a ſpirit of it within him;</hi> ſome do diſtinguiſh it thus, between a gift of prayer, and a grace of prayer; but I had rather take it in theſe termes, for graces are gifts, and we muſt come and diſtinguiſh again and againe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119912:72"/> gifts, and ſpirituall gifts, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall gifts, and ſupernaturall gifts of ſuch a kind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this is cleare, that all that ever a hypocrite doth in prayer is from an artificiall motion in his ſpirit; my meaning is thus: he hath gotten by induſtrie, by imitation, by converſe, by cuſtome, and uſe in that dutie, ſuch an art, that there is nothing either belongs to prayer, or the exact performance of it outwardlie, but he hath it with more abundant curioſitie than the beſt Saint hath, that he ſtrives to perfect himſelfe in exceedinglie.</p>
            <p>But take this for the generall rule, that is rather from an art than from the ſpirit prayer, and many times he gets the art ſo curiouſlie, that he refreſheth many Saints and poore ſouls by it, though he have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the ſenſe of it on his own heart; he acts that part ſo exactlie and carefullie to the ſight of men, that it works much upon the affections of all that heare him, and converſe with him: This I ſpeake now as to thoſe that are moſt carefull. Indeed there be ſome ſorts of hypocrites that are
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119912:72"/> not ſo curious, that are rather for a meer outward forme, and are very dead in it, and make it up ſome other way, but take hypocriſie in generall, it is ſeene moſt in prayer.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie to diſcover this hypocriſie to you as to the art.</p>
            <p>Firſt, know, that <hi>the great ſtudy of a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite is about his expreſſions more than for any impreſſions, or any reall ſights of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his condition or estate;</hi> as if he were to mourne for ſin, and open his own heart, he ſtudies to ſet it out in the moſt melting way, though his heart be not melted, or if he be to ſet out the love of God, he will do it with the exacteſt expreſſions, but he finds not the love of Chriſt conſtraining, and thoſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons flowing from that love in his heart.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, as to that, as his expreſſions, <hi>ſo his greatest enlargements in that duty of prayer is when he is moſt in publike, not ſo much in private and ſecret dealings with his own heart;</hi> this is now to thoſe that deale with others, dead at home, enlarged
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119912:73"/> abroad: Oh my Brethren, this is a moſt wicked frame of hypocriſie in that duty, when men look at their words, not at their hearts, to make their hearts ſpeake within them; if I be enlarged in prayer when I am with others, and dead when I am in private, it is a certaine ſigne I have nothing in my heart, only ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gales fill my ſailes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as to that know, there is a <hi>ſecret rejoycing in the very manner of the expreſſions of a mans wants or of his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> whatſoever he deſires of God, which none but thoſe find that have to deale with thoſe things in their owne hearts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, And which is as to expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions againe, know that a hypocrite, in the fourth place, <hi>is more troubled when he wants an enlargement as to expreſſions, than when he wants a power of affection to duties, and to God,</hi> according to the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of what he is to act in that dutie; a Saint can content himſelfe more with a ſigh and a groane, than all the externall enlargements that can be; if a hypocrite
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119912:73"/> can be enlarged as to gifts, he can eaſily diſpenſe with ſome deadneſſe as to the frame of his owne heart, pray you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that; if you cannot be in your clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet as vehement in ſighs and groanes as if you were in companie with others, if your inward motions do not prompt you to as much vehemencie of ſoule to go out to God to beg what you want, and longings after him to enjoy what he hath communicable to your ſoules, when alone as well as when before others, it is a dangerous ſymptome of hypocriſie, it is a ſigne certainly that I have ſomewhat at the bottome that is not ſound; therefore conſider that.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to particulars, know, <hi>that a hypocrite loves to lengthen out his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties when he is to performe them before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to hurrie them over in private;</hi> truly moſt Profeſſours are as Papiſts in that, for they tell over their private du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as ſo many beads, till they come to a publike Maſſe, then they are ſolemne, but there is nothing of Religion in all thoſe things: if they come to company, then
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119912:74"/> they do every thing circumſtantially, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, then they lengthen them out ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to time and every proportion, and this is a very cloſe diſcovery of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie in any ſoule, that is ſlight in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and can hurry over his duties there, yet can be mighty ſolemne when he is in a publike place; pray you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Take this for a Rule, a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite both in private and publike pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>he flags at laſt,</hi> this will come cloſe to every ones heart, the longer he prayes the worſe he is, the heart more dead, beſt at firſt, at the beginning he is zealous: it may be ſence of wants preſſes him, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing holds him up, but the longer he goes on the worſe he is. But the contrary is now in a Saint, the longer he is with God, the more his heart is with him, he grows in his duties; though he be dead at firſt, he will be ſure to get ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of God, ſome quicknings, ſome enlivenings, though he have been long getting up his heart to a duty, yet when once it is up, he finds the water flows in,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119912:74"/> the more he is with God, the more he gets up his ſoule, the divine nature gets more breath and ſtrength by breathing after God, the longer it breaths the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it breaths; a hypocrite hath much adoe to keep up his affections to the firſt ſtart, either privately, or publikely, hardly able to keep in his ſpirit, but he is at a loſs as to the divine nature of thoſe things as to the glory of them; therefore he is fain to pumpe and ſtrain for expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions when his affections are loſt; this you will find as a perfect ſecret in your own hearts that know and are privie to your own ſoules.</p>
            <p>The Spirit may indeed withdraw ſometimes, but takes it commonly and ordinarily, the ſoule is never ſo moved as when it is touched in the heart; but a hypocrite you ſhall have his duties done very ſleightlie at the latter end, when there ſhould be moſt vigour, but you ſhall find the duties of Saints, when once the ſoule begins to get heat and warmth with the love of Chriſt, and ſence of wants, and pure thoughts of the love of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119912:75"/> Jeſus Chriſt, it can pray everlaſtinglie, if he had a body fit to his ſoule he could be alwaies praying; and though a Saint may faile in expreſſions towards the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, yet his affections are higher, he can hardly leave Chriſt, or the thoughts of him, he would be alwaies with him; there is abundance of adoe to get up our hearts to any frame, but when once it is up, and goes on with the ſtrength of God, then he finds new aſſiſtance every moment comming in; you ſhall have a hypocrite at firſt, like a fountaine, flowing in expreſſions, but he begins to grow low at laſt, and juſt ſo much water let out as may maintaine him for a while, and turne his wheele and motion: but take a Saint, he is commonlie beſt at laſt, as to faith, and ſpirituall workings in his own heart; And this, my Brethren, will a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you of the nature of hypocriſie as to prayer; for a hypocrite acts for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and from ſelf-ſtrength, and any artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall motion, as a Clock or ſo, grows ſlower at latter end, untill it be woond up againe; ſo it is really with thoſe men.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:119912:75"/>
            <p>Fourthly, The hypocriſie of men in prayer is ſeen in this, <hi>that an hypocrite ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver goes with an abſolute preſent ſence of his needs of aſſiſtance, or of acceptance, either of the Spirits power, or of Chriſts interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> if he go to Chriſt for ſtrength, it is to employ it to his own ends. But, my Brethren, there is no Saint goes to a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ordinarilie and commonly, but he goes with that deep ſence of that perfect need he hath of the Holy Ghoſt to ſupply him, he can do nothing; though he have parts, yet he ſees he muſt have his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, elſe he cannot act, and when he hath acted, he ſees as much need of accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at laſt as of aſſiſtance at firſt. A hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite acts meerlie from his owne ſtrength; in ſome extraordinarie dutie it may be he may caſt up his eye, and ſay, Lord carry me on in this extraordinary dutie, but commonly in prayer he never fees the need of the Holy Ghoſt to teach him how to pray, how to move to God, and what to pray, and that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould hold out his mediation, and ſtand betweene him and the Father to make a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119912:76"/> perfect attonement; there is nothing will diſcover hypocriſie more than this, if you do but conſider it ſeriouſly; for there is no hypocrite that ever was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottomed of himſelfe, his own ſtrength, that ever ſaw the eternall conſtant need of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That I may not hold you long; a hypocrite in his duties <hi>he praies for thoſe things with ſeeming earneſtneſſe that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prized, nor knew the worth of;</hi> He praies for pardon, it may be elegantlie, with exceeding affections, as to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but he never knew what it was to have pardon, to have divine incomes in his heart; he praies for enjoyments of Chriſt, but yet he never knew the worth of an enjoyment of Chriſt; and that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſcovered in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>In that he can quiet himſelfe with common hopes of him;</hi> I hope I ſhall have him, though now I have him not, and ſo takes his duties inſtead of Chriſt for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; he can pray for Chriſt, and yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelfe with a generall common ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion that he will ſhew himſelfe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119912:76"/> good at laſt, though he have no earneſt preſſing, nor longing for him at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is ſeen in this, <hi>that the ſoule ſecretly diſlikes what he praies for, as to thoſe enjoyments, as to the power, and ſpirit, and life of them;</hi> there is no hypocrite, but if he pray for to be transformed, to be made like unto Chriſt, and be ſanctified, but oh, he hath a ſecret regret, when he comes to the practicall part of it, he could rather wiſh there were no ſuch thing, or he had ſtood upon his own bottome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and eſpeciallie it is ſeen in this, <hi>that thoſe things are matter of petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not any ground of endeavour after the enjoyment of them,</hi> they are only the bare matter of Petition: I pray for them, and ſeek after them, but I never endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for them; I pray for Chriſt, but never look after him; I pray to have my ſins mortified, but I never take the courſe to have that vertue, and that power from Chriſt that may kill my corruptions: we only put it into our prayers as comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall acts and no more. Thoſe prayers
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119912:77"/> that are not accompanied with earneſt heartie endeavours to get the things prayed for, according to the rule pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, are hypocriticall. I pray I may be pardoned, and I go on in ſin, and never looke after the mediation of the Lord Jeſus, nor ſtudy how theſe bleſſed conveyances are made over to my ſoule; Oh there is a mightie ſtraine as to that.</p>
            <p>Sixthlie, A hypocrite in <hi>prayer calls God Father by his own ſpirit, not by the ſpirit of adoption,</hi> pray you obſerve that; by his own ſpirit, for he hath not the ſpirit of prayer, which is the ſpirit of adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; now that you may know the ſpirit of prayer, what the meaning of that is, he calls God Father by his own ſpirit, not by the ſpirit of adoption.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>He goes not to God from an inward ſence of fatherly love,</hi> there is no hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite in the world but he hath a ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward frame of ſpirit, whereby he looks upon God as an enemie, and judge to him in his greateſt enlargements; he goes not to God from the ſence of fatherlie love,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119912:77"/> though he may call God father with abundance of varietie in expreſſion; pray you conſider that: no man can call God father but from the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but from the ſence of his love ſhed abroad in his heart in prayer; I go to him, becauſe his love as well as my needs workes me up to go to him, the taſtes of the ſweetneſſe of that fatherlie love workes up my heart, I cannot but go to him.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, <hi>this ſpirit of prayer lies in that ſutableſſe of a ſon-like affection unto God:</hi> that ſutableneſſe of a ſon-like affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and nature unto God, whereby I go as a Son unto a Father. Now that is certaine, a hypocrite hath no relation to God, he never minds him as a father, he hath not that inward propenſitie, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward love and affection unto God as a Son, which lies in the working of the heart inwardlie unto God as unto a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as it is in nature, ſo it is in grace; take a child, and tell him it is his Father, from once he knows it is his Father, there will be an inward working towards
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119912:78"/> him more than to any perſon in the world, there will be ſome diſpoſition in the heart that will anſwer preſently your repreſentation of him as a Father; ſo it is in the Goſpell, when you go to the Father, there will be ſomething that will anſwer this; <hi>thou art our Father, though</hi> Abraham <hi>be ignorant of us:</hi> the ſoule muſt cry <hi>Abba, Father:</hi> that no hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite can do in the world, he cannot act as to a Father, but his own ſpirit prompts him: ſtrength either of his neceſſities, or the ſtrength of his abilities carries him on.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, know this as to a hypocrite in prayer: <hi>his heart failes him when his enlargements faile him,</hi> which is contrary to a Saint, which is contrarie to the heart of a Saint; his heart though he can but groane, though he can but chatter as a Crane, yet his heart is up, if he have any promiſe, there he hangs, if he can have any thing to build up his ſoule in, it keeps up his heart, any twig to hang on. But nothing but comforts and enlargements can keep up the heart of a hypocrite; but
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119912:78"/> a Saint from the inward working of the Spirit can keep up, though he ſhould have nothing elſe; but a hypocrite in duties, if he ſhould be but once denied enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he is as dead as a ſtock. Take but a Saint under a promiſe, though he wants enlargements, let God ſhame me as to that, I have enough in the promiſe, and the inward groanings of my ſoule are more to me than all enlargements.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, take in this too: a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite ſhews his hypocriſie in prayer, <hi>that he makes his prayer his ſhift upon every turne, upon every occaſion, it is his prayer beares him up ſtill.</hi> After that he hath done any thing that is unſutable to the Goſpel, if he can but go and powre out a prayer he is well enough; his prayer is that which charmes him into quietneſſe after guilt; by prayer he gets his eaſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires to it; if he have committed ſome fault in his ordinary courſe of life as to his relations, if he can but go to prayer, there is all his life and refuge, that is all; he licks himſelfe whole by prayer: for it is a dutie man ſhould go to God in, and a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119912:79"/> dutie of drawing a ſoule to God, and when I beg of God pardon, I am ſo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted, though I never get the ground of pardon, he cannot be quiet untill he hath been upon his knees, and then he is well, this is his common ſhift: but a Saint can never be quiet, though he pray night and day, untill he hath gotten in prayer Chriſts bloud, and have hold upon Chriſt as the attonement and propitiation.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, Then eſpeciallie take in but this, that I may adde no more upon this head; if he can but <hi>ninthly get teares in prayer, then he is well, for he makes his teares to waſh away his guilt,</hi> and mingles his teares with Chriſts bloud; if he can but blubber his cheeks in teares, oh how is he content? how much is he ſatisfied? whereas teares are the moſt dangerous ſignes of Hypocriſie in the world, if they be not the juyce of a broken ſpirit, the droppings of a melted heart, the dews of a ſoule that hath been under the ſights of love; there is the moſt dangerous ſignes of hypocriſie that can be poſſible, that when a mans prayers are bedewed with
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119912:79"/> teares, then he is well, he hath then no need of Chriſts bloud, he mingles his teares with his ſacrifices, and that is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction enough at preſent. You will in theſe things ſee enough of your owne hearts, if you have had any dealing with them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Now let us view a hypocrite as to his converſe with Saints, his commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, and ſee how we can trace him there.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the generall you muſt know, <hi>he is very carefull to keep in, and keep a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie with Saints:</hi> elſe he would be a profane perſon, and would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by Saints, all his ſtrivings are that he may keep in there, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſteales in ſo ſecretly, ſo cloſelie among them, that none knows how he is gotten in.</p>
            <p>But you ſhall ſee his hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This is the hypocriſie of men as to converſe Saints, <hi>that they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward prejudices against convincing wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Saints (if there be any ſuch in the world,)</hi> he will be ſure to have his heart
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119912:80"/> worke ſecretly againſt them, however he carry it to themſelves, he hath a ſecret inward regret againſt cloſe convincing walking Saints. I would I could ſpeake that word ſo loud that it might be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, for it is hard to find ſuch a Saint in the world; yet take one that hath a watchfull and obſervant eye, he cares ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little for his company, but only for a deſigne.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, as to converſes with Saints, <hi>a hypocrite labours alwaies to dreſſe himſelfe ſo, that he may be very handſome when he goes abroad: that is his care alwaies, he cares not how he is at home, how careleſſe, and neglective, how ſleight in his duties, how unworthy in his actings,</hi> ſo he may but keep up a faire correſpondencie with thoſe he is ſtill abroad with; he will ſpeake much of heaven and Chriſt, tell you of repentance, and experiences abroad: but oh, not a word of examining his owne ſoule, or a word of God at home, and this is the moſt wicked ſtraine of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie that can be, for all his deſigne is to gather all the good thoughts of men up
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119912:80"/> and down the world, keep himſelfe ſo, that if he ſhould come to fall or falter (as he feares he ſhall) he might have abundance of votes of good men for him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as to converſe with Saints, <hi>an hypocrite hath an affected tone, or garbe, or carriage, whereby a man may be thought to be ſingular, to have ſomewhat more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary of mortification, or ſpirituall ſtraines of glory:</hi> this is as wicked a ſtraine of hypocriſie as can be; Some men affect a particular tone of language, or expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome a whining expreſſion, ſome ſo neatly, and others ſo ſeriouſlie, that they would be thought to be grave and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſober men and Chriſtians, and they have an affected tone of their own; it is the vaineſt way of hypocriſie that can be to ſpeake of divine things, as if they were whining them out, and weeping them out, and ſpeaking with ſuch geſtures as may give the world too much ground to make Religion ridiculous, whereas their naturall language is not ſo, but they have affected ſuch a way and garbe that they
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119912:81"/> would be thought ſome body; and this, that in praying, and preaching, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with ſome perſons, they would be thought to be them alone that take in all the ſence of things, and they have no more ſence than Poſts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, which is a maine one, as to converſe with Saints, <hi>a hypocrite hath his heart riſing againſt a cloſe, faithfull, nipping reproofe of other Saints. Saul</hi> could never endure <hi>Samuel</hi> after he told him ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully about that buſineſſe of his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, out of my ſight, ſo you have many inſtances about the Prophets and the Kings, <hi>you have ſome hypocrites carries it ſo cunningly, that they will take a reproofe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, but hate you ever after,</hi> have an evill eye upon you that you muſt keep out of the way of him; a hypocrite would not have others know his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, he is afraid he ſhall here ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he knows he is guiltie of, and he cannot abide that, he would be thought ſomewhat by others, though he knows ſomewhat by himſelfe: he is afraid he will be put to it, which he cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119912:81"/> to have his graces queſtioned; that is a perfect ſigne of a hypocrite as any in the world; he would have all men take it for granted: what, not I a Saint? that have been accounted a Profeſſour ſo long, and now be queſtioned for my graces? yea ſoule, and be damned for it too: thou a ſoule that cannot endure to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? I confeſſe there be ſome waies of reproofe that would make a man hate reproofe, when it is for things that are common, when it is for poore and vaine things, when done out of paſſion, and not done with care and tenderneſſe to a perſon, and with the weight of the glory of God upon a man, it is hard for the beſt Saint to take a reproofe ſo; but when there is faithfulneſſe, and realitie to men, dealing with their ſoules, and purely touching their conſciences, and riſings of heart, and then cannot endure reproofe: I may ſay, if thou be not a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, or will prove one, there is none in the world: it is a ſigne thou art dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh proud in thy heart, and loveſt a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and haſt a luſt thou art loath
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119912:82"/> to part with, and would'ſt gladly cover in thy owne ſpirit, thou wouldſt live at large, and not have thy heart known to thy ſelfe, nor others; thou wouldſt live at large, thou loveſt ſome corruption. A Saint deſires to have corruption killed every day: Oh that I did but know wherein the flaw lies of my graces, wherein the miſtake in my owne ſpirit lies, he would be glad of it. Thou art a wicked hypocrite that loveſt not a ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cloſe reproofe, though it cut thee at the heart; and then I would ſay this: that it is the perfect character of a Saint, if he can take in a reproofe in the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt manner, from the ſharpeſt tongue in the world, if it diſcover his corruption, and ſtrike at it, it is a ſigne a man is out of love with his ſins, and wants a way only to be rid of them, he is glad when it is made odious to him by any body.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>The ſtraine of hypocriſie, as to communion, lies in this, that a hypocrite doth inwardly ſleight and contemne Saints below him, and envy Saints above him,</hi> you will find it too true in the hearts of many: he
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119912:82"/> ſleights firſt any that is below him, he hath a poore and low eſteeme of them, he is a poore ignorant fellow that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not any thing of God, though it may be the breathings of that poore ſoule unto God are far beyond his: he lives in himſelfe, and any that are below himſelfe are under ſome reflections of the inward workings of his owne heart. Then he hath a ſecret envy againſt them that are above him, he lives ſo that he would alwaies be at one ſtay and frame, he cannot abide that any ſhould attaine more than himſelfe, if they do, they are proud, or high, or vaine; and if they do not come up to him, he thinks him a poor low profeſſour, though his ſoule be groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning night and day after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Sixthlie, Another ſtraine of hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is commonly in this, that <hi>a hypocrite is mighty cenſorious and prying abroad into other mens faults, and ſleight and careleſſe for the ſeeing to his own heart for the ſame thing, or worſe;</hi> this is Chriſts Charge to the Phariſees, Caſt out the beame, thou hypocrite, out of thine own eye before
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119912:83"/> thou find fault with the mote in thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; he hath a beame at home in his own eye, and he will not charge his own ſoule before God: he can ſee a little thing in another, charge him with all unſutableſſe: but to his own conſcience, though he fee many a deſperate corrrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his own heart, he lets it alone, as if he never were the man guilty of them, Eagle-eyed abroad, Owle-eyed at home; take heed of cenſuring, elſe you had need be very through at home; it is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſigne of hypocriſie if you be not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious at home: if a man be thorough with his own ſpirit he may be thorough abroad, Chriſt gives it himſelfe as a ſign of a perfect hypocrite; when <hi>a ſoule ſhall ſee a mote in anothers eye, and leave a beame in his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, Hypocriſie lies in this as to communion with Saints, <hi>that a hypocrite cannot love Saints but of one ſize, one that agrees with him in his own humour and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;</hi> That you will find in the New Teſtament, the Phariſees could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure them that were not of their owne
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119912:83"/> opinion, they would perſecute them to the death; ſo ſome men cannot endure any one, though never ſo much grace and grace and godlineſſe, if they be not of the ſame opinion, that is a ſigne it is not for holineſſe or grace in any ſoule that you affect them.</p>
            <p>In the eighth and laſt place, to adde no more as to this, know as to converſe with Saints: <hi>Every hypocrite hath his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret back doore, and veine with carnall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours,</hi> though he have communion with Saints now and then, and make that his profeſſion, yet he hath his private haunts, where he ſhews himſelfe in his colours one way or other, ſome ſecret waies of iniquitie he hath with others, though he profeſſes to be in communion with Saints; that will appeare, and doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare often, for ſtill his veine lies that way, his humour lies that way, though his eye ſeems to be this way, there is the humour hid that way in the man, and there will be as familiar embraces among the one as the other when it comes, and as heartie kind of rejoycings with the one
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119912:84"/> as with the other. A ſecret wicked back doore that they take, and they thinke there will be none to tell: Now they will be telling of the greateſt experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and anon in the greateſt wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, at leaſt countenancing of them. I would now come to the third thing, wherein it is acted as to civill converſes and I ſhall ſhow you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That a hypocrite can put on any face according to any perſons or times in the world;</hi> among Saints he will be a Saint, and comply with them, among others be as ſutable, he can take up any forme, ſo Religion be that that may cover all at laſt, for he fits his actings to his ends, which are various according to ſeverall parties, and companies; and ſeverall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties ſhall have ſeverall actings, he will be zealous if the times will admit it, he will be hot and violent, and if his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany will not ſerve him to that, he will be as dull, as heavy againe, put on a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber temper, and weare gray haires, be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and criticall, and ſerious in the Goſpell; and this is very common, my
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119912:84"/> Brethren, and this is the politike hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite; there are hundreds of theſe in the world, they ſwarme up and down <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at this day, men that have no more Religion than beaſts, as to power and principles in their owne ſpirits: turne every way, and every where with the times.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe men ſhew their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie in this, <hi>they make Religion ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to every principle of men, and every deſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in converſes about civill things, <hi>he will wipe his mouth at ſmall and little things.</hi> A little oath ſometimes, a covert lyes, ſpeaks very demurely, hardly gotten out, (as it were) he can paſſe it by as his common infirmitie; if he tell a little lye in a bargaine, ſpare me in this, ſaies he, to go to the houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> he will take his allowance though it be not given him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>He ſtudies perfectly to pleaſe men,</hi> and he is troubled more when he diſpleaſes men, than when he finds his heart unſutable to God.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:119912:85"/>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>He cares to keep off ſcandall to his perſon more than guilt from his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> no matter if he can keep off ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall though guilt lies faſt.</p>
            <p>Then ſixthly and laſtly, to ſay no more, <hi>ſuch a hypocrite as this in all his converſes will meddle no more with Religion than may fit his Calling, and his Relations.</hi> As the King of <hi>Navar</hi> ſaid, he would launch no further into the deeps than he might come in againe with the ſame wind, no farther then ſight of the ſhoare; ſo it is with hypocrites, if ſuch a way of God be never ſo pretious and pure, I will not meddle with it, I muſt take care to my Familie, not to my ſoule; therefore the waies of Chriſt never come into counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance with ſuch men till it be countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the world, you ſhall never have them hot and zealous till the State have made way for them: you ſhall never have them care for Religion, where the power muſt be practiſed, till the State do it.</p>
            <p>I have done in one word, that is, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you take heed and beware of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119912:85"/> it is that which is in every duty, in every act you do, when you act faireſt you are in moſt danger of hypocriſie; when you think you are lying in the duſt, you are not free from the moſt deſperate hypocriſie; when you think you are wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out your heart for ſin, you are not free from that damnable leaven of hypocriſie; when your contemplations are ſo high, as you thinke you are abſtracted from all the world, and the enjoyments of it, that you imagine you are up in glorie, yet you will ſee that hypocriſie is a ſecret ſpirit that runs through all your actings, it is ſuch a ſecret thing that it will mingle with your beſt duties, and make you hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites in the very acting of them: Oh! that men would but look to it, nothing like pureneſſe, ſincerity, reality, inward integrity, to be true to God and my own conſcience, to take my heart every day and cut it in peeces by a ſpirituall inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and daylie triall, nothing like it, after every duty to aske my ſoule what is done, after every prayer to anatomize every petition againe, and know how it
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119912:86"/> was in the frame and workings, and the anſwers and returnes, and the bleſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it upon my heart, nothing will do well elſe; what a diſſection will it be when an old hypocrite will be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? What that will be none knows yet, what a conſumed Lungs, and Liver, and Heart will there be, ſtrangely eaten out, and none knows how it comes; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the body will be well liking, all the fleſh faſt and ſound, nothing but the vitals eaten, ſtrangely eaten as with a Moath and Canker; It will be ſo with you, I beſeech you feare leſt it grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you: Beware of hypocriſie, look to it every day, for it is in every duty; and above all things looke after that cleare, pure, ſincere temperature, and integrity of ſpirit in every dutie, whereby you may walke with God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:119912:86"/>
            <head>SERMON VI.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LUKE 12.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, which is Hypocriſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have ſhewed you in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall exerciſes what the characters of hypocriſie is, what they are in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtates, how to trace them in duties in generall, in prayer eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, in communion of Saints, in actings in the world, and civill reſpects.</p>
            <p>But you may remember, at the firſt opening of the words, I told you that there were ſome ſorts of hypocrites that did not ſo much diſcover themſelves, but muſt be diſcovered by the truths of the Goſpell that are propounded, they are not ſo conſciencious of want of integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as they are wanting in principles; thoſe
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119912:87"/> we have moſt endeavoured to diſcover.</p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place I told you, ſome there are that know themſelves to be ſo, at leaſt they have ſecret conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous checks of conſcience, yet go on in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: I would a little ſpeake to them at preſent, and then make application of the whole.</p>
            <p>There are many, I ſay, that knows themſelves to be unſound in their owne ſpirits and yet go on in profeſſion, and that you would thinke ſtrange; <hi>and it is more ſtrange to thinke a man ſhould be a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite and not know it: than that a man ſhould know his hypocriſie and yet go on in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall in the opening of this ſhew you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it may be ſo, and that it is often ſo, and moſt hypocrites ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall diſcover how it can be that they can go on in profeſſion ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily and freely as they do.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Wherein their hypocriſie ſtill lies.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:119912:87"/>
            <p>Firſt, That it may be ſo, and that they do go on ſo, I ſhall make it cleare in theſe particulars; <hi>and I beſeech you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Take the common principle of a naturall conſcience, which is enlightned, (for every hypocrite hath an enlightned conſcience) it is not ſo dull as it is in other men, unleſſe it be after a long time of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; but the naturall conſcience of a man will tell him thus, that this is not right, you do not this according to this rule, for there is a light left in a mans conſcience till God give a man over to blindneſſe and darkneſſe, there is is a light will alwaies give a man a check without there be ſome eminent thing to ſilence conſcience at the preſent, as it was with the Heathens in the ſecond of the <hi>Romans,</hi> their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences did naturally accuſe, and excuſe, them upon the common principle of that light of nature imprinted on them, this is not juſt, this is not ſutable; though they had not ſuch written rules before them, yet there were ſuch dictates ſutable to the impreſſion that God left upon their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119912:88"/> conſciences, much more an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, an enlightened hypocrite under the Goſpell; but a naturall conſcience will tell a man really, and check him in a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſay, this never came from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, this motion of yours did not run freely in your ſpirits, this prayer was but pumpt, it comes not from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, you had ſome by-end or other; did you not aime at this or that, ſome applauſe or comfort to your ſelves, never minded Chriſt? Conſcience will ſpeake if you be not judicially hardned: it will ſpeake very loud to a man, at leaſt it will give a man ſuch checks as a man ſhall conſider, and by the cuſtome of it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is thus and thus with him: For looke as it is with the Saints under full light, and full evidence, ſo it is with a hypocrite under the enlightenings of his conſcience: ſaies <hi>Paul,</hi> I have lived in all good conſcience unto this day, that is, walked according to the principles of reaſon and Religion, according to the light I had, lived in all good conſcience unto this day, never ſtrained my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:119912:88"/>
            <p>Now it is impoſſible for a man under enlightening (if he have not a mighty ſecure frame of ſpirit, or wonderfull dexteritie of colouring his heart) but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall conſcience will reflect upon him, and ſay, this was not intended right though the action was done, this was not ſo ſpirituall, nor ſo firmely acted before God; you know you had your intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beſides the rule. But then</p>
            <p>Secondlie, Take ſuch a conſcience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Miniſtrie of the Goſpell, where there are Characters given on both ſides, where hearts are dealt withall ſeriouſlie, and with abundance of cleareneſſe, where the deſigne is to anatomize the ſpirit, to give characters of a Saint, and give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions between common graces, and thoſe graces that are purely ſanctifying, changing and transforming the ſoule, and thoſe that are common, and worke nor the image of God in the ſoule, if you have any light (as hypocrites have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of light, otherwiſe they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver play their tricks ſo as they do) it is impoſſible but the heart ſhould ſay, this is
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119912:89"/> not right, I find not this right in my own ſpirit; it is impoſſible they ſhould lye under theſe things and have no convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no checks ſecretly that he is truly ſuch an one.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He may by reflecting upon himſelfe know it by his getting in his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if he had nothing but that which he gets in duties, when he hears how Saints get communion with God in duties, how their ſoules are taken up with Chriſt, what glorious enjoyments they have of God, in Prayer, and Sacraments, what glorious frames they find upon their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits when they have communion, he knows he can hardly get from one duty to another; the truth is, a hypocrite is the pooreſt, miſerableſt ſoule in the world: he never hath any thing but what he gets from hand to mouth, when he comes to dye he is a begger, nothing at all to live on, and he knows he never met with Chriſt ſo as to humble him and to lay him low, he knows when he heares other Saints ſpeake of the Goſpell, and the ſweetneſſe they have had in the ſights
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119912:89"/> of Chriſt, pardoning and applying his love to them: he knows he hath not theſe things; when he comes to action he is as dead, and as low as may be; and as I told you, he is pooreſt and worſt at laſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthlie, <hi>God delights to diſcover a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, he delights in that exceedingly,</hi> and commonlie doth it, and laies it upon a man cloſely and wonderfullie by won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull flaſhes of ſpirit, and God delights to do it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Becauſe it is a ſecret that none can find out but himſelfe, therefore he delights to anatomize a wicked, cunning, deceitfull heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondlie, God he delights to do it, <hi>becauſe he loves to put a ſpeciall marke upon them of all perſons in the world,</hi> thoſe that have deceived others ſhall deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, he put a marke upon the firſt hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite in the world that ever was, that he changed his countenance, ſo that if you had no more, take them altogether and you ſhall find, that a man may very well be a hypocrite, and know himſelfe
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:119912:90"/> to be ſo, and yet go one; nay, it is very hard for a man to be long a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite under the Goſpell but he muſt lye under the checks of it. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, you will ſay, how can this be? How can he continue in Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in Churches? how can he continue all this while and not be terrified, and not leave off all profeſſion? My Brethren,</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, <hi>pray take in theſe things, know it is the moſt deluding ſin in the world, the moſt pleaſant ſin in the world to a man,</hi> as men love by Art to imitate nature, they are mighty pleaſed with it to repreſent Nature in Art, how men give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their ſtudies, and are pleaſed with it; there is nothing more pleaſing to a man as hypocriſie is, that he can turne himſelf at any time here and there, &amp; evade all things that are laid upon him by the Goſpell. (It is juſt as you ſee with thoſe that are your theeves or cut-purſes, that have a curious art and dexterity to do it; they will take a mans purſe out of his pocket ſo exactly, that he cannot know it is done, but they are gone, and when
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:119912:90"/> they come together at night, they rejoyce and brag who hath done the beſt feats,) ſo hypocrites cannot but know in their naturall conſciences it is againſt the rule, but there is abundance of pleaſure in it to cheat themſelves, and cheat others, till God worke mightilie upon them: for to imitate a Saint in every thing, and do it exactly, pleaſes a hypocrite, that he can delude others: when he hath been in prayer, coſened and deluded the beſt ſort of men in the world, as I have heard ſome ſay, they could delude all the Saints in the world, for that is pleaſing to a man that nouriſhes his ſelfe-love, and that does carry him on to act, ſo as to be well thought of by others, it ſhews a man an artificiall man that can thus and thus move up and down the world, and none ſee him, or take notice of him, all think him a bleſſed Saint; I am confident there is no ſin ſo pleaſing to a ſoule as hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is, for it will have ſo many varieties of Artificiall motions laid before it to act by, that a man is not tyed to one or tother, but ſtill acted in variety, and the ſence of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119912:91"/> divine things is not on his heart at all, as I ſhall ſhew you in the ſecond place.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>he may go on in profeſſion though he know himſelfe to be ſo;</hi> he may go on, becauſe he knows not the nature and vileneſſe of his ſin at all, only ſees he is not as he ſhould be, and it is the ſame with other ſins; he may lye long under a ſin, ſo long as Conſcience is not preſſed on with an unreſiſtible conviction, only a generall cold conviction is upon him; he ſees that he hath done ſo and ſo, and he is ſo and ſo, but there is not any thing of the power of conviction upon his ſoule, for then a ſoule ſhould not be able to ſtand under it, but cry out he cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it; but commonly it is with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie (ſuch a pleaſing ſin) as with other ſins; a man ſees the guilt by the rule, but not by the light of a divine conviction, ſtrangely working in his ſoule and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo goes on as thoſe did which the Prophet ſpeakes of, <hi>you lye, and ſteale, and commit adultery, and yet come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before me;</hi> they had brazen faces for all that, they never felt the power of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119912:91"/> conviction upon their ſpirits, and if God ſhould ſhew any man any one ſin, he would never act that ſin, but he would abhor the very ſights of it; But there are ſuch poore common generall convictions meerly from conſcience; conſcience hath a power within a man, but it never ſtirs with terrour till God anew, as it were, ſhews his ſin, and his miſerable eſtate by ſin, by a light from heaven, and ſo ſets conſcience afreſh a working; God then gives it a new Commiſſion to charge his ſoule, he goes to duty though he knows himſelfe full of hypocriſie, yet he can go to duty as quietly as can be; a man may know himſelfe to be a hypocrite and yet go on in it; becauſe</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>He thinkes he ſhall weare out his hypocriſie by his duties,</hi> though he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them in it, though he contract guilt by them: and moſt of his hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is in his duties, and that is exceeding ſtrange, but it is moſt true, for a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite thinkes by his duties to weare out all his deceits; as he colours his hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by it, ſo he hopes to weare it out by
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119912:92"/> it, he hopes it is a worke of time, though he have a bad heart yet he hopes to have a better heart, though he never looks to Chriſt for it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>He hath ſomething at preſent that he gets by his profeſſion,</hi> ſomething that is ſutable to ſome end, ſome luſt or other of his own, and that keeps him up, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe generall convictions; I know not how to call them convictions, they are ſo cold and poore upon a mans heart, but he hopes to get ſomething, either applauſe of men to be a good Chriſtian, or ſomething to be thought of by men, or to get ſome peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that the violence and deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wrath fall not upon him. Aye, but</p>
            <p>Fifthly, which is moſt of all, that I may ſhew you this; <hi>God doth judicially give up thoſe kind of hypocrites that have begun without him, tooke up profeſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any workings of God upon their ſoules, he gives them up commonly unto a reprobate mind,</hi> that you have ſo commonly named in the New Teſtament, ſo injudicious
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119912:92"/> as they cannot underſtand their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but go on ſtill, ſee no more in one condition than another; but that I may ſpeake of Gods dealing with hypocrites in this way.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As I told you, God delights to diſcover hypocrites, ſo <hi>he hath moſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them of any in the world, and he diſcovers them commonly,</hi> either</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>By ſome ſecret giving them up, or withdrawing ſtrength;</hi> giving them up to ſome corruption, or withdrawing ſtrength from them abſolutely, that they find nothing of former ſtrength at all: ſo he doth many times with thoſe that have lived upon parts, gifts, and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it is ordinary for God to leave them, as you have it in <hi>John</hi> 15. they wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the life and ſap that they were wont to have is withdrawn, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is gone, ſo it is with many; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that is the Reprobate mind; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away from the underſtanding that common light, that the ſoule ſhall only looke after the outward part of a duty, but never knew the life of it, never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119912:93"/> nor diſtinguiſhes when he is in a bad or a good condition. Oh! looke after the impreſſion and ſence of the things of God upon your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, The way that God takes to diſcover hypocrites, he gives them up to ſome eminent corruption to breake out as to diſcover them; as it was with <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> he had many gnawings of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doubtleſſe under Chriſts Miniſtry alwaies, and under Chriſts eye, but he was never diſcovered till he gave him up to that covetous heart, that wicked cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption that lay moſt in his heart, then he was diſcovered preſently, then thirty peeces of ſilver was enough for Jeſus Chriſt. Either God gives them up to deadneſſe, to be twiſe dead, that is, dead in their own hearts, the meaning is, they loſt both their naturall affections, and the affections they had on their hearts by common gifts and workings, they loſt both, and now nothing takes hold of them; or elſe he gives them up to ſome eminent corruption, that all the world ſees there is one never minded the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:119912:93"/> now it is broke out; or elſe</p>
            <p>Secondlie, As to that head, <hi>God gives them up unto a deſpaire,</hi> which is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and that is twofold:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Either ſecret deſpaire,</hi> they tug in duties, may by night and day, when they are preſt in conſcience, and they get nothing, go to Sermons and they find no blowings of the Spirit, no breathings at all upon their hearts, and ſo grow into a ſecret deſpaire inſenſibly.</p>
            <p>Now there is a ſecret kind of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in Saints, but this ſoule goes on and never finds any thing of God or Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>There is a terrifying deſpaire</hi> which ſometimes God gives them up to, whereby they are terrified with the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deouſneſſe of the wrath of God, crying out they are damned, they are damned, and they never commonly get out of it: you never heare of any hypocrite in the Scripture that ever got out when God laid a charge upon him; becauſe God would have ſoules walke ſo purely and clearely with him in all their duties.</p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:119912:94"/>
            <p>Now as you ſee how he may know himſelfe to be ſo, to be thus, and yet act; ſo ſee the nature of his hypocriſie; and take it in ſhort.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>though he know himſelfe to be a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and to be unſound, yet he is loath to have it ſaid ſo, or have it diſcovered, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide that,</hi> he would not have any one thinke ſo, though he knows it himſelfe, but yet would walke ſo exactly as he could; ſo it was with <hi>Balaam, Num.</hi> 21.22, 23. all along how gladly would he have gone to curſe the Iſraelites? but God would not ſuffer him: though he knew he was a moſt wicked notorious hypocrite, and a witch too, yet how would he pretend to <hi>Balack</hi> he would go to God; he would gladly have done it, but God had a mighty check upon him: it was a Propheſie to all the world, how all dealings with Saints ſhould be, though he ſpoke good things, and he could not but ſpeake them, yet he would gladly avoid them for the money, and ſtill he had an over-awing of God upon him: So it is with many hypocrites, though
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119912:94"/> they know themſelves to be unſound at the heart and bottome, yet they would have all thinke well of them, what they want of integritie that they would make up in the handſomneſſe of their deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and cariage up and downe the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Though he know himſelfe to be an hypocrite, yet there is none will be more cenſorious of hypocriſie in others,</hi> even to poore Saints; but that is a common rule, he will be ſevere in the cenſuring of others, and he may thinke by that, that others may thinke him far from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Nay, what ſhall I ſay? in the third place know this, <hi>though he know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thus to be in that condition, yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtrives to root out the wickedneſſe of that frame out of his own heart, but to ſmother it, and cover it, and palliate it from the eyes of men ſome way or other,</hi> not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it in his own ſpirit, but ſmother it, ſo that it may looke Saint-like ſtill; but a gracious heart, as ſoone as it diſcovers hypocriſie, as he ſees the ſtraines of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:119912:95"/> in his heart, he looks to root it out as ſoone as it is diſcovered. But to ſpeake no more to that, let us now come to the application of it to all your hearts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If this be ſo: I beſeech you once againe to put your hearts upon the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration, and examination of your own eſtates; what are you? Now you looke well, come to heare, you are not in ſight ſo ugly, what are you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? Have you not ſtrange ſtraines of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie if you be not hypocrites? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you looke ſeriouſly to your own hearts: this is the end of all this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to put men ſeriouſlie upon the triall of their own ſpirits, that they may not be unſound in the Goſpell, that they may not have a rotten ſpirit within, that the liver, and lungs, and heart be not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted whileſt they deale with the great things of the Goſpell; that is, that the faculties of the ſoule may be purelie acted to God; there are more hypocrites now in the world, than in any one Age ſince the Creation; it was a hard thing
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:119912:95"/> to pick out one formerlie; but God will ſhew many of them in theſe daies, he is a trying the world, and as he goes along he will try ſpirits moſt. Oh, you have trials under the Goſpell, have you got a cleareneſſe? Can you ſay you have a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inward freeneſſe with God? Oh, what uſe have you made of the Goſpell? Have you inward glorious incomes of God from the breathing in of divine frames in your actings towards God? Let me ask you but theſe common queſtions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Cannot you find ſome time to play with your ſins ſometimes, ſo they bite you not, and ſting you?</hi> Cannot you take ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creating times for your ſins and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Pray you conſider of it; a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite doth ſo: he dares not make a trade of it, but he will make a recreation of it now and then, he loves that he dares not practice, you can now and then play with your wanton thoughts as long as they do not fly in your face, you can delight your ſelfe in your ſecret wiſhes: Oh that I were at it; look to your own ſoules. Nay, what is this Religion that men
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:119912:96"/> ſpeake of? do you find ſuch kind of things in your hearts? he that can play with ſin for recreation can joine himſelf unto ſin for delight, and to be one nature with him: a Saint hates appearances, he cannot endure the thoughts of it.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, <hi>Are there not ſome ſins you call little ſins, and ſome duties you call little duties, and ſome duties that you never lay upon your conſcience?</hi> Look to your hearts in that, you are never humbled for the commiſſion of ſins, or the omiſſion of duties, it is a dangerous ſymptome of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. A hypocrite will be ſure to make diſtinctions in the Goſpell; there be ſome ſecret workings up of corruptions and ſins, as vanitie of thoughts, diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in duties, and ſecret riſings of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and deſires in a mans heart which he never chargeth his conſcience withall, and ſome duties he never laies upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſo long as he can paſſe thorough the maine body he never cares for the ſpeciall circumſtances of the Goſpell. A gracious and upright heart ſaies: Shall I call that little that is againſt the glorie
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:119912:96"/> of an infinite God? It is the object makes the ſin great, not the act: this dutie hath as much authority upon my heart though never ſo meane, though but to waſh a Saints feet, as to offer the greateſt ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices before the eyes of all the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let me aske you this, <hi>Are you not afraid of trialls, and to be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered to your own hearts?</hi> Do you not endeavour ſometimes, if poſſible, to evade the ſtrength of a conviction, and the ſtrength of a word from God that is laid upon your heart, afraid to looke into your own hearts and ſee your ſpirits, to be diſcovered to your ſelves? do not you many times huſh conſcience, and ſay, be quiet conſcience, ſtay a while to your own conſciences, I will be better, I will ſtrive againſt it, I will not be thus and thus carried away? do you not find theſe things? A dangerous ſymptome; a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite endeavours to evade the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Goſpell, he is afraid to abide the power and the glorie of it; if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find out prudentiall conſiderations enough, he will get ſpirituall pretences,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:119912:97"/> he will be ſure if he can evade convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he will do it, that is a very dangerous ſigne. And againe,</p>
            <p>Fourthlie, Examine your own hearts, <hi>Is there not ſome of the fat of the Cattle, of the ſheep,</hi> (to allude to that of <hi>Saul,</hi> for he was an hypocrite) <hi>in the going on in your duties, reſerved?</hi> Is there not ſome <hi>Agag</hi> for honors ſake you would keep up, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15 read over that place at your leiſure: God bids <hi>Saul</hi> ſlay the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> deſtroy them all in the third verſe, yet he reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an <hi>Agag,</hi> and the beſt of the ſpoile, here was the diſcoverie of his wicked heart, he would have ſacrificed ſome of the fat things, he had a mind to triumph by <hi>Agag:</hi> he thought it was too much to deſtroy all thoſe things, though God gave a peremptorie command to deſtroy all, I will ſacrifice them to God to make an attonement, only reſerved ſome of the beſt to carrie to my people in triumph, that they may ſee the out-goings of God; that loſt him his Kingdom, and diſcovered his hypocriſie firſt of any act, he had a ſecret luſt to honour himſelfe by it; have
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:119912:97"/> you none of the fat of your corruptions? Have you never a luſt laid up? Is there never a corruption that your ſoules have countenanced, or do countenance?</p>
            <p>It is a dangerous ſigne of hypocriſie, if a man have any thing that the word of God ſaith is not the mind of God, that he reſerves in his heart without utter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. Well, look to it I beſeech you, and eſpeciallie look to that of the triall of your ſpirits, whether you can be willing to be tried, for you ſhall find a hypocrite will appeale to God and his conſcience, but he cannot endure to be tried by Saints, he will appeale to God if it be not ſo, yet he cannot endure to be put to it, to have his heart ript open. Nay, it is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to ſay, God knows my heart, but if you come to try his heart, and ſay, how can this grace ſtand with this corruption, he cannot endure that, he will hate the thoughts of it. And if you do try him him about his eſtate, you muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it with him, but you muſt take it for granted, elſe he will try your graces as well as you try his, and queſtion your
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:119912:98"/> ſtate as much as you his: And then if he be put to it at laſt, as to triall of his own ſpirit, he will ſave all with a whining confeſſion, and that is all you will get of him; therefore look to your ſelves as to theſe things.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I ſhould now have come to have preſt on the exhortation of the Lord Jeſus; beware of hypocriſie, you that are Chriſtians, you that are reall Saints ſhould beware of it, and ſo to all ſorts of profeſſours, take heed and beware of it, and ſhewed you theſe things. To have opened the nature of it, and the hideouſneſſe of it.</p>
            <p>And firſt from the danger of it to your ſoules, it is the moſt dangerous ſin you can have in your ſoules, and that, Firſt, becauſe <hi>it is the last reſerve, it is undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable,</hi> a man muſt ſearch as with a Candle that finds it out: as the Jews were to ſearch for the Leaven with a Candle, and then curſe all the reſt, it is a cloſe ſin: indeed there are ſome actings of it that are very groſſe; but as for ſpirituall ſecret hypocriſie in duties,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:119912:98"/> compare them with actings they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding cloſe and undiſcernable in the ſoules of men; a ſoule muſt dig very deep, and be very obſervant, and have a watch over his ſoule every moment if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he would trie his heart; it is ſo cloſe and ſo cunning, that a man will hardlie beleeve it is there, there is ſuch a hidden motion upon a man, that he cannot tell how it comes.</p>
            <p>Secondlie beware of it: <hi>It is infectious,</hi> it is a dangerous infectious ſpreading na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it will be over all the faculties on a ſudden: it will repreſent you all kind of glaſſes that can be poſſible; it can in the morning give you one glaſſe to looke in, at noone another glaſſe, and in the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one different from both; take one part of the Law you ſhall ſee your ſelves in it very faire, it ſpreads over all: it will, it may be, begin with your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and give you ſtrange ſights and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of God, then come in upon your affections upon a ſudden, and work them to this end, and to their end: it will kiſſe and kill at once; looke to it, for it
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:119912:99"/> is the moſt dangerous ſin of any in the world in a mans heart.</p>
            <p>For if the ſoundneſſe be gone from a mans heart, what will he do then? A man cannot act like a man when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſoule is gone, he cannot act, neither Scripture, reaſon, nor his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but a particular cloſe humour.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, beware of it: <hi>It is the most inconſtant in its motions, the moſt various in its repreſentations, ſo many habits, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny formes</hi> it will appeare in to you, and alter upon every occaſion, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, unleſſe a man be given up to try his own heart, to find it out: A heart, and a heart: you ſhall have a faire heart now, and a wicked heart anon: come and talke with a Perſon now, and you ſhall find them in a good frame, ſo as if they were commanded by the power of of it, come an houre after, and you ſhall find them in a wicked damnable ſtraine of ſpirit, ſpeaking like mad men, this is moſt common: eſpeciallie come to talke with a man privately, what abundance of ingenuitie there is: come to another
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:119912:99"/> action, and at another time, and he is not the ſame man, hypocriſie will appeare, and this is the miſery mens ſoules are juggled to hell, put in ſo many formes, they know not when they are right, know not what is the reall complexion they ſhould have in the Goſpell, it is ſo various and ſo cunning: it juggles a mans ſoule to hell.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>It is the moſt odious thing to God of any, it takes his name in vaine moſt of any,</hi> it is againſt his ſimplicitie, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſciencie, his puritie, God hates nothing more than this ſtate, therefore he ſets himſelfe againſt hypocrites of all ſorts of people in the world.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have come to have ſhewed you how to avoid it, what are the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all remedies of hypocriſie, the ſpeciall things to keep a man from the evill of it, the way to preſerve a man from this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſin: but I would not leave ſome poore ſoules without ſome kind of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; all this while many will ſay, Alas, I am the man: I am the woman: cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlie I have been a hypocrite all my
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:119912:100"/> daies: I would only ſpeake a little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to ſuch poore ſoules.</p>
            <p>Firſt, know this: <hi>Jealouſie of thine own heart, and ſevere inquiſition into it, is a good hopefull Character that thou art far off that condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a twofold jealouſie that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you may not be deceived.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>A jealouſie on probable grounds, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and cloſe ſymptomes, and hints from actings,</hi> which may teach many a ſoule that hypocriſie may have place in his heart; for I find this and that when I come to looke on the whole ſtraine of my life, I have not my heart ſo carried out in ſpirituall things: I never minded this and that in my actings: this is a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie that may conſiſt with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, there is <hi>a jealouſie that ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from feare and care leſt I ſhould be ſuch an one, from the hatred of the thing:</hi> thou ſeeſt the vileneſſe of it, and thou ſeeſt thou canſt never be quiet till thou haſt the cleareneſſe of integritie made out to thee: that is good, that is ſweet: none
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:119912:100"/> more apt to cenſure a Saint than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; you know when Jeſus Chriſt made the queſtion about his betraying, the hypocrite ſpake laſt, never ſpake till he was put to it; every one ſaid at the Supper, Lord is it I? Is it I? Every one had rather dye than heare that word ſpoken; but when it comes to <hi>Judas,</hi> he was forced to it at laſt, and yet he would not confeſſe it; but when the conviction lay upon him, and he muſt needs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, then he went out, and that was all you heard of him till he hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, To comfort poore ſoules, <hi>they have no reaſon to conclude themſelves hypocrites, when they are glad if God by any meanes diſcover and deſtroy their hypocriſie whatever way it be:</hi> for there lies the weight when God ſhall be bleſſed for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering a mans heart to him: take this for a rule; If a ſoule can rejoyce and bleſſe God for his convictions of ſin, as for his comforts after conviction it is a ſigne of a moſt bleſſed glorious ſpirit; though the ſight of hypocriſie be the ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:119912:101"/> ſight in the world, yet when he ſees it he bleſſeth God for it.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, <hi>Never thinke thou art an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, if thy heart is ſet againſt the nature of ſin, and purſueſt the enjoyment, of the nature of God,</hi> whileſt thy heart is ſet againſt the nature of ſin, and followeſt on the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, that is, to be really poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a ſubſtantiall enjoyment of God, when the very nature of ſin is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy heart, and when the nature of godlineſſe is in thine eye as to enjoyment, to be fully poſſeſſed with that.</p>
            <p>Fourthlie, know this too: <hi>Never ſay thou art a hypocrite when no outward act can content thee, though never ſo glorious, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thou haſt an inward frame according to that act,</hi> according to the inward ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie of the Goſpell, if thou lookeſt to have thy ſoule in a frame to thy duty, thou needeſt not feare hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>While thy ſoule is as much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for omiſſion of thy duty as for commiſſion of thy ſin, thou needeſt not feare that thou art a hypocrite,</hi> while thy ſoule is as much troubled for omiſſion of a duty, or
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:119912:101"/> an act of faith, or cloſing with Chriſt, or of any outward duty wherein thou haſt enjoyed Chriſt, as for commiſſion of ſin, thou needeſt not feare thou art a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.</p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, <hi>thou needeſt not feare thou art a hypocrite whilſt thou hateſt thine own ſtrength in thy duties as much as an outward act of ſin, or the moſt diſtemper of thy ſpirit,</hi> or a corruption done in the wickedneſſe of thy heart; I ſpeake on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this a little to divert the thoughts of poore ſoules that ſay, I am certainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this frame of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But looke to your own hearts every one, if you find all theſe, or any of them in any life upon your ſoules, you are free from that ſtate; but if you find not ſuch an univerſall oppoſite nature to ſin, but a frame to ſin againſt God, if you find not ſuch conſtant pure frames in your owne ſpirits as to principles, intentions, and ends, you will never be able to free your ſelves from ſuch a ſtate and condition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="sermon">
            <pb n="184" facs="tcp:119912:102"/>
            <head>SERMON VII.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LUKE 12.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, which is Hypocriſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have endeavoured in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny exerciſes to open to you the nature of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and have told you the ſorts of hypocrites that are up and down the world, and in Churches: Now in the latter daies they grow more glorious than ever, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts exhortation had need be more preſſing; formerlie hypocriſie was courſely cloathed, could hardlie ſtep out among the Saints, they were ſo prying, and ſo cunninglie carefull to obſerve the dangers of the Devill in times of danger and perſecution: Now when the Sun ſhines, faire daies againe, Religion ſeems
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:119912:102"/> to flouriſh in the outſide of it, and there is a benefit, by the name of it, men will be very glorious in hypocriſie: and if ever there were need to preſſe Chriſts exhortation, it is now upon all ſorts of men and profeſſours: among his owne diſciples there was one among twelve, he bids them beware, <hi>take heed:</hi> It is a good caution for them all, Saints are ſubject to the ſtraines of it many times, without they have an abundant care in their own ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Therefore that I ſhall do, is ſtill to preſſe this exhortation upon your hearts, that it may take ſome weight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: for beleeve it, however you looke upon your ſelves, or whatever thoughts others have of you, we had need to tell you to beware of hypocriſie, the better you are thought of, the more danger. And you may remember the laſt time, firſt I told you, you had need to looke to your own ſpirits concerning this ſin, becauſe of the danger of it in its nature and workings.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, becauſe of the uglineſſe, and
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:119912:103"/> vileneſſe of it, of all other ſins in the ſoule how it is that which is perfectlie againſt the nature of God, his holineſſe and ſimplicitie, his faithfulneſſe and realitie to the Sons of men, how it is that that makes a man like the devill moſt of any ſin: he will beleeve, and is convinced of the things that the Goſpell ſpeakes of that they are true: but here lies the greatneſſe of his wickedneſſe, the cunningneſſe of his deceit, that he ſets up an art of deceiving in the world, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sons of men that they ſhould not beleeve the word of God; there is none like the devill, ſo perfectlie like the devill as hypocrites, <hi>I have choſen you twelve, and one of you is a devill,</hi> none is called a devill in Scripture but he: and there lies the ſutableneſſe that he is a lyar, and hypocriſie is a perfect lye in the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Then I ſhewed you the uglineſſe of it likewiſe, that it doth indiſpoſe the ſoule to every thing that is good, when one is in the beſt frame, as it were, that ſpoiles all, it is of a poyſonous nature.</p>
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:119912:103"/>
            <p>I ſhall go on to ſhew you what is that you muſt continuallie look after if you meane to beware of it, and prevent it, as the care and remedie of this ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Therefore firſt, as to the generall, and as the maine thing, if ever you meane to beware of hypocriſie <hi>you muſt principle your hearts, and farniſh them with all the graces of the ſpirit,</hi> you will never be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere elſe, you will never be ſincere till you have all graces, and the workings of them proportionable in your ſoules and ſpirits, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. he begs of them to go on, and <hi>this I pray that your love may abound more and more in all knowledge, and in all experience, that you may be able to approve the things that are excellent, that you may be ſincere, Phil.</hi> 1.9. A man muſt have all judgement, a diſcerning eye, for ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, doth not lye only in the intentions of men, but in the reall workings of all the frames of the ſoule, of all the graces as they are in the heart, when a man can approve the things that are excellent, that is, he can judge them, and try them, and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:119912:104"/> act them as they are diſcovered to be truths, that is ſinceritie: for ſinceritie is not ſo much a diſtinct grace as a reſult of the harmonious workings of all graces in the ſoule, there muſt be a rectified mind to make a man ſincere, for it is not a good intention that will make an action good, or make you ſincere in any action, but as it flows from inward reall frames and principles that are ſutable; <hi>Peter</hi> was an affectionate man, and he ſaid to Chriſt when he told him of his ſufferings, ſpare thy ſelfe, do not go and ſuffer, he did it out of a good intention, but he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked for it, he had a cleare intention, would not have the leaſt hurt come to Chriſt, but it was againſt the deſigne that Jeſus Chriſt came about, therefore he ſaid, <hi>get thee behind me Sathan:</hi> It was not that ſincerity, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, that you may be ſincere: Oh that ſincerity of ſoule! it lies in thoſe two things; that you may be ſincere, you muſt be able to judge and approve things that are excellent.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it ſignifies <hi>ſuch a ſtraine
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:119912:104"/> as is without any mixture, hath no compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any forraigne thing in it,</hi> when every thing is pure in its native colour, you muſt prove all things, be able to try all things, and have a judgement of them: that you may be ſo unmixt in your act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that you may have nothing at all of the corruption of the world in it; for we commonlie in our duties mixe our owne ends, and our own intereſts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements in the things of God, and whatever the intentions be, yet if there be any ſuch mixtures, you are not ſincere; though you may thinke you do well, and are very exact in the Goſpell, yet you cannot be ſincere whileſt there is ſuch a mixture in your principles and ends, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. A man is not ſincere when there are any mixtures, when a man is carried on by inward motions of ſin: Now, I confeſſe, there will be many mixtures, but there are mixtures in intentions, and mixtures in principles, and ends: and theſe are dangerous, for a man cannot be ſincere if theſe be predominant over him. As if I go to God, if it be not to glorifie
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:119912:105"/> God, and to have communion with him, having the higheſt end, and do not act from a ſpirituall principle of holy love to him, and his glorie, if I have any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in my intentions, though other things may come in accidentallie, yet if they be incorporated in the principle, then I am not ſincere.</p>
            <p>For to make up that ſinceritie, a man muſt have that ſpirit of ſinceritie that is pure to act from God to God, from the Spirit unto Chriſt. Now here is a pure way of acting, when the ſoule ſees what its own ſtrength is, caſts it out, lies at Chriſts feet, is carried out by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Gods ſpirit, will not have any thing but the ſtrength of Chriſt, when the intentions goe along together with the acting of theſe things, when there is a pure intention, that I fix but my eye whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on one object, for there be many conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations that come in accidentally, but the eye is fixt upon one object; I muſt have Chriſt, and my ſoule is working after him, and there I center my heart, that is ſinceritie indeed, ſo we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:119912:105"/> the ſincere milke of the word, that is, that milke that is unmixt with the corruption of men, the ſincere milke, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. therefore looke to your owne hearts, if ever you meane to avoid hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, you muſt be ſure that you keep from mixtures, mixtures of unſound principles, and ends, ſelfe-love, ſelfe-ends, take heed of the aire of the world, left that come in and fill your ſailes in your duties; take heed of any thing that may mixe with your principles, &amp; your ends; for in acting towards God, you cannot act purelie, but you muſt act from ſingle and entire principles in your hearts, and cleare apprehenſions of the object, and the end: And however you may conceive you act evenlie, and your heart is not feigning to be ſo in a duty; yet if you be not carried out in ſuch a heavenly harmony of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and inclinations, and your ends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, you will never be found to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, the word ſignifies <hi>that clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that perſpicuity that ſhould be in a mans ſoule in all his actings:</hi> ſo ſaith the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:119912:106"/> Apoſtle, that you may be ſincere, the word ſignifies ſuch a cleareneſſe, as when a man is under the judgement of the Sun, as under the Sun ſhining on a mans ſpirit, you will hardly avoid hypocriſie till your conſciences be under a light, and a brightneſſe of the glory of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings upon your hearts: for when your conſcience lies under darkneſſe and guilt as to the teſtimony it ſhould give, you will ſtill have ſhiftings off of hypocriſie from your ſpirits, to take off the weight and miſery off from you; but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would have you to be ſo cleare in your judgement of the Goſpell, as if you were to be judged by the Sun it ſelfe, it ſhould be found that there is nothing but ſinceritie: a faire teſtimonie in everie dutie, that inward whiteneſſe of a mans ſpirit in a duties, that it is not mixed with any bribings from without, nor ſecret evaſions from within. And that ſhining from the conſcience is ſo bright, that as the Apoſtle ſaith, this is the teſtimonie that we have, the teſtimonie of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: A man ſhould be ſo cleare in
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:119912:106"/> his own ſpirit if he meant to avoid hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie that if he were to be brought out to be judged before men and Angels, he might have ſuch an inward brightneſſe in his own ſpirit, that he might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and refreſhed in the ſight of it.</p>
            <p>For you find this commonly, take hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites in the time of convictions, they have no teſtimonie of God at all: Now take a ſincere heart, though he be under conviction, yet there is ſuch a light that he judgeth there is ſinceritie in his own heart, convince but a hypocrite of one thing he can give no account of the other: all comes in upon him, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth him, for he hath no brightneſſe within that will teſtifie to his ſoule at a dead lift; when conſcience accuſeth, he hath nothing to excuſe in his conſcience from the cleareneſſe of the acting of true principles in him: I beſeech you, if ever you meane to avoid hypocriſie, be ſincere, and if you will get ſinceritie, you muſt get all theſe graces clearelie ſhining and working in your owne ſpirits, for you will be put hard to it to get ſinceritie
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:119912:107"/> while your principles are darke and not even; if you find not your principles and ends meet together, and your eye is ſingly ſet upon the Lord Jeſus, and your hearts ſet for the glory of God, you will not have that inward plainneſſe in your own hearts. Though the nature of ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie lies much as to theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the clearneſſe of a mans princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and unmixtneſſe in them.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, a plainneſſe and ingenuitie in the actings of them; from theſe two flows that which we call that ſinceritie of ſpirit: To be free from ſembling, and faigning of things, when I am not mixt, when I am without impuritie in my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as to what I act: though there be hypocriſie in ſome other things, yet there is not in thoſe maine things. So that the firſt thing I would commend unto you, if you would avoid hypocriſie, is to furniſh your ſelves with all ſpirituall graces of ſinceritie, that you may be juſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun, that as they ſay of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, they try their young ones by the Sun, if they can endure the ſight of the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:119912:107"/> Sun they are then true: ſo you, if theſe things will endure the Sun, and the light of God, then you may ſay you act ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerelie.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, if you would avoid hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, <hi>lye alwaies under the dread of an omniſcient eye,</hi> this is that that men are diſcovered hypocrites by: they know not what the ſights of God are, that all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing God, if I thought God did looke into my heart, and did ſee me, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible I ſhould then go on in a way of ſin and deceit to deceive my own ſoule, for to deceive the omniſcient God: Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites thinke in the generall that God ſees all things, but they lye not under the dread and aw of an omniſcient God, no grace keeps a ſoule ſo much from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie as the feare of God, the awe and dread of God ſeeing into a mans heart; for though thy heart be cloſe to others, it is tranſparent to God, he ſees all the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy ſpirit, and veines of thy ſoule, how thou doſt delude thy owne heart, therefore if thou wouldſt be ſound, looke after that, the feare and dread of God:
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:119912:108"/> Remember, what is it for me to be well thought of by others when God ſees it not ſo, the omniſcient eye knows I have a ſecret cunning heart for to deceive? He ſees me, though I ſpeake faire to this and that perſon yet God knows I am wrong, he knows I am lying when I ſpeake a word, though others know it not: Oh, if the eye of God were but thought of by men, if we thought we had a divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with us, <hi>Whither ſhall I go? if I go to heaven thou art there,</hi> Pſal. 139. if a ſoule were under this conſideration, whither ſhall I go from thy preſence? I may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie this ſin cloſelie and ſecretlie, yet the eye of God is upon me, the Lord ſees me: I had better all the world ſhould ſee me than God, for he diſcovers me from the bottome: ſo much for that.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, If ever you meane to avoid hypocriſie in your own ſpirits, <hi>be alwaies conſidering the vanitie of this ſin of all other ſins:</hi> A ſin which there is no profit in at all: A hypocrite takes as much paines for all his cunning deceits as a Saint for all his ſinceritie; for a man to act as a
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:119912:108"/> King upon a Royall Stage, and the next moment he is in Rags, not a bit of bread, ſo here, a hypocrite, take him out of his duties, hath nothing to live upon but what they ſhirke up and down the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell for, and that is ſo miſerable and ſo poore a life, that they would give over the waies of Religion, if it were not for ſhame; and when a man conſiders old age is comming on, there is a day of darkneſſe, a midnight houre that muſt be upon my ſoule, God will one day take off all this diſguiſe, I am well thought of by others now, but what ſhall I be then, there is a night up on me, but there is a day upon others, and that which is the day of the Lord to others will be a midnight to me, and that will be the time of the diſcoverie of me to be miſerable. Better a man had never gone on in ſuch a hood, and have it plucked off, and to ſee ſuch an ugly face: Oh, what hideous cries will one day be! Oh, that I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made uſe of the name of Chriſt! Oh, that I had been through with my owne ſpirit, that I had never deceived my own
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:119912:109"/> ſoule, that I had known what my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had been before I played with the Goſpell, and dallied with the things of Chriſt; I beſeech you conſider, to be cloathed in darkneſſe after you have ſeemed to be cloathed with the brighteſt notions of the Goſpell, it is a vaine thing, a man gets nothing at all, lives upon the aire, what men ſay of him, the good thoughts, and good words of men, there is all, for he hath nothing from Chriſt as to the enjoyments of the Goſpell in his own ſpirit, and is not that ſad? Againe,</p>
            <p>Fourthlie, Looke to beware of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, <hi>for it is a dangerous thing if it go on to a height,</hi> hypocrites are ſeldome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted under the Goſpell, the reaſon is, they weare out all thoſe principles they knew, they curſe themſelves under the Goſpell, they have heard over and over againe the ſame things, and they make little of them in their own ſpirits; God ſeldome converts them, only that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction that is commonlie upon theſe that are hypocrites, is to ſhow them their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie to be their miſerie, whereas to
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:119912:109"/> others the time of their conviction is the time of their converſion: When God comes to profane men and ſtrikes them home, it is commonlie to convert them, but as to a hypocrite, it is Gods time to ſhew him his hell and miſery, and how he hath out-run his glaſſe, and paſt the day of the Goſpell: <hi>Oh that thou hadſt known in this thy day the things of thy peace, but now they are hid from thine eyes:</hi> God loves to make ſuch perſons examples to the world, if they get a breath at the laſt day it is well. Therefore looke to it you that begin to be formall, and to play with your convictions, and take them off now and then, dallying with the Lord, looke to it, it is a thouſand to one if ever you be converted, that that converts others condemnes you: And tremble at this, that you ſhould live under Ordinances and diſcoveries every day, and yet be no better; if you eſcape long without through-improved convictions upon your hearts, it is a dangerous ſymptome, it is a thouſand to one God hath made but an eſſay upon thy heart. Where did
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:119912:110"/> you find that ever God convinced a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite up and down the Goſpell, that was a profeſt one, if you look through the whole Bible, but he left his marke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them all the daies of their lives? It is a dreadfull thing; yet grace is not bound up, it is not limited at all, it may be God may ſhew more riches of grace upon ſome ſoules, but it is not uſuall: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ever you would be ſcared from hypocriſie take heed of that; when a man comes to dye, and ſhould come at laſt to refreſh himſelfe with the thought that he hath ſerved God faithfullie, and ſincerelie, and finds no comforts of all his duties and enjoyments, then to be convinced that he hath been one that hath deceived himſelfe is very terrible, when he ſhould have God eternallie, then to have that time of times of his everlaſting ruine; God will take ſome time or other to diſcover your hearts, and it may be he will diſcover them and you ſhall not be better, only let the world know, and your owne hearts know what you have been, and leave a ſecret-deadneſſe for
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:119912:110"/> ever upon your hearts, or fry in the wrath of it all your daies, as you go up and downe the world, conſume you to nothing with the ſenſe of wrath; Oh prize a ſincere heart, and prize opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and take heed of puttings off, and delaying time, and being careleſſe of what you are about, for that is the trick of a hypocrite to put off, and thinke it will be better, and hug himſelfe with ſome conſiderations, that time will be otherwiſe, take heed: the day of the Lord will be a day of blackneſſe. And that you may be further ſet againſt the nature of this ſin: (for that is my deſign) I beſeech you conſider the hideous doom upon hypocrites, the laſt doome upon hypocrites: when Chriſt would ſpeake the uttermoſt of miſery, he ſaith, he will give them their portion with hypocrites, they ſhall burne in the hotteſt fire, they and the devils together ſhall be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the uttermoſt wrath, the ſubjects of the infinite wrath of God, they ſhall be moſt enlarged for wrath, for they are veſſels fitted for wrath, you know, as the
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:119912:111"/> Apoſtle ſpeakes, ſo prepared, ſo enlarged for wrath: ſo is the ſoule of a hypocrite that hath lived all his daies in darkneſſe, and blackneſſe, only reſtrained himſelfe as to outward acts: but he is fit for wrath, he hath laid in ſuch treaſures there, that he is every day treaſuring up wrath againſt the day of wrath, that he will be forced to take in the thoughts of wrath, becauſe he hath ſinned againſt the greateſt light, and opportunities, and advantages of the Goſpell: Oh, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that you would fright your ſelves out of hypocriſie, (if you can do nothing elſe) and formalitie, and mixt frames of your ſpirits; ſcare your hearts with the day of judgement, with the ſadneſſe of the doome, with the miſerie of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, If ever you meane to be free from hypocriſie, <hi>you muſt through with your ſpirits night and day, ſound them to the bottome,</hi> let your line be long, let it downe to the bottome of the well, give conſcience leave to ſpeake in the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of God every day upon your hearts:
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:119912:111"/> beg of God to try you, to ſearch you, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid: Go every day to God to ſearch you, and be glad, and beg of all the Saints to remember thee, for there is deceits of hypocriſie in every one of our hearts; never come off viewing of your ſpirits till you have diſcovered ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other: if ever you would be freed from hypocriſie you muſt do this; alwaies keep a narrow watch upon the ſecret parts, be not afraid to looke into your own hearts, but aske every motion what it comes from, whither it moves, try every thing in your own ſpirits; let not any motion go free unexamined in your ſoules, but have a ſevere cenſure of it; no dutie but have a jury on it; looke into the maine frame of your ſpirits: try your principles and intentions firſt, try your motions, obſerve your ends, and how you attaine them conſtantlie; if ever men would be ſincere and free of hypocriſie, they muſt be thus ſpirituallie ſevere to their owne ſoules: it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſeveritie, it is bleſſed; it is the ſleight common dealing with our ſpirits,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:119912:112"/> (that we are formall and cold) that makes ſo many deceits in mens hearts which lodges ſo ſecretlie within; we do not go to purpoſe with the ſearch of our own ſpirits, challenging our hearts in every dutie; we ought, I confeſſe, to be carefull how we queſtion the motions of grace in our hearts: But a watchfull Saint, if he will cleare himſelfe of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, muſt be eying, and prying into every thing that he doth: obſerve his ſetting out in his duties, the carriage and frames of his ſoule, obſerve the tune afterwards that he is in, for hypocriſie will get upon a ſudden into a mans heart, and a man will thinke himſelfe to be an hypocrite preſently if he be not thus ſtrict and wary; ſo that if you will lay all theſe to your hearts ſeriouſly, it may be a pretious meanes to keep you from the danger of this leaven, though it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for to cure it, but only as you grow in grace, and get ſound and ſincere principles in your hearts. So much for the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. However let it be a word of
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:119912:112"/> comfort unto ſome poore ſoules, that have all this while been harkening after hypocriſie, charging of their own hearts, for I would not let any ſoule go away but with ſome refreſhment. Some will ſay, I ſee ſo much hypocriſie in my own heart, that I cannot but thinke my ſelfe one that never had any grace, or ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in my own ſpirit: I know not what to do, or what to ſay to mine own heart; conſider, I ſay, theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, know, <hi>it is good for thee to have thy hypocriſie diſcovered,</hi> it is a mercy to thee, and a favour of God that he will ſhew thee thy inward parts, that he will diſcover the ſecrets of thy heart, whileſt he lets others go in that eſtate, and never knows what is within all the daies of their lives, only mind outward acts: this is ſo far from being a diſcouragement, that you ſhould bleſſe God for it, that he hath been pleaſed to ſhew thee thine own heart, the ſtraines of hypocriſie in a duty; God might have left thee to go on, and thought thy ſelfe what thou art not.</p>
            <pb n="206" facs="tcp:119912:113"/>
            <p>Secondlie, Remember, <hi>the more thou diſcovereſt the ſecret workings of hypocriſie, the more it is a ſigne thou groweſt in grace;</hi> for this is the great end of grace, as by the incomings of it to kill ſin, ſo for to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſin, and the ſecrets of it: the more ſpirituall any heart grows, the more he grows in the inward ſights of his own heart, the more he comes to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with thoſe ſpirituall kinds of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his own ſpirit: And be not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore troubled at that poore ſoule, for it is rather a ſigne of thy grace than hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, than of any other impulſe, becauſe God doth ſtill by degrees ſhew thee thy own heart, ſo long as thy heart is againſt it.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, be not diſcouraged by the ſights of hypocriſie <hi>as long as thou findeſt a ſincere heart from the diſcovery of it: that is, ſo long as thou lyeſt in wait from the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of thy heart to diſcover it, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bewailes it from the ſincerity of thy ſoule;</hi> know that it is a true ſigne of a ſincere heart, he lies in wait to diſcover his hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, he laies himſelfe in ſecret ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:119912:113"/> continually to ſpy out the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningneſſe and deceits of his own heart. For you ſhall find thoſe ſignes of a ſincere heart.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This will diſcover a ſincere heart, that I may comfort a poore ſoule, <hi>though he may have hypocriſie in him, yet he will be most impartiall to himſelfe from once he finds it out,</hi> it may be he will be charitable to others, yet he will be ſevere to himſelfe; if he find out any hypocriſie, he will be ſure to fall on it with all deteſtation, he will charge his own ſoule, as if it were the damned ſoule, he will rather lay too much weight upon his conſcience, lay it too ſevere on his own ſpirit, than any way excuſe himſelfe; but hypocrites will deale gently with themſelves, if they have not an excuſe at hand, they will not lay it home too much to heart: but a reall Saint will ſay, Oh, wretched man: Oh thou unworthy heart, that ſhould live ſo long, and have ſo many advantages to kill this luſt, and art thou alive yet? Thou ſhalt never eſcape more, I will follow thee night and day with prayers and
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:119912:114"/> teares, it will not ſay it is my infirmitie; it is my failing, but is will call himſelfe a wretched man, a heart, and a heart, therefore looke to your own ſoules as to that, and comfort your ſoules any poore heart of you, that though you find hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, yet you deale ſeverelie with it.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Character of a ſincere heart is, <hi>though he have hypocriſie in him, he is moſt jealous of hypocriſie:</hi> when he finds his heart moſt calme, and faire, ſeemes leaſt checkt in conſcience, hath moſt reſpect from others, oh then he is moſt jealous leſt there be ſome deceit, he is alwaies looking at bottome, alwaies afraid through a ſpirit of care and holy jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie within him, alwaies afraid leſt he be deceived, and when his heart ſeemes to be ſo calme, ſo faire, any body would thinke his ſoule to be in a bleſſed frame, and a man himſelfe can ſee nothing upon himſelfe at preſent as to preſent actings, yet then he is afraid of thoſe things that gives moſt advantage to the actings of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            <pb n="209" facs="tcp:119912:114"/>
            <p>The third Character is, though he have hypocriſie in him, <hi>he loves to be throughly dealt withall, he counts the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his heart to be a pretious meanes of the ſaving of his poore ſoule:</hi> Oh how glad is he to ſee his own heart, and his hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſo he may but find it out to kill it, and go to God againſt it, making it the burden and mourning of his ſoule, he loves to find it out, he cannot abide any pleaſing words to him, unleſſe Chriſt ſpeakes them, he cannot endure, that though he have abundance of hypocriſie, it will not for all that give any counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to it, but earneſtly rejoyces to be throughly dealt with.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, <hi>though there may he hypocriſie, yet a ſincere heart will ſtand upon a true account, he cannot endure to have any one to commend his heart,</hi> he would not be accounted more than he is, he loves to be aſhamed, he cannot abide others to advance him in their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of his heart, that he ſees ſo much hypocriſie in: ſo that I ſay, let this be a comfort to you if you have no more.</p>
            <pb n="210" facs="tcp:119912:115"/>
            <p>But as to the ſincerity of your heart, that you would deale with your ſelfe, and would have a ſpirituall inſpection with feare and jealouſie alwaies, that you may ſtand upon a true account ſtill, that you cannot endure any body ſhould commend your heart. There is no Saint but he knows his heart to be the worſt part, he ſees ſo much wickedneſſe there, that he wonders how others can thinke well of him, he cannot abide that any one ſhould conceive he hath ſuch a heart that he mournes under night and day.</p>
            <p>So that I ſay, lay all theſe things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and though thou doſt find ſome hypocriſie in thy heart, yet be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, go on ſtill to follow the rule of Chriſt, that when you find it you do not lye under it; for that will bring guilt, and will ſpread far, but comfort your ſelves ſtill that there is a ſeed, that you do real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find that you are purſuing continually growth, that is the conſtant ſtudy of you, that you may be perfectly ſincere, that all your frames may act ſo evenly with God, that there be no jarring at all, that
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:119912:115"/> your conſciences may be kept continually under the power of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>But to conclude all: I beſeech you looke to it, you that are Profeſſours, you have heard the nature of hypocriſie, you have heard what deceits there are in the hearts of men, you have heard the ſtrictneſſe of Chriſt to his own Diſciples, how preſſing he was upon them, now look to your own ſoules, try your ſelves by all theſe things, examine your hearts over and over againe, do not content your ſelves with this, that you have names in the world, that you have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of inward kinds of experience, for now hypocrites will be growing up in the flouriſhings of the Goſpell, they will have an imitation of faith, and of patience, and of joy, as the Goſpell ſhines forth brightly, they will have an imitation of adoption, it is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing to thinke how a Profeſſour will bring himſelfe into the faſhion of a moſt glorious Saint, transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into an Angell of light, as it were, ſtriving to imitate every thing, and yet
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:119912:116" rendition="simple:additions"/> enjoy nothing, is loath to have his name expunged out of glory, out of the hearts of Saints. But alas the Lord will come and ſhew himſelfe exceeding dreadfull to Profeſſours in the latter daies; there is a terrour will be upon you one day, that you have only walked up and down and no more, you have found no ſweetneſſe, you have only cozened your ſelves and others: Oh that is miſery enough for every poore ſoule, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what hath been ſaid, lay it home upon your conſciences, examine your hearts, commune with your own ſpirits in the night-ſeaſon, and remember there will be a day to diſcover the hearts of men, and you ſhall ſtand naked, uncloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, and God will ſet a marke on you to all eternity,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:116" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Reader, theſe Books following are Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Tomlins,</hi> at the Sun and Bible neare <hi>Pye-Corner.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe general Practice of Phyſick, Fol.</item>
               <item>The Fortune Booke in Fol. Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Pleaſant Notes upon <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> Fol.</item>
               <item>Mr <hi>Collings</hi> his Cordials, firſt, ſecond, and third parts, quarto.</item>
               <item>His <hi>Vindiciae Ministerii,</hi> quarto.</item>
               <item>His Anſwer to Mr <hi>Sheppard,</hi> quarto.</item>
               <item>His Anſwer to <hi>Fiſher</hi> and <hi>Hammond,</hi> quar.</item>
               <item>His Anſwer to <hi>Boatman, Priane,</hi> and <hi>Humfries,</hi> quarto.</item>
               <item>Dr <hi>Holdſworth's</hi> twenty one Serm. quarto</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Euclids</hi> Elements in quarto Eng.</item>
               <item>Hiſtory of ſeven Champions, quarto.</item>
               <item>Packet of Letters, quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cupids</hi> Meſſengers, quarto.</item>
               <item>The Birth of Mankind or Womens Book, quarto.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119912:117"/>
               <item>The Perfect Phariſee under Monkiſh holineſſe, quarto.</item>
               <item>The falſe Jew, quarto.</item>
               <item>Mr <hi>Collings</hi> Five Leſſons for a Chriſtian to learne, octavo.</item>
               <item>His Faith and experience, octavo.</item>
               <item>Mr <hi>Wincolls</hi> Poems, octavo.</item>
               <item>Excellency of Chriſt, octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eraſmus Colloquies,</hi> octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wings</hi> and <hi>Libourns Urania Practica,</hi> octav.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Velitationes Polemicae,</hi> octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> Catechiſme, octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Janua Linguarum,</hi> octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brinſley's Cordelius,</hi> octavo.</item>
               <item>Mr <hi>Sidenham's</hi> Myſtery of Godlineſs, oct.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Watſon's</hi> untaught Bridegroome, Twelves.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119912:117"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
